IX

Pseudo-Critics

A certain set of individuals calling themselves critics have attacked Lavengro with much virulence and malice. If what they call criticism had been founded on truth, the author would have had nothing to say. The book contains plenty of blemishes, some of them, by-the-bye, wilful ones, as the writer will presently show; not one of these, however, has been detected and pointed out; but the best passages in the book, indeed whatever was calculated to make the book valuable, have been assailed with abuse and misrepresentation. The duty of the true critic is to play the part of a leech, and not of a viper. Upon true and upon malignant criticism there is an excellent fable by the Spaniard Iriarte.[333] The viper says to the leech, “Why do people invite your bite, and flee from mine?” “Because,” says the leech, “people receive health from my bite, and poison from yours.” “There is as much difference,” says the clever Spaniard, “between true and malignant criticism, as between poison and medicine.” Certainly a great many meritorious writers have allowed themselves to be poisoned by malignant criticism; the writer, however, is not one of those who allow themselves to be poisoned by pseudo-critics; no! no! he will rather hold them up by their tails, and show the creatures wriggling, blood and foam streaming from their broken jaws. First of all, however, he will notice one of their objections. “The book isn’t true,” say they. Now one of the principal reasons with those who have attacked Lavengro for their abuse of it is, that it is particularly true in one instance, namely, that it exposes their own nonsense, their love of humbug, their slavishness, their dressings, their goings out, their scraping and bowing to great people; it is the showing up of “gentility nonsense” in Lavengro that has been one principal reason for the raising the above cry; for in Lavengro, is denounced the besetting folly of the English people, a folly which those who call themselves guardians of the public taste are far from being above. “We can’t abide anything that isn’t true!” they exclaim. Can’t they? Then why are they so enraptured with any fiction that is adapted to purposes of humbug, which tends to make them satisfied with their own proceedings, with their own nonsense, which does not tell them to reform, to become more alive to their own failings, and less sensitive about the tyrannical goings on of the masters, and the degraded condition, the sufferings, and the trials of the serfs in the star Jupiter? Had Lavengro, instead of being the work of an independent mind, been written in order to further any of the thousand and one cants, and species of nonsense prevalent in England, the author would have heard much less about its not being true, both from public detractors and private censurers.

“But Lavengro pretends to be an autobiography,” say the critics; and here the writer begs leave to observe, that it would be well for people who profess to have a regard for truth, not to exhibit in every assertion which they make a most profligate disregard of it; this assertion of theirs is a falsehood, and they know it to be a falsehood.[334] In the preface Lavengro is stated to be a dream; and the writer takes this opportunity of stating that he never said it was an autobiography; never authorised any person to say that it was one; and that he has in innumerable instances declared in public and private, both before and after the work was published, that it was not what is generally termed an autobiography: but a set of people who pretend to write criticisms on books, hating the author for various reasons—amongst others, because, having the proper pride of a gentleman and a scholar, he did not, in the year ’43, choose to permit himself to be exhibited and made a zany of in London, and especially because he will neither associate with, nor curry favour with, them who are neither gentlemen nor scholars—attack his book with abuse and calumny. He is, perhaps, condescending too much when he takes any notice of such people; as, however, the English public is wonderfully led by cries and shouts, and generally ready to take part against any person who is either unwilling or unable to defend himself, he deems it advisable not to be altogether quiet with those who assail him. The best way to deal with vipers is to tear out their teeth; and the best way to deal with pseudo-critics is to deprive them of their poison-bag, which is easily done by exposing their ignorance. The writer knew perfectly well the description of people with whom he would have to do, he therefore very quietly prepared a stratagem, by means of which he could at any time exhibit them, powerless and helpless, in his hand. Critics, when they review books, ought to have a competent knowledge of the subjects which those books discuss.

Lavengro is a philological book, a poem if you choose to call it so. Now what a fine triumph it would have been for those who wished to vilify the book and its author, provided they could have detected the latter tripping in his philology—they might have instantly said that he was an ignorant pretender to philology—they laughed at the idea of his taking up a viper by its tail, a trick which hundreds of country urchins do every September, but they were silent about the really wonderful part of the book, the philological matter—they thought philology was his stronghold, and that it would be useless to attack him there; they of course would give him no credit as a philologist, for anything like fair treatment towards him was not to be expected at their hands, but they were afraid to attack his philology—yet that was the point, and the only point in which they might have attacked him successfully; he was vulnerable there. How was this? Why, in order to have an opportunity of holding up pseudo-critics by the tails, he wilfully spelt various foreign words wrong—Welsh words, and even Italian words—did they detect these misspellings? not one of them, even as he knew they would not, and he now taunts them with ignorance; and the power of taunting them with ignorance is the punishment which he designed for them—a power which they might but for their ignorance have used against him. The writer besides knowing something of Italian and Welsh, knows a little of Armenian language and literature; but who knowing anything of the Armenian language, unless he had an end in view, would say, that the word for sea in Armenian is anything like the word tide in English? The word for sea in Armenian is dzow, a word connected with the Tibetian word for water, and the Chinese shuy, and the Turkish su, signifying the same thing; but where is the resemblance between dzow and tide? Again, the word for bread in ancient Armenian is hats; yet the Armenian on London Bridge is made to say zhats, which is not the nominative of the Armenian noun for bread, but the accusative: now, critics, ravening against a man because he is a gentleman and a scholar, and has not only the power but also the courage to write original works, why did not you discover that weak point? Why, because you were ignorant, so here ye are held up! Moreover, who with a name commencing with Z, ever wrote fables in Armenian? There are two writers of fables in Armenian—Varthan and Koscht, and illustrious writers they are, one in the simple, and the other in the ornate style of Armenian composition, but neither of their names begins with a Z. Oh, what a precious opportunity ye lost, ye ravening crew, of convicting the poor, half-starved, friendless boy of the book, of ignorance or misrepresentation, by asking who with a name beginning with Z ever wrote fables in Armenian; but ye couldn’t help yourselves, ye are duncie. “We duncie!” Ay, duncie. So here ye are held up by the tails, blood and foam streaming from your jaws.

The writer wishes to ask here, what do you think of all this, Messieurs les Critiques? Were ye ever served so before? But don’t you richly deserve it? Haven’t you been for years past bullying and insulting everybody whom you deemed weak, and currying favour with everybody whom you thought strong? “We approve of this. We disapprove of that. Oh, this will never do. These are fine lines!” The lines perhaps some horrid sycophantic rubbish addressed to Wellington, or Lord So-and-so. To have your ignorance thus exposed, to be shown up in this manner, and by whom? A gypsy! Ay, a gypsy was the very right person to do it. But is it not galling, after all?

Ah, but we don’t understand Armenian, it cannot be expected that we should understand Armenian, or Welsh, or—. Hey, what’s this? The mighty we not understand Armenian or Welsh, or—. Then why does the mighty we pretend to review a book like Lavengro? From the arrogance with which it continually delivers itself, one would think that the mighty we is omniscient; that it understands every language; is versed in every literature; yet the mighty we does not even know the word for bread in Armenian. It knows bread well enough by name in English, and frequently bread in England only by its name, but the truth is, that the mighty we, with all its pretension, is in general a very sorry creature, who, instead of saying nous disons, should rather say nous dis: Parny in his Guerre des Dieux, very profanely makes the three in one say, Je faisons; now, Lavengro, who is anything but profane, would suggest that critics, especially magazine and Sunday newspaper critics, should commence with nous dis, as the first word would be significant of the conceit and assumption of the critic, and the second of the extent of the critic’s information. The we says its say, but when fawning sycophancy or vulgar abuse are taken from that say, what remains? Why a blank, a void, like Ginnungagap.[335]

As the writer, of his own accord, has exposed some of the blemishes of his book—a task, which a competent critic ought to have done—he will now point out two or three of its merits, which any critic, not altogether blinded with ignorance, might have done, or not replete with gall and envy would have been glad to do. The book has the merit of communicating a fact connected with physiology, which in all the pages of the multitude of books was never previously mentioned—the mysterious practice of touching objects to baffle the evil chance. The miserable detractor will, of course, instantly begin to rave about such a habit being common: well and good; but was it ever before described in print, or all connected with it dissected? He may then vociferate something about Johnson having touched: the writer cares not whether Johnson, who, by-the-bye, during the last twenty or thirty years, owing to people having become ultra Tory mad from reading Scott’s novels and the Quarterly Review, has been a mighty favourite, especially with some who were in the habit of calling him a half crazy old fool—touched, or whether he did or not; but he asks where did Johnson ever describe the feelings which induced him to perform the magic touch, even supposing that he did perform it? Again, the history gives an account of a certain book called the Sleeping Bard, the most remarkable prose work of the most difficult language but one, of modern Europe—a book, for a notice of which, he believes, one might turn over in vain the pages of any review printed in England, or, indeed, elsewhere. So here are two facts, one literary and the other physiological, for which any candid critic was bound to thank the author, even as in The Romany Rye there is a fact connected with Iro-Norman Myth, for the disclosing of which, any person who pretends to have a regard for literature is bound to thank him, namely, that the mysterious Finn or Fingal of Ossian’s Poems is one and the same person as the Sigurd Fafnisbane of the Edda and the Wilkina, and the Siegfried Horn of the Lay of the Niebelungs.

The writer might here conclude, and, he believes, most triumphantly; as, however, he is in the cue for writing, which he seldom is, he will for his own gratification, and for the sake of others, dropping metaphors about vipers and serpents, show up in particular two or three sets or cliques of people, who, he is happy to say, have been particularly virulent against him and his work, for nothing indeed could have given him greater mortification than their praise.

In the first place, he wishes to dispose of certain individuals who call themselves men of wit and fashion—about town—who he is told have abused his book “vaustly”—their own word. These people paint their cheeks, wear white kid gloves, and dabble in literature, or what they conceive to be literature. For abuse from such people, the writer was prepared. Does anyone imagine that the writer was not well aware, before he published his book, that, whenever he gave it to the world, he should be attacked by every literary coxcomb in England who had influence enough to procure the insertion of a scurrilous article in a magazine or newspaper! He has been in Spain, and has seen how invariably the mule attacks the horse; now why does the mule attack the horse? Why, because the latter carries about with him that which the envious hermaphrodite does not possess.

They consider, forsooth, that his book is low—but he is not going to waste words about them—one or two of whom, he is told, have written very duncie books about Spain, and are highly enraged with him, because certain books which he wrote about Spain were not considered duncie. No, he is not going to waste words upon them, for verily he dislikes their company, and so he’ll pass them by, and proceed to others.

The Scotch Charlie o’er the water people have been very loud in the abuse of Lavengro—this again might be expected; the sarcasms of the priest about the Charlie o’er the water nonsense of course stung them. Oh! it is one of the claims which Lavengro has to respect, that it is the first, if not the only work, in which that nonsense is, to a certain extent, exposed. Two or three of their remarks on passages of Lavengro, he will reproduce and laugh at. Of course your Charlie o’er the water people are genteel exceedingly, and cannot abide anything low. Gypsyism they think is particularly low, and the use of gypsy words in literature beneath its gentility; so they object to gypsy words being used in Lavengro where gypsies are introduced speaking—“What is Romany forsooth?” say they. Very good! And what is Scotch? has not the public been nauseated with Scotch for the last thirty years? “Ah, but Scotch is not”—the writer believes he knows much better than the Scotch what Scotch is and what it is not; he has told them before what it is: a very sorry jargon. He will now tell them what it is not—a sister or an immediate daughter of the Sanskrit, which Romany is. “Ay, but the Scotch are”—foxes, foxes, nothing else than foxes, even like the gypsies—the difference between the gypsy and Scotch fox being that the first is wild, with a mighty brush, the other a sneak with a gilt collar and without a tail.

A Charlie o’er the water person attempts to be witty, because the writer has said that perhaps a certain old Edinburgh High-School porter, of the name of Boee, was perhaps of the same blood as a certain Bui, a Northern Kemp who distinguished himself at the battle of Horinger Bay.[336] A pretty matter, forsooth, to excite the ridicule of a Scotchman! Why, is there a beggar or trumpery fellow in Scotland, who does not pretend to be somebody, or related to somebody? Is not every Scotchman descended from some king, kemp or cow-stealer of old, by his own account at least? Why, the writer would even go so far as to bet a trifle that the poor creature, who ridicules Boee’s supposed ancestry, has one of his own, at least as grand and as apocryphal as old Boee’s of the High School.

The same Charlie o’er the water person is mightily indignant that Lavengro should have spoken disrespectfully of William Wallace; Lavengro, when he speaks of that personage, being a child of about ten years old, and repeating merely what he had heard. All the Scotch, by-the-bye, for a great many years past, have been great admirers of William Wallace, particularly the Charlie o’er the water people, who in their nonsense-verses about Charlie generally contrive to bring in the name of William, Willie, or Wullie, Wallace. The writer begs leave to say that he by no means wishes to bear hard against William Wallace, but he cannot help asking why, if William, Willie, or Wullie, Wallace was such a particularly nice person, did his brother Scots betray him to a certain renowned southern warrior, called Edward Longshanks, who caused him to be hanged and cut into four in London, and his quarters to be placed over the gates of certain towns? They got gold, it is true, and titles, very nice things, no doubt; but, surely, the life of a patriot is better than all the gold and titles in the world—at least Lavengro thinks so—but Lavengro has lived more with gypsies than Scotchmen, and gypsies do not betray their brothers. It would be some time before a gypsy would hand over his brother to the harum-beck,[337] even supposing you would not only make him a king, but a justice of the peace, and not only give him the world, but the best farm on the Holkham estate;[338] but gypsies are wild foxes, and there is certainly a wonderful difference between the way of thinking of the wild fox who retains his brush, and that of the scurvy kennel creature who has lost his tail.

Ah! but thousands of Scotch, and particularly the Charlie o’er the water people, will say, “We didn’t sell Willie Wallace, it was our forbears who sold Willie Wallace—If Edward Longshanks had asked us to sell Wullie Wallace, we would soon have shown him that—” Lord better ye, ye poor trumpery set of creatures, ye would not have acted a bit better than your forefathers; remember how ye have ever treated the few amongst ye who, though born in the kennel, have shown something of the spirit of the wood. Many of ye are still alive who delivered over men, quite as honest and patriotic as William Wallace, into the hands of an English minister, to be chained and transported for merely venturing to speak and write in the cause of humanity, at the time when Europe was beginning to fling off the chains imposed by kings and priests. And it is not so very long since Burns, to whom ye are now building up obelisks rather higher than he deserves, was permitted by his countrymen to die in poverty and misery, because he would not join with them in songs of adulation to kings and the trumpery great. So say not that ye would have acted with respect to William Wallace one whit better than your fathers—and you in particular, ye children of Charlie, whom do ye write nonsense-verses about? A family of dastard despots, who did their best, during a century and more, to tread out the few sparks of independent feeling still glowing in Scotland—but enough has been said about ye.

Amongst those who have been prodigal in abuse and defamation of Lavengro, have been your modern Radicals, and particularly a set of people who filled the country with noise against the King and Queen, Wellington, and the Tories, in ’32. About these people the writer will presently have occasion to say a good deal, and also of real Radicals. As, however, it may be supposed that he is one of those who delight to play the sycophant to kings and queens, to curry favour with Tories, and to bepraise Wellington, he begs leave to state that such is not the case.

About kings and queens he has nothing to say; about Tories, simply that he believes them to be a bad set; about Wellington, however, it will be necessary for him to say a good deal, of mixed import, as he will subsequently frequently have occasion to mention him in connection with what he has to say about pseudo-Radicals.

X

Pseudo-Radicals

About Wellington, then, he says, that he believes him at the present day to be infinitely overrated. But there certainly was a time when he was shamefully underrated. Now what time was that? Why the time of pseudo-Radicalism, par excellence, from ’20 to ’32. Oh, the abuse that was heaped on Wellington by those who traded in Radical cant—your newspaper editors and review writers! and how he was sneered at then by your Whigs, and how faintly supported he was by your Tories, who were half ashamed of him; for your Tories, though capital fellows as followers, when you want nobody to back you, are the faintest creatures in the world when you cry in your agony, “Come and help me!” Oh, assuredly Wellington was infamously used at that time, especially by your traders in Radicalism, who howled at and hooted him; said he had every vice—was no general—was beaten at Waterloo—was a poltroon—moreover a poor illiterate creature, who could scarcely read or write; nay, a principal Radical paper said boldly he could not read, and devised an ingenious plan for teaching Wellington how to read. Now this was too bad; and the writer, being a lover of justice, frequently spoke up for Wellington, saying, that as for vice, he was not worse than his neighbours; that he was brave; that he won the fight at Waterloo, from a half-dead man, it is true, but that he did win it. Also, that he believed he had read Rules for the Manual and Platoon Exercises to some purpose; moreover, that he was sure he could write, for that he the writer had once written to Wellington, and had received an answer from him; nay, the writer once went so far as to strike a blow for Wellington; for the last time he used his fists was upon a Radical sub-editor, who was mobbing Wellington in the street, from behind a rank of grimy fellows. But though the writer spoke up for Wellington to a certain extent when he was shamefully underrated, and once struck a blow for him when he was about being hustled, he is not going to join in the loathsome sycophantic nonsense which it has been the fashion to use with respect to Wellington these last twenty years. Now what have those years been to England! Why the years of ultra-gentility, everybody in England having gone gentility mad during the last twenty years, and no people more so than your pseudo-Radicals. Wellington was turned out, and your Whigs and Radicals got in, and then commenced the period of ultra-gentility in England. The Whigs and Radicals only hated Wellington as long as the patronage of the country was in his hands, none of which they were tolerably sure he would bestow on them; but no sooner did they get it into their own, than they forthwith became admirers of Wellington. And why? Because he was a duke, petted at Windsor and by foreign princes, and a very genteel personage. Formerly many of your Whigs and Radicals had scarcely a decent coat on their backs; but now the plunder of the country was at their disposal, and they had as good a chance of being genteel as any people. So they were willing to worship Wellington because he was very genteel, and could not keep the plunder of the country out of their hands. And Wellington has been worshipped, and prettily so, during the last fifteen or twenty years. He is now a noble fine-hearted creature; the greatest general the world ever produced; the bravest of men; and—and—mercy upon us! the greatest of military writers! Now the present writer will not join in such sycophancy. As he was not afraid to take the part of Wellington when he was scurvily used by all parties, and when it was dangerous to take his part, so he is not afraid to speak the naked truth about Wellington in these days, when it is dangerous to say anything about him but what is sycophantically laudatory. He said in ’32, that as to vice, Wellington was not worse than his neighbours; but he is not going to say in ’54, that Wellington was a noble-hearted fellow; for he believes that a more cold-hearted individual never existed. His conduct to Warner, the poor Vaudois, and Marshal Ney, showed that. He said in ’32, that he was a good general and a brave man; but he is not going, in ’54, to say that he was the best general, or the bravest man, the world ever saw. England has produced a better general—France two or three—both countries many braver men. The son of the Norfolk clergyman was a brave man; Marshal Ney was a braver man. Oh, that battle of Copenhagen! Oh, that covering the retreat of the Grand Army! And though he said in ’32 that he could write, he is not going to say in ’54 that he is the best of all military writers. On the contrary, he does not hesitate to say that any Commentary of Julius Cæsar, or any chapter in Justinus, more especially the one about the Parthians, is worth the ten volumes of Wellington’s Despatches; though he has no doubt that, by saying so, he shall especially rouse the indignation of a certain newspaper, at present one of the most genteel journals imaginable—with a slight tendency to liberalism, it is true, but perfectly genteel—which is nevertheless the very one which, in ’32, swore bodily that Wellington could neither read nor write and devised an ingenious plan for teaching him how to read.

Now, after the above statement, no one will venture to say, if the writer should be disposed to bear hard upon Radicals, that he would be influenced by a desire to pay court to princes, or to curry favour with Tories, or from being a blind admirer of the Duke of Wellington; but the writer is not going to declaim against Radicals, that is, real Republicans, or their principles; upon the whole, he is something of an admirer of both. The writer has always had as much admiration for everything that is real and honest as he has had contempt for the opposite. Now real Republicanism is certainly a very fine thing, a much finer thing than Toryism, a system of common robbery, which is nevertheless far better than Whiggism [364]—a compound of petty larceny, popular instruction, and receiving of stolen goods. Yes, real Republicanism is certainly a very fine thing, and your real Radicals and Republicans are certainly very fine fellows, or rather were fine fellows, for the Lord only knows where to find them at the present day—the writer does not. If he did, he would at any time go five miles to invite one of them to dinner, even supposing that he had to go to a workhouse in order to find the person he wished to invite. Amongst the real Radicals of England, those who flourished from the year ’16 to ’20, there were certainly extraordinary characters, men partially insane, perhaps, but honest and brave—they did not make a market of the principles which they professed, and never intended to do so; they believed in them, and were willing to risk their lives in endeavouring to carry them out. The writer wishes to speak in particular of two of these men, both of whom perished on the scaffold—their names were Thistlewood and Ings. Thistlewood, the best known of them, was a brave soldier and had served with distinction as an officer in the French service; he was one of the excellent swordsmen of Europe; had fought several duels in France, where it is no child’s play to fight a duel; but had never unsheathed his sword for single combat, but in defence of the feeble and insulted—he was kind and open-hearted, but of too great simplicity; he had once ten thousand pounds left him, all of which he lent to a friend, who disappeared and never returned him a penny. Ings was an uneducated man, of very low stature, but amazing strength and resolution; he was a kind husband and father, and though a humble butcher, the name he bore was one of the royal names of the heathen Anglo-Saxons. These two men, along with five others, were executed, and their heads hacked off, for levying war against George the Fourth; the whole seven dying in a manner which extorted cheers from the populace, the most of them uttering philosophical or patriotic sayings. Thistlewood, who was, perhaps, the most calm and collected of all, just before he was turned off, said, “We are now going to discover the great secret”. Ings, the moment before he was choked, was singing “Scots wha hae wi’ Wallace bled.” Now there was no humbug about those men, nor about many more of the same time and of the same principles. They might be deluded about Republicanism, as Algernon Sidney was, and as Brutus was, but they were as honest and brave as either Brutus or Sidney, and as willing to die for their principles. But the Radicals who succeeded them were beings of a very different description; they jobbed and traded in Republicanism, and either parted with it, or at the present day are eager to part with it, for a consideration. In order to get the Whigs into power, and themselves places, they brought the country by their inflammatory language to the verge of a revolution, and were the cause that many perished on the scaffold; by their incendiary harangues and newspaper articles they caused the Bristol conflagration, for which six poor creatures were executed; they encouraged the mob to pillage, pull down and burn, and then rushing into garrets looked on. Thistlewood tells the mob the Tower is a second Bastile; let it be pulled down. A mob tries to pull down the Tower; but Thistlewood is at the head of that mob; he is not peeping from a garret on Tower Hill like Gulliver at Lisbon. Thistlewood and Ings say to twenty ragged individuals, Liverpool and Castlereagh are two satellites of despotism; it would be highly desirable to put them out of the way. And a certain number of ragged individuals are surprised in a stable in Cato Street, making preparations to put Castlereagh and Liverpool out of the way, and are fired upon with muskets by Grenadiers, and are hacked at with cutlasses by Bow Street runners; but the twain who encouraged those ragged individuals to meet in Cato Street are not far off, they are not on the other side of the river, in the Borough, for example, in some garret or obscure cellar. The very first to confront the Guards and runners are Thistlewood and Ings; Thistlewood whips his long thin rapier through Smithers’ lungs, and Ings makes a dash at Fitzclarence with his butcher’s knife. Oh, there was something in those fellows! honesty and courage; but can as much be said for the inciters of the troubles of ’32? No; they egged on poor ignorant mechanics and rustics, and got them hanged for pulling down and burning, whilst the highest pitch to which their own daring ever mounted was to mob Wellington as he passed in the streets.

Now, these people were humbugs, which Thistlewood and Ings were not. They raved and foamed against kings, queens, Wellington, the aristocracy, and what not, till they had got the Whigs into power, with whom they were in secret alliance, and with whom they afterwards openly joined in a system of robbery and corruption, more flagitious than the old Tory one, because there was more cant about it; for themselves they got consulships, commissionerships, and in some instances governments; for their sons clerkships in public offices; and there you may see those sons with the never-failing badge of the low scoundrel-puppy, the gilt chain at the waistcoat-pocket; and there you may hear and see them using the languishing tones, and employing the airs and graces which wenches use and employ, who, without being in the family way, wish to make their keepers believe that they are in the family way. Assuredly great is the cleverness of your Radicals of ’32, in providing for themselves and their families. Yet, clever as they are, there is one thing they cannot do—they get governments for themselves, commissionerships for their brothers, clerkships for their sons, but there is one thing beyond their craft—they cannot get husbands for their daughters, who, too ugly for marriage, and with their heads filled with the nonsense they have imbibed from gentility-novels, go over from Socinus to the Pope, becoming sisters in fusty convents, or having heard a few sermons in Mr. Platitude’s “chapelle,” seek for admission at the establishment of mother S—, who, after employing them for a time in various menial offices, and making them pluck off their eyebrows, hair by hair, generally dismisses them on the plea of sluttishness; whereupon they return to their papas to eat the bread of the country, with the comfortable prospect of eating it still in the shape of a pension after their sires are dead. Papa (ex uno disce omnes) living as quietly as he can; not exactly enviably, it is true, being now and then seen to cast an uneasy and furtive glance behind, even as an animal is wont, who has lost by some mischance a very sightly appendage; as quietly however as he can, and as dignifiedly, a great admirer of every genteel thing and genteel personage, the Duke in particular, whose Despatches, bound in red morocco, you will find on his table. A disliker of coarse expressions, and extremes of every kind, with a perfect horror for revolutions and attempts to revolutionise, exclaiming now and then, as a shriek escapes from whipped and bleeding Hungary, a groan from gasping Poland, and a half-stifled curse from down-trodden but scowling Italy, “Confound the revolutionary canaille, why can’t it be quiet!” in a word, putting one in mind of the parvenu in the Walpurgis Nacht. The writer is no admirer of Goethe, but the idea of that parvenu was certainly a good one—yes, putting one in mind of the individual who says:—

“Wir waren wahrlich auch nicht dumm,
Und thaten oft was wir nicht sollten;
Doch jetzo kehrt sich alles um und um,
Und eben da wir’s fest erhalten wollten.”

We were no fools, as every one discern’d,
And stopp’d at nought our projects in fulfilling;
But now the world seems topsy-turvy turn’d,
To keep it quiet just when we were willing.

Now, this class of individuals entertain a mortal hatred for Lavengro and its writer, and never lose an opportunity of vituperating both. It is true that such hatred is by no means surprising. There is certainly a great deal of difference between Lavengro and their own sons; the one thinking of independence and philology, whilst he is clinking away at kettles, and hammering horse-shoes in dingles; the others stuck up at public offices with gilt chains at their waistcoat-pockets, and giving themselves the airs and graces of females of a certain description. And there certainly is a great deal of difference between the author of Lavengro and themselves—he retaining his principles and his brush; they with scarlet breeches on, it is true, but without their republicanism and their tails. Oh, the writer can well afford to be vituperated by your pseudo-Radicals of ’32!

Some time ago the writer was set upon by an old Radical and his wife; but the matter is too rich not to require a chapter to itself.

XI

THE OLD RADICAL

“This very dirty man, with his very dirty face,
Would do any dirty act, which would get him a place.”

Some time ago the writer was set upon by an old Radical and his wife; but before he relates the manner in which they set upon him, it will be as well to enter upon a few particulars tending to elucidate their reasons for so doing.

The writer had just entered into his eighteenth year, when he met at the table of a certain Anglo-Germanist an individual, apparently somewhat under thirty, of middle stature, a thin and weaselly figure, a sallow complexion, a certain obliquity of vision, and a large pair of spectacles. This person, who had lately come from abroad, and had published a volume of translations, had attracted some slight notice in the literary world, and was looked upon as a kind of lion in a small provincial capital. After dinner he argued a great deal, spoke vehemently against the Church, and uttered the most desperate Radicalism that was perhaps ever heard, saying, he hoped that in a short time there would not be a king or queen in Europe, and inveighing bitterly against the English aristocracy, and against the Duke of Wellington in particular, whom he said, if he himself was ever president of an English republic—an event which he seemed to think by no means improbable—he would hang for certain infamous acts of profligacy and bloodshed which he had perpetrated in Spain. Being informed that the writer was something of a philologist, to which character the individual in question laid great pretensions, he came and sat down by him, and talked about languages and literature. The writer, who was only a boy, was a little frightened at first, but, not wishing to appear a child of absolute ignorance, he summoned what little learning he had, and began to blunder out something about the Celtic languages and their literature, and asked the Lion who he conceived Finn Ma Coul to be? and whether he did not consider the “Ode to the Fox,” by Red Rhys of Eryry, to be a masterpiece of pleasantry? Receiving no answer to these questions from the Lion, who, singular enough, would frequently, when the writer put a question to him, look across the table, and flatly contradict some one who was talking to some other person, the writer dropped the Celtic languages and literature, and asked him whether he did not think it a funny thing that Temugin, generally called Genghis Khan, should have married the daughter of Prester John? [369] The Lion, after giving a side-glance at the writer through his left spectacle glass, seemed about to reply, but was unfortunately prevented, being seized with an irresistible impulse to contradict a respectable doctor of medicine, who was engaged in conversation with the master of the house at the upper and farther end of the table, the writer being a poor ignorant lad, sitting of course at the bottom. The doctor, who had served in the Peninsula, having observed that Ferdinand the Seventh was not quite so bad as had been represented, the Lion vociferated that he was ten times worse, and that he hoped to see him and the Duke of Wellington hanged together. The doctor, who, being a Welshman, was somewhat of a warm temper, growing rather red, said that at any rate he had been informed that Ferdinand the Seventh knew sometimes how to behave himself like a gentleman—this brought on a long dispute, which terminated rather abruptly. The Lion having observed that the doctor must not talk about Spanish matters with one who had visited every part of Spain, the doctor bowed, and said he was right, for that he believed no people in general possessed such accurate information about countries as those who had travelled them as bagmen. On the Lion asking the doctor what he meant, the Welshman, whose under jaw began to move violently, replied, that he meant what he said. Here the matter ended, for the Lion turning from him, looked at the writer. The writer, imagining that his own conversation hitherto had been too trivial and common-place for the Lion to consider it worth his while to take much notice of it, determined to assume a little higher ground, and after repeating a few verses of the Koran, and gabbling a little Arabic, asked the Lion what he considered to be the difference between the Hegira and the Christian era, adding, that he thought the general computation was in error by about one year; and being a particularly modest person, chiefly, he believes, owing to his having been at school in Ireland, absolutely blushed at finding that the Lion returned not a word in answer. “What a wonderful individual I am seated by,” thought he, “to whom Arabic seems a vulgar speech, and a question about the Hegira not worthy of an answer!” not reflecting that as lions come from the Sahara, they have quite enough of Arabic at home, and that the question about the Hegira was rather mal à propos to one used to prey on the flesh of hadjis. “Now I only wish he would vouchsafe me a little of his learning,” thought the boy to himself, and in this wish he was at last gratified; for the Lion, after asking him whether he was acquainted at all with the Sclavonian languages, and being informed that he was not, absolutely dumb-foundered him by a display of Sclavonian erudition.

Years rolled by—the writer was a good deal about, sometimes in London, sometimes in the country, sometimes abroad; in London he occasionally met the man of the spectacles, who was always very civil to him, and, indeed, cultivated his acquaintance. The writer thought it rather odd that, after he himself had become acquainted with the Sclavonian languages and literature, the man of the spectacles talked little or nothing about them. In a little time, however, the matter ceased to cause him the slightest surprise, for he had discovered a key to the mystery. In the meantime the man of spectacles was busy enough; he speculated in commerce, failed, and paid his creditors twenty pennies in the pound; published translations, of which the public at length became heartily tired; having, indeed, got an inkling of the manner in which those translations were got up. He managed, however, to ride out many a storm, having one trusty sheet-anchor—Radicalism. This he turned to the best advantage—writing pamphlets and articles in reviews, all in the Radical interest, and for which he was paid out of the Radical fund; which articles and pamphlets, when Toryism seemed to reel on its last legs, exhibited a slight tendency to Whiggism. Nevertheless, his abhorrence of desertion of principle was so great in the time of the Duke of Wellington’s administration, that when S— left the Whigs and went over, he told the writer, who was about that time engaged with him in a literary undertaking, that the said S— was a fellow with a character so infamous, that any honest man would rather that you should spit in his face than insult his ears with the mention of the name of S—.

The literary project having come to nothing,—in which, by-the-bye, the writer was to have all the labour, and his friend all the credit, provided any credit should accrue from it,—the writer did not see the latter for some years, during which time considerable political changes took place; the Tories were driven from, and the Whigs placed in, office, both events being brought about by the Radicals coalescing with the Whigs, over whom they possessed great influence for the services which they had rendered. When the writer next visited his friend, he found him very much altered; his opinions were by no means so exalted as they had been—he was not disposed even to be rancorous against the Duke of Wellington, saying that there were worse men than he, and giving him some credit as a general; a hankering after gentility seeming to pervade the whole family, father and sons, wife and daughters, all of whom talked about genteel diversions—gentility-novels, and even seemed to look with favour on high Churchism, having in former years, to all appearance, been bigoted Dissenters. In a little time the writer went abroad; as, indeed, did his friend; not, however, like the writer, at his own expense, but at that of the country—the Whigs having given him a travelling appointment, which he held for some years, during which he is said to have received upwards of twelve thousand pounds of the money of the country, for services which will, perhaps, be found inscribed on certain tablets, when another Astolfo shall visit the moon. This appointment, however, he lost on the Tories resuming power—when the writer found him almost as Radical and patriotic as ever, just engaged in trying to get into Parliament, into which he got by the assistance of his Radical friends, who, in conjunction with the Whigs, were just getting up a crusade against the Tories, which they intended should be a conclusive one.

A little time after the publication of The Bible in Spain, the Tories being still in power, this individual, full of the most disinterested friendship for the author, was particularly anxious that he should be presented with an official situation, in a certain region a great many miles off. “You are the only person for that appointment,” said he; “you understand a great deal about the country, and are better acquainted with the two languages spoken there than any one in England. Now I love my country, and have, moreover, a great regard for you, and as I am in Parliament, and have frequent opportunities of speaking to the Ministry, I shall take care to tell them how desirable it would be to secure your services. It is true they are Tories, but I think that even Tories would give up their habitual love of jobbery in a case like yours, and for once show themselves disposed to be honest men and gentlemen; indeed, I have no doubt they will; for, having so deservedly an infamous character, they would be glad to get themselves a little credit, by a presentation which could not possibly be traced to jobbery or favouritism.” The writer begged his friend to give himself no trouble about the matter, as he was not desirous of the appointment, being in tolerably easy circumstances, and willing to take some rest after a life of labour. All, however, that he could say was of no use, his friend indignantly observing that the matter ought to be taken entirely out of his hands, and the appointment thrust upon him for the credit of the country. “But may not many people be far more worthy of the appointment than myself?” said the writer. “Where?” said the friendly Radical. “If you don’t get it, it will be made a job of, given to the son of some steward, or, perhaps, to some quack who has done dirty work; I tell you what, I shall ask it for you, in spite of you; I shall, indeed!” and his eyes flashed with friendly and patriotic fervour through the large pair of spectacles which he wore.

And, in fact, it would appear that the honest and friendly patriot put his threat into execution. “I have spoken,” said he, “more than once to this and that individual in Parliament, and everybody seems to think that the appointment should be given to you. Nay, that you should be forced to accept it. I intend next to speak to Lord A—.” [372a] And so he did, at least it would appear so. On the writer calling upon him one evening, about a week afterwards, in order to take leave of him, as the writer was about to take a long journey for the sake of his health, his friend no sooner saw him than he started up in a violent fit of agitation, and glancing about the room, in which there were several people, amongst others two Whig members of Parliament, said: “I am glad you are come, I was just speaking about you. This,” said he, addressing the two members, “is so-and-so, the author of so-and-so, the well-known philologist; as I was telling you, I spoke to Lord A— [372b] this day about him, and said that he ought forthwith to have the head appointment in —; and what did the fellow say? Why, that there was no necessity for such an appointment at all, and if there were, why—and then he hummed and ha’d. Yes,” said he, looking at the writer, “he did indeed. What a scandal! what an infamy! But I see how it will be, it will be a job. The place will be given to some son of a steward or to some quack, as I said before. Oh, these Tories! Well, if this does not make one—” Here he stopped short, crunched his teeth, and looked the image of desperation.

Seeing the poor man in this distressed condition, the writer begged him to be comforted, and not to take the matter so much to heart; but the indignant Radical took the matter very much to heart, and refused all comfort whatever, bouncing about the room, and, whilst his spectacles flashed in the light of four spermaceti candles, exclaiming: “It will be a job—a Tory job! I see it all, I see it all, I see it all!”

And a job it proved, and a very pretty job, but no Tory job. Shortly afterwards the Tories were out, and the Whigs were in. From that time the writer heard not a word about the injustice done to the country, in not presenting him with the appointment to —; the Radical, however, was busy enough to obtain the appointment, not for the writer, but for himself and eventually succeeded, partly through Radical influence, and partly through that of a certain Whig lord, for whom the Radical had done, on a particular occasion, work of a particular kind. So, though the place was given to a quack, and the whole affair a very pretty job, it was one in which the Tories had certainly no hand.

In the meanwhile, however, the friendly Radical did not drop the writer. Oh, no! On various occasions he obtained from the writer all the information about the country in question, and was particularly anxious to obtain from the writer, and eventually did obtain, a copy of a work written in the court language of that country, edited by the writer, a language exceedingly difficult, which the writer, at the expense of a considerable portion of his eyesight, had acquired, at least as far as by the eyesight it could be acquired. What use the writer’s friend made of the knowledge he had gained from him, and what use he made of the book, the writer can only guess; but he has little doubt that when the question of sending a person to — was mooted in a Parliamentary Committee—which it was at the instigation of the Radical supporters of the writer’s friend—the Radical on being examined about the country, gave the information which he had obtained from the writer as his own, and flashed the book and its singular characters in the eyes of the Committee; and then of course his Radical friends would instantly say: “This is the man! there is no one like him. See what information he possesses; and see that book written by himself in the court language of Serendib. This is the only man to send there. What a glory, what a triumph it would be to Britain, to send out a man so deeply versed in the mysterious lore of —, as our illustrious countryman; a person who with his knowledge could beat with their own weapons the wise men of —! Is such an opportunity to be lost? Oh, no, surely not; if it is, it will be an eternal disgrace to England, and the world will see that Whigs are no better than Tories.”

Let no one think the writer uncharitable in these suppositions. The writer is only too well acquainted with the antecedents of the individual, to entertain much doubt that he would shrink from any such conduct, provided he thought that his temporal interest would be forwarded by it. The writer is aware of more than one instance in which he has passed off the literature of friendless young men for his own, after making them a slight pecuniary compensation and deforming what was originally excellent by interpolations of his own. This was his especial practice with regard to translation, of which he would fain be esteemed the king. This Radical literato is slightly acquainted with four or five of the easier dialects of Europe, on the strength of which knowledge he would fain pass for a universal linguist, publishing translations of pieces originally written in various difficult languages; which translations, however, were either made by himself from literal renderings done for him into French or German, or had been made from the originals into English, by friendless young men, and then deformed by his alterations.

Well, the Radical got the appointment, and the writer certainly did not grudge it him. He, of course, was aware that his friend had behaved in a very base manner towards him, but he bore him no ill-will, and invariably when he heard him spoken against, which was frequently the case, took his part when no other person would; indeed, he could well afford to bear him no ill-will. He had never sought for the appointment, nor wished for it, nor, indeed, ever believed himself to be qualified for it. He was conscious, it is true, that he was not altogether unacquainted with the language and literature of the country with which the appointment was connected. He was likewise aware that he was not altogether deficient in courage and in propriety of behaviour. He knew that his appearance was not particularly against him, his face not being like that of a convicted pickpocket, nor his gait resembling that of a fox who has lost his tail; yet he never believed himself adapted for the appointment, being aware that he had no aptitude for the doing of dirty work, if called to do it, nor pliancy which would enable him to submit to scurvy treatment, whether he did dirty work or not—requisites, at the time of which he is speaking, indispensable in every British official; requisites, by-the-bye, which his friend, the Radical, possessed in a high degree; but though he bore no ill-will towards his friend, his friend bore anything but good-will towards him; for from the moment that he had obtained the appointment for himself, his mind was filled with the most bitter malignity against the writer, and naturally enough; for no one ever yet behaved in a base manner towards another, without forthwith conceiving a mortal hatred against him. You wrong another, know yourself to have acted basely, and are enraged, not against yourself—for no one hates himself—but against the innocent cause of your baseness; reasoning very plausibly, “But for that fellow, I should never have been base; for had he not existed, I could not have been so, at any rate against him”; and this hatred is all the more bitter, when you reflect that you have been needlessly base.

Whilst the Tories are in power the writer’s friend, of his own accord, raves against the Tories because they do not give the writer a certain appointment, and makes, or says he makes, desperate exertions to make them do so; but no sooner are the Tories out, with whom he has no influence, and the Whigs in, with whom he, or rather his party, has influence, than he gets the place for himself, though, according to his own expressed opinion—an opinion with which the writer does not, and never did, concur—the writer was the only person competent to hold it. Now had he, without saying a word to the writer, or about the writer with respect to the employment, got the place for himself when he had an opportunity, knowing, as he very well knew, himself to be utterly unqualified for it, the transaction, though a piece of jobbery, would not have merited the title of a base transaction; as the matter stands, however, who can avoid calling the whole affair not only a piece of—come, come, out with the word—scoundrelism on the part of the writer’s friend, but a most curious piece of uncalled-for scoundrelism? and who, with any knowledge of fallen human nature, can wonder at the writer’s friend entertaining towards him a considerable portion of gall and malignity?

This feeling on the part of the writer’s friend was wonderfully increased by the appearance of Lavengro, many passages of which the Radical in his foreign appointment applied to himself and family—one or two of his children having gone over to Popery, the rest become members of Mr. Platitude’s chapel, and the minds of all being filled with ultra notions of gentility.

The writer, hearing that his old friend had returned to England, to apply, he believes, for an increase of salary, and for a title, called upon him, unwillingly, it is true, for he had no wish to see a person for whom, though he bore him no ill-will, he could not avoid feeling a considerable portion of contempt; the truth is, that his sole object in calling was to endeavour to get back a piece of literary property which his friend had obtained from him many years previously, and which, though he had frequently applied for it, he never could get back. Well, the writer called; he did not get his property, which, indeed, he had scarcely time to press for, being almost instantly attacked by his good friend and his wife—yes, it was then that the author was set upon by an old Radical and his wife—the wife, who looked the very image of shame and malignity, did not say much, it is true, but encouraged her husband in all he said. Both of their own accord introduced the subject of Lavengro. The Radical called the writer a grumbler, just as if there had ever been a greater grumbler than himself until, by the means above described, he had obtained a place; he said that the book contained a melancholy view of human nature—just as if anybody could look in his face without having a melancholy view of human nature. On the writer quietly observing that the book contained an exposition of his principles, the pseudo-Radical replied, that he cared nothing for his principles—which was probably true, it not being likely that he would care for another person’s principles after having shown so thorough a disregard for his own. The writer said that the book, of course, would give offence to humbugs; the Radical then demanded whether he thought him a humbug—the wretched wife was the Radical’s protection, even as he knew she would be; it was on her account that the writer did not kick his good friend; as it was, he looked at him in the face and thought to himself, “How is it possible I should think you a humbug, when only last night I was taking your part in a company in which everybody called you a humbug?”

The Radical, probably observing something in the writer’s eye which he did not like, became all on a sudden abjectly submissive, and, professing the highest admiration for the writer, begged him to visit him in his government; this the writer promised faithfully to do, and he takes the present opportunity of performing his promise.

This is one of the pseudo-Radical calumniators of Lavengro and its author; were the writer on his death-bed he would lay his hand on his heart and say, that he does not believe that there is one trait of exaggeration in the portrait which he has drawn. This is one of the pseudo-Radical calumniators of Lavengro and its author; and this is one of the genus, who, after having railed against jobbery for perhaps a quarter of a century, at present batten on large official salaries which they do not earn. England is a great country, and her interests require that she should have many a well-paid official both at home and abroad; but will England long continue a great country if the care of her interests, both at home and abroad, is in many instances intrusted to beings like him described above, whose only recommendation for an official appointment was that he was deeply versed in the secrets of his party and of the Whigs?

Before he concludes, the writer will take the liberty of saying of Lavengro that it is a book written for the express purpose of inculcating virtue, love of country, learning, manly pursuits, and genuine religion, for example, that of the Church of England, and for awakening a contempt for nonsense of every kind, and a hatred for priestcraft, more especially that of Rome.

And in conclusion, with respect to many passages of his book in which he has expressed himself in terms neither measured nor mealy, he will beg leave to observe, in the words of a great poet, who lived a profligate life, it is true, but who died a sincere penitent—thanks, after God, to good Bishop Burnet—

“All this with indignation I have hurl’d
At the pretending part of this proud world,
Who, swollen with selfish vanity, devise
False freedoms, formal cheats, and holy lies,
Over their fellow fools to tyrannise.”

—Rochester.

NOTES TO THE ROMANY RYE,
WITH
CORRECTIONS, IDENTIFICATIONS AND TRANSLATIONS.

Page 5. The man in black: The Rev. Fraser. See pp. 24–25, and “Arbuthnot” in Bibliog.—Barbarini, read Barberini: Urban VIII., pope 1623–44.—6. Nipotismo di Roma: See “Leti” in Bibliog.—Ganganelli: Clement XIV., pope, 1769–74.—10. Mezzofanti: So here and elsewhere in Romany Rye; Mezzofante in Lavengro—Cardinal Giuseppe, 1774–1849, the celebrated linguist.—Leon the Isaurian: Reigned at Constantinople from 717–741.—11. Ignacio: Spanish form of Ignatius.—14. Omani batsikhom: Manchu Tartar form of prayer given elsewhere by Borrow as Oum-ma-ni-bat-mi-houm. See Life, i., p. 176.—15. Bellissima Biondina (It.): Fairest of blondes.—16. Sono un Prete, etc. (It): I am a Roman Catholic Priest.—19. Zamarra (Sp.): A sheep-skin jacket with the wool outside.—Carajo: An oath fit neither to be written nor pronounced, but common to the lower classes of Spaniards, or to ambitious foreign Hispanophiles who cannot know its meaning. See Oudin’s Tesoro, Paris, 1607.—20. Scotch blood: He was, then, a Fraser of Lovat, of whom Simon Lord F. was a supporter of the last Pretender, Charles Edward Stuart, 1746.—Puta (Sp.): The most offensive word for harlot.—Alcoran des Cordeliers, i.e., “the Franciscans’ Coran”: A blasphemous work written in 1399 in Latin by Bartolommeo Albizzi (Albitius); first published in printed form at Milan in 1510, then by Luther in 1542 with his peculiar comments, and finally in French at Geneva, 1556. See “Albizzi” in the Bibliog.—22. Bible: The price of the old apple-woman’s Bible was, it will be remembered, one half-crown (Lavengro, p. 264).—23. Alexander VI.: Pope 1492–1503. He was a Spaniard of Valencia, and his family name was Rodrigo Borja, in It. Borgia.—24. L’opere sue, etc.: His deeds were not those of lions, but of foxes—a slight alteration of Dante’s L’opere mie, etc. See L’inf., xxvii., st. 25.—25. Oimè (It.): Alas!—To . . ., read Rome.—Sir John D., read Sir Thomas Dereham: A follower of the Stuarts; he died in 1739, and his monument stands in the English College at Rome.—There is at . . ., read Rome.—Yes, per Dio (It.): By Heaven!

Page 25. Parsons and Garnet: Two English Jesuits—Robert Parsons (1547–1610), superior to the Catholic Missions in England, and Henry Garnet (1555–1606), hanged because he refused to reveal the secrets of the confessional in connection with the Gunpowder Plot.—No hay remedio (Sp.): There is no help for it.—26. Inserted it: In vol. iv., p. 330.—32. Calañés: A Spanish hat worn by the lower classes, having the rim turned up against the crown.—There’s a chovahanee, etc.: The full ditty runs thus in one of Borrow’s MSS.:—

“THE PETULENGRES.

“There’s a chovahanee and a chovahanó,
The nav se lendè Petulengro;
Sore the chavès ’dré their ten
Are chories and labbenies—tatchipen,”

which reading corrects that of the text.—34. Flaming Bosville: Anselo Herne. See p. 67, and note to Lavengro, p. 363.—37. Gentleman Cooper and White-headed Bob: i.e., George Cooper and Ned Baldwin, who fought on the 5th of July, 1825, according to Pearce Egan’s Boxiana, v., pp. 61 and 80. Observe that the date harmonises perfectly with the chronology of the expedition.—38. Brynhilda the Valkyrie, or Amazon, was the wife of Gunnar and friend of Sigurd. See the Edda in Bibliog. Sigurd, called Fafnisbane or the Slayer of Fafnir, was a heroic character frequently mentioned in the Edda, the Wilkina Saga, Snorro’s Heimskringla, and Saxo-Grammaticus. In the Wilkina he is Sigurdr Sveinn, in the old Danish Heroic Ballads (Kiæmpeviser) he is Sigurd Snaresvend (Borrow’s “Snareswayne”), and Siegfrid in the Lay of the Nibelungs. Sivard or Sivord is a German variety of the same name.

Page 40. Feasting: This rustic banquet was offered to Sylvester and Ursula who were married that day, although our “rye” was not aware of the fact till later. The song was built up by our author from a very slender prose draft, which I find in its earliest form given thus:—

1. “DRABBING THE BAULO,

“We jaws to the drab-engro and lels dui or trin hors-worth of drab, and when we wels to the sweti we pens we can have a drab at a baulo. Then we kairs it opré, and jaws to a farm-ker to mang a bit of habben, and then we pens: ‘Chuva lis acai and dov-odoy baulo will lel it, and to-morrow sorlu we’ll wel apopli and mang it’. And so we kairs, and on the sorlu when we’ve got it, we toves it well; we kins levinor at the kitchema, and have a kosko habben. The boshom-engro plays (kils), and the tawni juva gils, a kosko puro Rommany guillie.” Then follows the gillie nearly as in the text.

2. “DRABBING THE BAULO.

“To mande shoon ye Rommany Chals
Who besh in the pus about the yag
I’ll pen how we drab the baulo.

“We jaws to the drab-engro ker
Trin horsworth there of drab we lels
And when to the swety back we wels
We pens we’ll drab the baulo.

“And then we kairs the drab opré,
And then we jaws to the farming ker
To mang a beti habben,
A beti poggado habben.

“A rinkeno baulo there we dick,
And then we pens in Rommany jib:
‘Chiv lis odoy oprey the chick,
The baulo he will lel lis,
The baulo he will lel lis.

“‘Apopli on the sorlo we
Will wel and mang him mullo,
Will wel and mang his truppo.’

“And so we kairs, and so we kairs,
We mang him on the sorlo,
And rig to the tan the baulo.

“And then we toves his wendror well
Till sore the wendror iuziou sie,
Till kekkeno drab’s adrey lis,
Till drab there’s kek adrey lis.

“And then his truppo well we hatch,
Kin levinor at the kitchema,
And have a kosko habben,
A kosko Rommano habben.

“The boshom-engro kils, he kils,
The tawni juva gils, she gils,
A puro Rommany gillie,
Now shoon the Rommany gillie.”

3. The third and last MS. is complete, but varies considerably from the printed text. Romany is written with two m’s, as in Lavengro throughout; in the fourth verse it reads: “In Rommany chib:chiv lis odoy opré the chik”; fourth line omits “and”; in the fifth and sixth verses it gives “sorlo” properly, instead of “saulo”; in seventh verse it reads “his wendror,” and in the last, “boshom-engro” and “tawni”.

From all these variants it results that MS. No. 3 furnishes a better reading than the printed text.

Page 42. Ursula’s Song: By the aid of the Gypsy list at the end of this volume, the translation can be easily made out by the curious reader.—46. Piramus: In MS. also Priamus.—Sanpriel: Corrupt form of Sanspareil, unrivalled.—Synfye: Slavonic form of Cynthia—th in Russian is pronounced ph or f; Thomas, Fómas.—47. Life of Charles: Add XIIth.—48. The church: Mentioned as three miles from the dingle, and on pp. 53, 110, as at M., has not yet been discovered.—58. The Edda: Early Icelandic literary monuments, consisting of the Elder or Poetic Edda collected by Sæmund, and the later or Prose Edda collected by Snorro Sturleson. See Mallet’s Northern Antiquities, Bohn’s Edition.—Sagas: Early historical tales handed down by oral tradition. See Bibliog.—67. Anselo Herne: His clan-name. See note to p. 363 of Lavengro. 68. Pulci: Luigi Pulci (1432–87). See Bibliog.—69. Ingravidata (It.): With child.—E nacquene, etc.: “And of her a son was born, says story, who subsequently gave great victory to Charlemagne”.—71. Fortiguerra: Niccolò Fortiguerra (1674–1735). He did not live to print his voluminous poem entitled Ricciardetto, having died in 1735, just “ninety years” from the date 1825, as our text declares.—76. Slammocks, etc.: Norwich worthies, I suppose; at least I do not find them in the Boxiana at my command.—89. The Armenian in this (xivth) chapter I find correct. Hramahyel should have been given hramaïyel, hntal, etc., khntal (χντάλ), and madagh, madag. See “Villotte” in the Bibliog.—91. Hard-mouthed jade: This favourite expression of Mr. Borrow’s proceeds, I opine, from his readings in the quaint eighteenth century literature with which his library abounded. In Defoe’s Moll Flanders, p. 301, edition of 1722, we read: “The witnesses were the two wenches, a couple of hard mouth’d jades indeed”. And on p. 323: “A hard mouth’d man”.—93. Brynhilda: See note to p. 38.—133–34.The “daffodil” poet: William Wordsworth (1770–1850).—141. Carlo Borromeo: The Cardinal saint, born 1538, died 1584.—143. Bricconi abbasso (It.): “Down with the rogues!”

Page 157. Friar Bacon: The celebrated scientist Roger Bacon (1214–94) was fated, like Virgil, to be popularly metamorphosed into a magician and conjuror. Hence the “Friar Bacon” series of chap-books, extending (so far as we know them) from the sixteenth century to the present. I will give the passage referred to by Mr. Borrow, so that it may be seen that the myth had no reference to the railway. No. 3 in Bibliog., leaf 8:—

“Chapter V. How Miles watched the Brazen-head, and in the end went away from his master.

“Fryer Bacon, having performed many wonderful things by his curious Art, was now sifting out how he might wall England with brass; wherefore he and Fryer Bungy, when they had raised the devil, bound him to a tree, for to make him tell them how it might be performed. He told them that they should make a Brazen-head, which (if they could watch it till it spoke) would tell them how it might be done. The head was made, and they watched till they could watch no longer. At last Fryer Bungey persuaded Fryer Bacon to let his man Miles watch while they slept; to which the Fryer agreed. Then Miles was called, who undertook to awake them when the Head would speak. So to sleep they went, and Miles expected some great speech to come from the Head. At last the Head cryed, ‘TIME IS’; at which Miles fell into a great laughter, and made his scoffs and jears thereat. Then it said, ‘TIME WAS’; but yet he would not awake his master, counting them but silly and frivolous words. Lastly, the Head said, ‘TIME IS PAST’; at which words down it fell, and in falling made such a noise that it awakened the two Fryers, and had almost affrighted poor Miles out of his senses,” etc.

Page 158. L . . ., read Liverpool; C . . ., read Chester.—162. Brooke of Borneo: Sir James Brooke, Rajah of Sarawak (1803–68), George Borrow’s school-mate at Norwich in 1816–17–18.—165. “Vails”: He means, of course, vale.—175–6–7. Romanvile: London. See “English Rogue” in Bibl.—176. The chi she is kaulo (read kauley), etc.: “The lass she is black, she sleeps upon her back”.—177–78. Sivord: Or Sivard, the same as Sigurd, called the Snaresvend (“Snareswayne” on the next page). See note to p. 38, and Romantic Ballads, 1826, pp. 83 and 90. For the reason of Borrow’s changing the Danish svend into “swayne,” see Life, ii., p. 269.—The horse Grayman: i.e., the “Skimming gray” of p. 96, Romantic Ballads.—183. The Maugrabin sorcerer: The “African Magician” in Lane’s translation. There is in this passage of The Romany Rye evidently a confusion of two of the tales in the Arabian Nights—those of Aladdin and Sindbad, fifth voyage.—221. Isten (pron. íshten): Hung. for God.—222. Magyar (pron. mädjr): A Hungarian.—223.Tékéli (1658–1705).—L’Eau de la Reine d’Hongrie, read de Hongrie, h being aspirate in this word.—Pigault Lebrun (Charles), 1753–1835; Les Barons de Felsheim, Paris, 1822.—Ersebet, read Erszebet, Elisabeth.—Florentius of Buda: Flourished 1790–1805. See “Budai Ferencz” in the Bibliog.—224.Álmus, or Álmos (älmosh), died 889. The Hungarian scholar Vámbéri, has exploded the “dream” (or rather “sleep”) theory heretofore entertained with regard to the origin of the name Almos; he says it is an epithet, meaning the Great, the Sublime, the Noble, the Glorious (Ursprung, pp. 62, 156).—225 (228 and elsewhere), Dunau, read Donau, Germ. for Danube.—Király and Ház: The former comes from the Servian Králj (lj like Span. ll or Port. lh), which the Hungarian lengthened into kir-ály, not finding it convenient to pronounce kr. [383] As for haz, from haus (Austrian pop. pronunciation hôs), we are told by Vámbéri that the ancient form was not ház, but hos (Ursp., p. 556).—226. Janos (pron. Yánosh): John.—226. Szava (Hung.): The Save.—229. Laszlo: Ladislaus.—Cilejia: The Roman Claudia Celleia, now Cilly, in Carinthia.—230. Matyas: In English Matthias.—Huz, read husz (Hung.): Twenty. Vámbéri questions this etymology of “hussar” (p. 283), but unsatisfactorily, we think.—Ulazslo: Wladislaus.—Tché Drak: The Roumanian cé dracŭ, but pronounced as in the text, and equivalent to the exclamation que diable!—Mohacs Veszedelem, read Mohacsi Veszedelem: The Disaster of Mohács, the title of a poem by Baron Liszti.—231. Bátory: A mere epithet, the “valiant”.—232. Lajos (laï-osh), Louis or Lewis.—Mufti: The ulémas or Doctors of the (Mahomedan) law.—233. Coloscvar, read Koloszvár, in German, Klausenburg.—Budáï Ferencz: See Bibliog.—235. Rysckie Tsar, read Russki Tsar: The Russian Emperor.—Plescova, now Pskov.—Iván Basilowitz, read Vasiliévitch, known as Iván the Terrible.—236. Izbushka (Russ.): Hut—Tyzza, read Tisza: The river Theiss.—Kopacs Teto, read Kopász Tetö.—Kassau, read Kaschau.—239. Eljen edes, etc. (pron. elyen edesh tsigáñ oor, elyen gool eraï): “Long live the sweet Gypsy gentleman, long live the gudlo Rye”.—241. Roth-Welsch: The German for Thieves’ Slang.—Tzernebock, read Tchernobog (g like Germ. ch): Black god, evil principle.—Bielebock, read Bielbog: White god, the good principle.—242. Saxo-Gramaticus, read Grammaticus, see Bibliog.—Fekete (Hung.): Black.—246. Erik Bloodaxe (Danish Blodöxe): King of Norway, Snorro, 1633, p. 64.—256.Regner Lodbrok: “Regnar” in Icelandic; Borrow gives the Danish term of this king’s name. See his famous Death Song in Mallet, pp. 383–85.—Halgerdr, read Halgerda, Mallet, pp. 340–41.—257. Biorn, read Björn and Ivarr, Ivar.—258. Verdammt (Germ.): Confounded.

Page 262. “Wife selling”: A very common practice among a certain class, it seems, in England; and, as this will hardly be credited in America, I will append some extracts from the newspapers. The Norfolk Chronicle of 5th May, 1894, says: “The belief formerly prevailed, especially among the rural population, that a man had a perfectly legal right to sell his wife to another, provided he observed two indispensable formalities. One was that he placed a halter about her neck, and the other that he led her into the market and publicly transferred her to the purchaser. Numerous instances of these strange transactions have been recorded. Our columns, on the 9th of February, 1805, contained an account of the sale of a wife at Norwich. A Kentish tailor, the affections and person of whose amiable spouse had been jockeyed away by a neighbouring horse-dealer, caparisoned her neck with a halter and surrendered all right and title to his virtuous rib, in consideration of the sum of £5. On the 2nd of May, 1823, a similar sale was effected in this city. A man named Stebbings disposed of his wile to a person named Turner for the sum of £6 10s. The latter paid £4 on account, took the woman home, and brutally turned his lawful wife out of doors.”

The London Daily Mail of 1st March, 1899, prints the following:—

“Very few people are aware that wives are literally sold to-day in England. A very common error of the vulgar is that a man by selling his wife releases himself from the marriage contract as surely as if he were legally divorced. In March, 1796, The Times announced the sale of a wife at Sheffield for sixpence. A short time afterwards the same journal calmly stated that the price of wives has risen in Smithfield Market from half a guinea to three guineas and a half! In 1803 a man led his wife, by a halter round her neck, into the cattle market at Sheffield, and sold her for a guinea, the purchaser leading away the woman to his home. In 1820 a man named Brouchet hired a cattle-pen in the Canterbury market, placed his wife in it, and ultimately sold her for 5s. Then wives began to increase in value, for soon afterwards one was sold for £15. This was followed by a ‘slump’. In 1855 a man led his wife with a halter round her waist into Derby marketplace and offered her for sale, but all be could get for her was eighteen pence and a quart of ale. In 1873 a husband left his home and creditors in Belper for the liberty of America. The week after his flight all his goods were put up for auction to satisfy his debts. His wife claimed part of the money, and this being refused she insisted on being offered for sale as part of her husband’s assets. There was no sale, however, for ‘Lot 29’. In even more recent days wife sales were common, and are even being effected in this present year of grace. In 1882 John Wilson, a collier of Alfreton, Derbyshire, sold his wife in a public-house for fourpence. Sheffield knife-grinders have long been noted for their transactions in the wife trade. Within quite recent times many a Sheffield wife has been sold by her husband for a gallon of beer, which has been drunk on the spot. Sometimes these sales assume a more formal aspect. In 1887, in the Sheffield County Court, a man admitted that he had bought another man’s wife for 5s. Most of these discreditable ‘deals’ escape notice, but a case has come to light where a man agreed to sell his wife to a collier, and the trio, with the woman’s father and mother and two family friends, assembled to arrange terms. Thirty shillings was the price finally agreed on. Four years ago, at Leeds, a man charged with bigamy pleaded that, as he had sold his wife for 3s. 6d. to another man, he could marry again legally! Eighteen months’ imprisonment was what he got, and more than deserved. A police court case in 1896 at Doncaster revealed the fact that John Tart sold his wife to Enoch Childs, on the understanding that the latter reared the vendor’s four children. In a Durham court in 1894 it transpired that a man named Shaw sold his daughter, a girl of sixteen, to a collier called Cudman, for 1s. Many a wife is at present sold in the East End of London, as well as in Yorkshire, for a quart of beer or an ounce of thick twist. It is the poor man’s method of divorce, and such is popular ignorance that there are scores of people who imagine that selling a wife is as legal a separation as a decree nisi pronounced by a bewigged and berobed judge.”

Page 265. Herodotus: The story is found in Thalia III., 84–88 (pp. 208–9 of Cary’s Eng. translation). The groom’s name was Œbares.—266. Deaghblasda, read deaghbhlasda (Ir.): Sweet-tasted, dainty. This is the soothing word hinted at, but not given, in Lavengro, p. 83.—269. AtH . . ., read Hertford, where John Thurtell was hanged, 9th January, 1824.—Ned Flatnose: Ed. Painter of Norwich.—270. Spring: His true name was Thomas Winter; see Lavengro, p. 168. He died 20th August, 1851.—276. . . . Fair, read Greenwich Fair, on Easter Monday. See Dickens’ Sketches.—279. Oilien (and p. 295, Oilein) nan Naomha, read Oilean na Naomhtha (Ir.): Island of the Saints (Patrick and Columba).—Finn-ma-Coul: The tale of Finn was first learned by Borrow in January, 1854, from his Irish guide Cronan, while travelling in Cornwall (Life, ii., p. 86, and note). This fact shows that Murtagh and his tale are introduced here to exhibit the author’s discovery of the identity between the Finn of Ireland and the Eddaic tradition of Sigurd Fafnisbane (p. 281). For Sigurd in the Wilkina Saga is suckled by a hind (p. 120) and fostered by Mymmer Smed or Mimer the Smith (p. 121) whom he eventually slays (p. 124). In the Eddaic Lay of the serpent-killer we read: “Sigurd took the heart of Fafnir and broiled it on a spit. And when he judged that it was done, he touched it with his finger to ascertain if that were really the case. Having burned his finger in the act, he put it to his mouth, and no sooner had the heart’s blood of Fafnir come in contact with Sigurd’s tongue than he understood the speech of birds,” etc. Here we have the two sides verified, the Irish by Cronan, and the Scandian by the Edda. But Brooke’s Reliques, a favourite work of Borrow’s in his Norwich days, and which he cites in 1832 (Life, i., p. 146), give us certain other fragments of these Finnic fables, whereby we can trace the sources of the text before us. For example, after Jack Dale had stripped Murtagh of all his money he is observed to be sitting “in deep despondency, holding his thumb to his mouth” (p. 278). And a little farther on (p. 282) a verse is cited from “Conan the Bald”. Now all this is found in Miss Brooke, that is, the names and the ideas—Conan the Bald (p. 106), Lochlin (p. 46), and Darmod Odeen (minus Taffy) and the verse with this note (p. 109):—“This strange passage is explained by some lines in the Poem of Dubmac-Dighruibh, where Finn is reproached with deriving all his courage from chewing his thumb for prophetic information.”—281. Siol Loughlin, read Lochlin (Ir.): Literally “the seed of Norway,” i.e., the Danish or Norwegian race. Miss Brooke very properly says (p. 46): “Lochlin is the Gælic (and Irish) name for Scandinavia in general”; but Borrow limits it to Denmark—the Danish race. And a little below, “the Loughlin songs” are his Danish Ballads which he published the following year.

Page 283. The story of Murtagh at the Irish College in Rome, and his subsequent wanderings in the South of France and in Spain, mask, as we have said elsewhere, the peregrinations of George Borrow in 1826–27.—286. M’anam on Dioul: Explained in Lavengro, note to p. 65.—291. Dungarvon times of old: See Life, i., p. 46, and ii., pp. 16–17. Cradock’s letter was dated, 18th August, 1849, and Mr. B.’s answer (i., p. 146) a little after.—Raparees: Irish marauders, temp. James II. See Life, i., p. 146, and Brooke’s Reliques, p. 205. The latter says that the word is from the Irish Réubóir Ri, plunderer, robber, freebooter of the king, from reubaim, I tear.—292. Chiviter Vik: Cività Vecchia, the modern seaport of Rome, fifty miles distant.—Army of the Faith: Spanish frontier corps of observation under Gen. Don Vicente Quesada, 1823–24.—Prince Hilt: The Duke d’Angoulême, nephew of Louis XVIII., and son of the Count d’Artois (afterwards Charles X.). D’Angoulême invaded Spain in 1823 with 100,000 Frenchmen, to restore Ferdinand VII. to his absolute throne, against the Liberals of 1820–23.—298. To . . ., read Rome.—At . . ., read Rome.—Educated at . . ., read Rome.—300. Direction of the east, read south. He could only have gone south from Horncastle to reach Boston (the “large town on the arm of the sea”) that day. The next he came to Spalding, some fifteen miles farther, where he met the recruiting serjeant, thence on to Norwich by Lynn Regis.

We must not forget that before Lavengro was begun, and fifteen years prior to the publication of The Romany Rye, that is, 26th December, 1842, Mr. Petulengro remarked to George Borrow at Oulton: “I suppose you have not forgot how, fifteen [seventeen] years ago, when you made horseshoes in the dingle by the side of the great north road, I lent you fifty guineas to purchase the wonderful trotting cob of the innkeeper with the green Newmarket coat, which three days after you sold for two hundred”. [386a] Now, this is a very remarkable statement, and, taken in connection with the fact that so little is said about Horncastle in the book, it seems to me we are justified in proclaiming that Borrow was never in Horncastle at all. The interview with the Magyar and the syllabus of Hungarian history are clearly drawn from his experiences in Hungary and Transylvania in the year 1844, and hence are an anachronism here. It is a pity that the author did not adhere to the chronological facts of his life so strictly in The Romany Rye as he did in Lavengro. Truth and literature would have gained by it. And then that valedictory pledge, [386b] confirmed in the appendix, drawing a veil over the period of his travails, if not his travels, was an error of judgment which, in an autobiography will, we fear, not easily be condoned.

APPENDIX.

Page 302. Age of nineteen, read twenty; he was twenty-one less four months at his father’s death.—303. Children of Roma: Borrovian for Gypsies.—305–6. Balm in Mary Flanders: See Lavengro, note to p. 423.—311. Canning: Premier from 24th April to his death, 8th August, 1827; succeeded by Viscount Goderich from September, 1827, to 25th January, 1828.—312. Vaya! qué demonio es este! (Sp.): Bless me! what demon have we here!—314. Sessions of Hariri: Arabic tales in prose interlarded with verse. The two languages: Chinese and Manchu.—315–6. Luigi Pulci: Io vo’ tagliar, etc.: I’ll sever the hands of them all and bring them to those holy monks. Tu sarai or perfetto, etc.: Now thou wilt be as true a friend to Christ as aforetime thou wert his foe (M. M., canto i, sts. 53 and 57).—318. Oberon: A poem by Wieland (1733–1813).—319. The father of Anglo-Germanism: Taylor of Norwich.—Andrew Borde: (see Bibliog.). The text of the Bodleian copy (1547?) runs as follows—(A 3 verso):—

“I am an Englysh man, and naked I stand here,
Musyng in my mynd what rayment I shall were;
For now I wyll were thys, and now I wyl were that,
Now I wvl were I cannot tel what.
All new fashyons be plesaunt to me,
I wyll haue them, whether I thryue or thee;
Now I am a frysker, all men doth on me looke,
What should I do but set cocke on the hoope;
What do I care yf all the worlde me fayle,
I wyl get a garment shal reche to my tayle;
Than I am a minion, for I were the new gyse;
The yere after this I trust to be wyse,
Not only in wering my gorgious aray,
For I wyl go to learnyng a hoole somers day;
I wyll learne Latyne, Hebrew, Grecke and Frenche,
And I wyl learne Douche sittyng on my benche;
I do feare no man, all men fearyth me,
I ouercome my aduersaries by land and by see;
I had no peere yf to my selfe I were trew,
Because I am not so diuers times I do rew;
Yet I lake nothing, I haue all thyng at wyll
If were wyse and wold holde my selfe styll,
And medel wyth no matters not to me partayning;
But I haue suche matters rolling in my pate,
That I wyl speake and do I cannot tell what.” etc.

—321. Mr. Flamson: Samuel Morton Peto, M.P., later Sir Morton Peto of Somerleyton Hall, some five miles inland from Lowestoft. See Life, ii., p. 52.—327. Orcadian poet: “Ragnvald, Earl of the Orkney Islands, passed for a very able poet; he boasts himself, in a song of his which is still extant, that he knew how to compose verses on all subjects,” Mallet, p. 235. The original Runic of the lines translated by Borrow is found in Olaus Wormius. Transliterated into Latin letters they read thus:—

Tafl em eg or at efta
Idrottir kan eg niu
Tum eg tradla Runur
Tid er mer bog og smider
Skrid kann eg a gidum
Skot eg og re so nyter
Hvor tweggia kan ek hyggiu
Harpslatt og bragdattu.

—329. Lieut. P. . ., read Perry. The item was taken from a newspaper (which, I know not) published in September, 1854. Mr. Borrow read it at Llangollen in Wales. I loaned the clipping and it was not returned.—330. Balaklava: The usual etymon of this famous name is the Italian Bella chiave, beautiful key.—331. Companion of Bligh: This was Thomas Hayward.—Once: See Bligh’s Narrative (Bibliog.), p. 55.—336. “Malditas sean tus tripas,” etc.: This Borrovian Spanish must be rendered truthfully or not at all. The squeamish may excuse the borracha: “D— your g—s; we had enough of the stink of your g—s the day you ran away from the battle of the Boyne”.—338. Coronach (Gælic), read Corránach: The funeral wail, a dirge; in Irish, coránach.—342. Abencerages, read Abencerrages: Arab. ibn-serradj; son of the saddle.—349–50. Whiffler: See note to Lavengro, p. 225.—352. Francis Spira: Francesco Spiera, a lawyer of Cittadella (Venice), accepted the doctrines of the Reformation in 1548. Terrified by the menaces of the Church of Rome and the prospective ruin of his family, he went to Venice and solemnly abjured the Evangelical faith in the hands of the Legate, Giovan della Casa (see Dict. de Bayle) who required him to return home and repeat his abjuration before his fellow-townsmen and the local authorities. Having performed this act, he fell into the horrid state of remorse depicted in the Protestant accounts of the time. The report was first brought to Geneva by Pietro Paolo Vergerio, ex-bishop of Pola, who visited Spiera in his last moments at Padua, whence he himself bent his way to the Valtelina, as a fugitive from the Roman Church.—Duncan Campbell and Falconer: See Bibliog.—John Randall: Here is a confusion of John Rolfe and John Randolph of Roanoke (1773–1833). Pocahontas, daughter of the Indian Chief Powhatan, saved the life of Captain John Smith in Virginia and married John Rolfe in 1614. John Randolph of Roanoke claimed to be descended from Pocahontas, but Rolfe is evidently the one referred to in the text. See Bibliog. under “Pocahontas”.—354. Iriarte (1750–96): Spanish poet and writer of fables. See Bibliog.—355. Autobiographical character of Lavengro denied: but see Life, ii., pp. 3–27 and 211.—357. Ginnúngagap: The “yawning abyss” of Northern Mythology. See Mallet, p. 402.—359. Horinger Bay: See note on Lavengro, p. 46.—360. Harum-beck, read harmanbeck, as in Lavengro, p. 158.—Holkham Estate: The seat of the Cokes of Norfolk and the Earl of Leicester. See White’s Norfolk, and the C . . . of Lavengro, p. 124.—363. He said in ’32: See Life, i., p. 143.—Son of Norfolk clergyman: Nelson (nom de noms!).—364–66. Thistlewood and Ings: See article in Celebrated Lives and Trials, vol. vi., p. 339.—368. The old Radical: John Bowring in 1821.—Vol. of translations: See “Bowring” in Bibliog.—Red Rhys: Rhys Goch of Snowdon. See Wild Wales, p. 150, and “Gorchestion” in Bibliog.—369. The Doctor of Medicine: Dr. Lewis Evans. See Life, i., p. 74.—370.S . . ., read Southey.—Literary project (1829–30): See Life, i., p. 129.—371. Astolfo: His journey to the moon mentioned in Pulci, ed. 1546, Canto xxi., f. cxx. b:—

“Malagigi tagliava le parole,
Astolfo sopra ’l suo caval rimonta;
Cavalcano a la luna tanto e al sole
Che capitorno al castel di Creonta”.

—372. In —, read China.—373. To —, read China.—Copy of a work: Borrow’s edition of the Manchu New Testament, St. Petersburg, 1835, in 8 parts, 4to.—All the dashes mean Canton or China.—Serendib: (Ceylon) put for China.

NOTES TO LAVENGRO, WITH CORRECTIONS, IDENTIFICATIONS AND TRANSLATIONS.

Page 1. East D---: East Dereham, a small town in Norfolk, 16 miles W. of Norwich, and 102 N.E. of London. Here Capt. Thomas Borrow, the father of George, was often stationed from 1792 to 1812.—1. East Anglia: This Anglo-Saxon kingdom comprised the present counties of Norfolk, Suffolk and Cambridge.—1. Tredinnock, read Trethinnick; Parish of St. Cleer, Cornwall.—2. Big Ben: Benjamin Brain or Bryan was born in 1753. Some of his most severe “battles” were fought between 1780 and 1790—one on the 30th of August in the latter year, with Hooper at Newbury, Berks. A few days after this exploit, he picked a quarrel with Sergeant Borrow of the Coldstream Guards, which resulted in the Hyde Park encounter. Some four months later, i.e., 17th January, 1791, the decisive fight for the championship came off between Brain and Johnson. It was an appalling spectacle, and struck dumb with horror, even in that day, the witnesses to the dreadful conflict. Big Ben was the victor, and remained champion of England from that date until his death three years (not “four months”) later—8th April, 1794. “Lavengro,” carried away by the enthusiasm of early reminiscence, allowed himself to declare that his father read the Bible to Brain in his latter moments. But in 1794 Thomas Borrow was busy recruiting soldiers in Norfolk, one hundred miles from the scene of the dying pugilist. However, the error was probably one of date merely, and during the year 1791 Thomas doubtless read the Bible to him in London, since we learn from Pierce Egan that “Ben derived great consolation from hearing the Bible read, and generally solicited those of his acquaintance who called upon him to read a chapter to him”. [555]—3. Captain: The West Norfolk Militia was raised in 1759 by the third Earl of Orford. He died in December, 1791, when the regiment was reorganised (not “raised”) under the new Colonel, the Hon. Horatio Walpole, subsequently the sixth Earl of Orford. Thus in February, 1792, Thomas was transferred from the Guards to be Sergeant-major in the W.N.M., and stationed at East Dereham. He married the following year, became Quarter-master (with the rank of Ensign) in 1795, and Adjutant (Lieutenant) in February, 1798. This his final promotion doubtless gave him the honorary rank of Captain, since in the Monthly Army List for 1804 we read: “Adjutant, Thomas Borrow, Capt.”. But a letter before me dated 18th April, 1799, from his Major, is officially addressed to him as “Lieut. Borrow, Adjutant,” etc., etc.—3. Petrement: Our author knew very well that his mother’s maiden name was Ann Perfrement, pronounced and written Parfrement at the present day by those of the family we have met. The correct spelling is found on the tombstone of her sister, Sarah, at Dereham (1817), and on that of her brother, Samuel, at Salthouse near Holt (1864).—3. Castle of De Burgh: A fanciful Borrovian epithet applied to Norwich Castle. Nor did the exiles build the Church of St. Mary-the-Less, in Queen Street, Norwich; it was a distinct parish church long before Elizabeth’s reign, and in her time the parish was consolidated with the neighbouring one of St. George’s, Tombland, while the church became municipal property. But the French exiles of the Edict of 1685 did worship there, even as did the Dutch refugees from Alva’s persecution a century before (1565-70).—4. Middle Age: Borrow’s father was thirty-four, and his mother twenty-one, at the date of their marriage. John was born seven years after the marriage, and George ten. The mother was, then, thirty-one at George’s birth.—4. Bishop Hopkins: Sermons.—4. Angola: More correctly Angora.—5. Foreign grave: Lieut. John Thomas Borrow died at Guanajuato, Mexico, 22nd November, 1833.

Pages 12-13. “Snorro” Sturleson: Poet and historian of Iceland (1178-1241). Harald (not Harold) III., called “Haardraade”. Battle of Stamford Bridge, a.d. 1066, same year as Norman Conquest. See Mallet’s Northern Antiquities, pp. 168-71 and 194; Snorro’s Heimskringla, ii., p. 164, and his Chronica, 1633, p. 381, for the quotation; also Bibliog. at end of Romany Rye.—13. Winchester: Rather Winchelsea, according to the Regimental Records.—14. A gallant frigate: A reminiscence of Norman Cross gossip in 1810-11. “Ninety-eight French prisoners, the crew of a large French privateer of eighteen guns called the Contre-Amiral Magon, and commanded by the notorious Blackman, were captured 16th October, 1804, by Capt. Hancock of the Cruiser sloop, and brought into Yarmouth. They marched into Norwich, 26th November, and the next morning proceeded under guard on their way to Norman Cross barracks”—Norwich Papers, 1804.—15. Lady Bountiful: Dame Eleanor Fenn (1743-1813).—15. Bard: William Cowper (1731-1800).—16. Some Saint: Withburga, daughter of Anna, king of the East Angles, was the “saint” and the “daughter” at the same time.—19. Hunchbacked rhymer: Alexander Pope.—20. Properties of God, read attributes.—20. Rector: The Rev. F. J. H. Wollaston.—20. Philoh: James Philo (1745-1829).—21. Tolerism, read toleration.—24. Mere: Whittlesea Mere, long since drained.—31. Bengui: See the vocabulary at the end for all Gypsy words in this volume.—34. Jasper: The change from Ambrose to Jasper was made in pencil in Mrs. Borrow’s transcript at the last moment in 1849, before handing it to the printers.—38. Three years: Included in the subsequent narrative, not excluded from it as his Norwich school days (1814-15, 1816-18) were. They extend from July, 1811, to April, 1813—from Norman Cross to Edinburgh. The chronology, according to the Regimental Records, was as follows: George was at East Dereham from 22nd July to 18th November, 1811, at J. S. Buck’s (“Dr. B.’s”) school; 30th November, 1811, to February, 1812, at Colchester; 28th February to 5th March, 1812, at Harwich; 15th to 19th March, at Leicester; 21st to 30th March, at Melton Mowbray; 2nd to 25th April, at Leicester again; 28th April to 3rd May, at Tamworth (Lavengro, pp. 367-68); 8th to 26th May, at Macclesfield; 28th May to 2nd August, at Stockport; 3rd to 23rd August, at Ashton; 24th August to 15th December, at Huddersfield (W. W., p. 64, and Lavengro, pp. 39-41); 16th December, 1812, to 19th March, 1813, at Sheffield; 20th and 21st March, 1813, at Leeds; 22nd March, at Wetherby; 23rd March, Boroughbridge; 24th March, Allerton; 25th March, Darlington; 26th March, Durham (W. W., pp. 258-59); 27th and 28th March, Newcastle; 29th March, Morpeth; 30th March, Alnwick; 3rd and 4th April, at Berwick-upon-Tweed; 6th April, 1813, Edinburgh Castle.—38. Lilly: See Bibliog.

Page 42. Bank of a river: The Tweed. The scene here described occurred on a Sunday, 4th April, 1813, near Berwick, where they “arrived the preceding night” (p. 44).—42. Elvir Hill: See Borrow’s Romantic Ballads, Norwich, 1826, pp. 111-14. This piece entitled “Elvir Hill,” one of the old Danish ballads of Vedel’s collection, 1591, represents the dangers attending a youth who “rested” his “head upon Elvir Hill’s side” where he was so charmed in his sleep by a brace of seductive fairies, that

“If my good luck had not managed it so
That the cock crew out then in the distance,
I should have been murder’d by them on the Hill,
Without power to offer resistance.

“’Tis therefore I counsel each young Danish swain
Who may ride in the forest so dreary,
Ne’er to lay down upon lone Elvir Hill
Though he chance to be ever so weary.”

43. Skaldaglam: The barditus of Tacitus, or the “din” made by the Norse “bards” (skalds) on shields and with shouts as they rushed into battle. It is not in Molbech, but Snorro frequently uses it in his Chronica, 1633.—43. Kalevala: Title of the great Finnish epic, of which the hero is Woinomöinen.—43. Polak: Polander or Pole.—43. Magyar (pron. Mädjr): Hungarian.—43. Batuscha: An erratum of the author for his Batuschca (161)—better Batyushca, “father Tsar”—but generally applied by Borrow to his friend the Pope.—45 to 55: See Life, i., pp. 39-43.—46. Bui hin Digri: The Jomsburg Viking, a.d. 994. See Borrow’s Romantic Ballads, p. 136, and Once A Week, ix., p. 686. The account is given in Snorro’s Chronica, 1633, p. 136 (see Bibliog.), but a more accessible version of it is found in Mallet’s Northern Antiquities (Bohn’s ed.), pp. 144-45.—46. Horunga Vog, read Hjörúnga Vâgr in Icelandic, or Vaag in Danish. In Romany Rye (p. 359) it is Englished as “Horinger Bay”.—50. Hickathrift: A Norfolk worthy of the eleventh century, whose prodigious exploits with the axle of his cart as an offensive weapon, and the wheel as a shield, are handed down in the chap-books of the last three centuries. See p. 63; also Bibliog. at the end of Romany Rye.—51. Elzigood: William E., of Heigham, Norwich, enlisted October, 1789, became Drum-major in the regiment, 22nd October, 1802; called facetiously or maliciously Else-than-gude on p. 54.—55. O’Hanlon: Redmond O’Hanlon (d. 1681), a proprietor of Ulster, dispossessed under the Cromwellian settlement, and afterwards leader of a band of outlaws.—56. Disbanded: The W.N.M. regiment left Edinburgh in July, 1814, and was disembodied at Norwich, 19th July. It was again called out, 10th July, 1815, and sent to Ireland. John Borrow was appointed Ensign, 29th May, 1815, and Lieutenant, 13th December of the same year. The regiment sailed from Harwich (“port in Essex”) 31st August, reaching Cork harbour (“the cove”) about 9th September, 1815. 63. Wight Wallace (story book of): See Bibliog.

Page 63. Shorsha: The Irish for George, properly written Seors, but the author usually wrote his Irish by sound.—64. Saggart, read sagart: (Lat. sacerdos), a priest.—64. Finn-ma-Coul: In Irish Fionn-mac-Cumhail, the father of Ossian.—64. Brian Boroo: In Irish, Brian Boroimhe, a king of Ireland (926-1014).—65. Saggarting: Studying with reference to the priesthood.—65. Mavourneen: Properly mo mhuirnin, my darling.—65. Hanam mon Dioul: Wrongly given for M’anam o’n Diabhal [God preserve] my soul from the devil! See Romany Rye, p. 286, where it is quite correct—from sound.—66. Christmas over: 1816. Regiment quartered at Templemore. John, now a lieutenant (not “ensign”), is sent with a detachment to Loughmore, three miles away. Sergeant Bagg, promoted to that rank, 10th July, 1815, accompanies him.—66. Mountain: Called locally, “Devil’s Bit,” and not Devil’s Hill or Mt., as in the text.—68. Fine old language (add: which):

“A labhair Padric ’nninsè Fail na Riogh
’San faighe caomhsin Colum naomhtha ’n I.”
(which) “Patrick spoke in Innisfail to heathen chiefs of old,
And Columb, the mild prophet-saint, spoke in his island-hold.”

So Borrow gives the Irish and his version in Romantic Ballads, p. viii. The Erse lines were taken from Lhuyd’s Archæologia Britannica, Oxford, 1707, sign. d.—69. The Castle: Loughmore Castle.—71. Figure of a man: Jerry Grant, the Irish outlaw. See the Newgate Calendars subsequent to 1840—Pelham. Griffith, etc.—72 and 83. “Sas” and “Sassanach,” of course mean Englishman or English (Saxon).—74. Clergyman of the parish: The Rev. Patrick Kennedy, vicar of Loughmore. His name is also on the list of subscribers to the Romantic Ballads, Norwich, 1826, as J. Kennedy, by mistake.—76. Swanton Morley: A village near East Dereham.—82. Arrigod yuit (Irish), read airgiod dhuit: Have you any money?—82. Tabhair chugam (pron. tower khoogam): Give (it) to me.—83. Is agam an’t leigeas (read an t-leigheas): I have the remedy.—83. Another word: deaghbhlasda: See Romany Rye, p. 266, and Notes and Queries, 5th May, 1855, p. 339, article by George Métivier.

Page 84. Old city: Norwich. The regiment having returned to head-quarters, 11th May, 1816, was mustered out 17th June. The author describes the city from the “ruined wall” of the old Priory on the hill to the east.—85. The Norman Bridge: is Bishop’s Bridge.—85. Sword of Cordova, in Guild Hall, is a mistake for the sword of the Spanish General Don Xavier Winthuysen.—90. Vone banished priest: Rev. Thomas d’Éterville. The MS. gives the following inedited account of D’Éterville. I omit the oft-recurring expletive sacré (accursed):—

[Myself. Were you not yourself forced to flee from your country?

D’Éterville. That’s very true. . . . I became one vagabond—nothing better, I assure you, my dear; had you seen me, you would have said so. I arrive at Douvres; no welcome. I walk to Canterbury and knock at the door of one auberge. The landlord opens. “What do you here?” he says; “who are you?” “Vone exiled priest,” I reply. “Get you gone, sirrah!” he says; “we have beggars enough of our own,” and he slams the door in my face. Ma foi, il faisoit bien, for my toe was sticking through my shoe.

Myself. But you are no longer a vagabond, and your toe does not stick through your shoe now.

D’Éterville. No, thank God, the times are changed. I walked and walked, till I came here, where I became one philologue and taught tongues—French and Italian. I found good friends here, those of my religion. “He very good man,” they say; “one banished priest; we must help him.” I am no longer a vagabond—ride a good horse when I go to visit pupils in the country—stop at auberge—landlord comes to the door: “What do you please to want, sir?” “Only to bait my horse, that is all.” Eh bien, landlord very polite; he not call me vagabond; I carry pistols in my pocket.

Myself. I know you do; I have often seen them. But why do you carry pistols?

D’Éterville. I ride along the road from the distant village. I have been to visit my pupil whom I instruct in philology. My pupil has paid me my bill, and I carry in my purse the fruits of my philology. I come to one dark spot. Suddenly my bridle is seized, and one tall robber stands at my horse’s head with a very clumsy club in his hand. “Stand, rascal,” says he; “your life or your purse!” “Very good, sir,” I respond; “there you have it.” So I put my hand, not into my pocket, but into my holster; I draw out, not my purse, but my weapon, and—bang! I shoot the English robber through the head.

Myself. It is a bad thing to shed blood; I should be loth to shoot a robber to save a purse.

D’Éterville. Que tu es bête! mon ami. Am I to be robbed of the fruits of my philology, made in foreign land, by one English robber? Shall I become once more one vagabond as of old? one exiled priest turned from people’s doors, my shoe broken, toe sticking through it, like that bad poet who put the Pope in hell? Bah, bah!

By degrees D’Éterville acquired a considerable fortune for one in his station. Some people go so far as to say that it was principally made by an extensive contraband trade in which he was engaged. Be this as it may, some twenty years from the time of which I am speaking, he departed this life, and shortly before his death his fellow-religionists, who knew him to be wealthy, persuaded him to make a will, by which he bequeathed all his property to certain popish establishments in England. In his last hours, however, he repented, destroyed his first will, and made another, in which he left all he had to certain of his relations in his native country;—“for,” said he, “they think me one fool, but I will show them that they are mistaken. I came to this land one banished priest, where I made one small fortune; and now I am dying, to whom should I leave the fruits of my philology but to my blood-relations? In God’s name, let me sign. Monsieur Boileau left the fruits of his verses to his niece; eh bien, I will bequeath the fruits of my philology to my niece and nephew. There, there! thanks be to God, it is done! They take me for a fool; I am no fool. Leave to the Pope the fruits of my philology! Bah, bah! I do no such thing. I do like Monsieur Boileau.”]

Page 93. Earl’s Home: Earlham Hall, the residence of Joseph John Gurney (1788-1847), the Norwich banker and famous Quaker. The “tall figure” mentioned on the next page was Mr. Gurney, then twenty-eight years of age.—95. Only read Greek: This is a mistake. Mr. Gurney was an early student of Italian. See Braithwaite’s Life, i., pp. 25 and 49.—Zohar: Very correct. Braithwaite, i., p. 37.—Abarbenel, read Abarbanel or Abrabanel: A Spanish Jew driven from Spain in 1492. See p. 282.—97. Castle Hill: Norwich.—97. Fair of horses: Tombland Fair, held on Maundy Thursday every year.—100. Heath: Mousehold Heath, near Norwich. See also pp. 106, 161, etc.—112. “Gemiti, sospiri ed alti guai” (compare Dante, Inf., iii., 8: “Quivi sospiri, pianti, e alti guai”): Groans, sighs, and deep lamentations.—114. Ab Gwilym: See Bibliog. at the end of Romany Rye.—114. Cowydd: A species of Welsh poetry.—114. Eos (W.); Nightingale.—114. Narrow Court: Tuck’s Court, St. Giles, Norwich.—115. Old master: William Simpson of the law firm of Simpson & Rackham, Norwich.—115. Bon jour: read “Bonjour . . . ! bien des chases de ma part à Monsieur Peyrecourt or Pierrecourt”. “Expressions” in this sense (kind regards) is the Spanish expresiones, disguised as French.—118. Bwa Bach: The “little hunchback”. See p. 114.—119 to 125. Parkinson the poet: This character, who appears for the first time among the inedited episodes of Lavengro, was a real one, although his true name (Parkerson) is given somewhat veiled, as usual with Mr. Borrow. He seems to have been the poet-laureate of farmers, corn-merchants, drovers and publicans, selling his muse to the highest bidder, at first in printed sheets of eight pages, and subsequently gathered into pamphlets of thirty or more pages which he offered for one or two shillings each. They were printed by R. Walker, “near the Duke’s Palace, Norwich,” and sold by “Lane and Walker, St. Andrew’s”. They are without date, but cannot range far from 1818. Here are some specimens of his style: “The Norwich Corn Mart. By J. Parkerson, Junior.”

At one o’clock the busy scene begin,
Quick to the hall they all are posting in;
The cautious merchant takes his stand,
The farmer shows the produce of his land,

etc., for sixty-six lines. “On Mr. L . . . taking leave of his wife and children, who was sentenced to transportation for fourteen years” (!):—

Hannah, farewell, I’m bound to go,
To taste the bitter draught of woe,

134 lines. “A Description of the Pine-Apple at Trowse”:—

Both Beauty and Art have exerted their skill,
You will find on a spot near the brow of a hill;
The hill is near Norwich and call’d Bracondale,
I stept into Vince’s myself to regale,

etc., four pages of that.—124. Mr. C.: Thomas William Coke, Esq., of Holkham, Earl of Leicester in 1837, and died in 1842.

Pages 128-133. The Wake of Freya: This incident must have occurred to Mrs. Borrow at her home, Dumpling Green, East Dereham, on a Friday night, 5th December, 1783, when she was twelve (not “ten”) years old. Her eldest sister, Elizabeth, would be in her seventeenth year. Friday was then, as now, market day at Dereham. The place was the Blyth farm about one and a half miles (not “three”) from “pretty D”. The superstition referred to in this episode is, or was, a very common one in Norfolk, and even other countries. See the Norfolk Chronicle for 14th May, 1791; Glyde’s Norfolk Garland, pp. 13-14, and George Borrow in the Quarterly Review for January, 1861, p. 62.—130. Freya: The Venus of the North was the sister of Frey, according to Mallet (p. 94), and the original sources.—136. To London: Crome (John’s teacher) died at Norwich, 22nd April, 1821; but John could not leave until after the Regimental Training, which closed that year on 26th June; hence his departure may be set down for the last of June, 1821.—136. Rafael: Note spelling here (also pp. 223 and 225) and Raphael on p. 352.—137. Corregio, read Correggio.—139. Murray and Latroon, the Scotch outlaw and the “English Rogue”. See Bibliog. at the end of Romany Rye.—142. “Draoitheac,” magic, read draoidheachd (Ir.).—144. Muggletonians: Evidently a Borrovian slip here. See Notes and Queries for 3rd April, 1852, p. 320.—145. Vedel: Anders Sörensen Vedel, first collector of the Kiæmpeviser, or Heroic Ballads of the Danes, Copenh., 1591.—146. Chapter xxiii.: Interview between William Taylor (21 King Street, Norwich) and George Borrow.—151. Orm Ungarswayne: “Orm the youthful Swain,” Romantic Ballads, p. 86. But see the Danish ballad “Birting” in Borrow’s Targum, St. Petersb., 1835, pp. 59-61, commencing:—

“It was late at evening tide,
Sinks the day-star in the wave,
When alone Orm Ungarswayne
Rode to seek his father’s grave”.

—151. Swayne Vonved: See this piece in Romantic Ballads, pp. 61-81.—151. Mousha, read Muça, in Arabic or Moshé in Hebrew; both represent our Moses. But the Jew’s name was Levi, according to the MS.—153. The Fight: Between Painter and Oliver, near North Walsham, 17th July, 1820. This chapter xxiv. relates the author’s call on Mr. Petre of Westwick House, which must have been after 20th May, when it was decided that the “battle” should take place within twenty miles of Norwich.—155. Parr: There were two Parrs, one, Thomas, called “English” or “Old” Parr (1483-1635) who lived 152 years, and Samuel, called the “Greek” Parr (1747-1825,) who had been Head Master of the Norwich Grammar School from 1778 to 1785. This Dr. Samuel Parr was the one referred to by Mr. Petre.—155. Whiter: Rev. Walter Whiter, author of the Commentary on Shakespeare, Lond. 1794, and Etymologicum Magnum, Camb., 1800, 4to; enlarged ed., Camb., 1822-25, 3 vols. 4to.—156. Game Chicken: Henry Pierce, nicknamed Game Chicken, beat Gulley, 8th October, 1805 (Egan’s Boxiana, i., p. 145).—156. Sporting Gentlemen: John Thurtell and Edward Painter (“Ned Flatnose”).—158. Harmanbeck: Slang for constable—word taken from the English Rogue.—161. Batuschca (read Bátyooshca): See p. 43.—161. Priberjensky, read Préobrazhenski: Crack regiment of the Russian Imperial Guard, so called from the barracks situated near the Church of the Transfiguration (Préobrazhenïe).

Page 166. The Fight of 1820, chapter xxvi. We will here give a condensed portion of a chapter which we suppressed from the Life.

On the 20th of May, 1820, an eager crowd might have been seen pressing up to a card displayed in the Castle Tavern, Norwich. The card was signed T. C. and T. Belcher; but every one knew that the initials stood for the Champion of England, Thomas Cribb. The purport of the notice was that Edward Painter of Norwich was to fight Thomas Oliver of London for a purse of 100 guineas, on Monday, the 17th of July, in a field within twenty miles of the city.

A few days after this announcement, George Borrow was charged by his principals to convey a sum of money to a country gentleman by the name of John Berney Petre, Esq., J.P., residing at Westwick House, some thirteen and a half miles distant on the North Walsham road. The gentleman was just settling the transfer of his inheritance, his father having died eight months before. Borrow walked the entire distance, and while he tarried with the magistrate, the interview took place between him and Thurtell who desired to secure a field for the fight. Mr. Petre could not accommodate them, and they drove on to North Walsham. There they found the “pightle” which suited them in the vicinity of that town, on the road leading to Happisburgh (Hazebro).

Norwich began to fill on Saturday, the 15th of July, as the stage-coaches rolled in by the London (now Ipswich) and Newmarket roads. The Inn attached to the Bowling Green on Chapel-Field, then kept by the famous one-legged ex-coachman Dan Gurney (p. 167), was the favourite resort of the “great men” of the day. Belcher, not old Belcher of 1791, but the “Teucer” Belcher, and Cribb, the champion of England, slept at the Castle Tavern, which like Janus had two faces—backed on the Meadows and fronted on White-Lion. The Norfolk in St. Giles and the Angel on the “Walk,” housed other varieties of the sporting world.

At an early hour on Monday, the 17th, the roads were alive with pedestrians, equestrians, Jews, Gentiles and Gypsies, in coaches, barouches and vehicles of every sort. From Norwich they streamed down Tombland into Magdalen street and road, out on the Coltishall highway, and thence—sixteen and one half miles in all—to North Walsham and the field. One ancient MacGowan (the Scotch for Petulengro) stood on Coltishall bridge and counted 2050 carriages as they swept past. More than 25,000 men and thieves gathered in concentric circles about the stand.

I do not propose to attempt the description of this celebrated pugna or “battle with the fists”. Those who crave such diversions will find this one portrayed fittingly in the newspapers of the time. The closing passage of one of them has always seemed to me to be a masterpiece of grim brutality: “Oliver’s nob was exchequered, and he fell by heavy right-handed blows on his ears and temple. When on his second’s knee, his head dangled about like a poppy after a shower.”

A second fight, this time between Sampson, called the “Birmingham boy,” and Martin the “baker,” lost much of its interest by reason of the storm described in Lavengro. “During the contest,” says the Norfolk Chronicle, “a most tremendous black cloud informed the spectators that a rare sousing was in preparation for them.” And the Mercury states that “the heavy rain drenched the field, and most betook themselves to a retreat, but the rats were all drinkled”. Thus the “cloud” was no fiction, by which the Gypsy foretold the dreadful fate awaiting John Thurtell before Hertford gaol, 9th January, 1824. Ned Painter never fought again. He was landlord of the White Hart Inn from 1823 to 1835. The present proprietor still shows his portrait there, with the above fact duly inscribed on the back of the frame.

Page 168. Public: The Castle Tavern, Holborn, kept by Tom Belcher—the “Daffy Club”.—169. “Here’s a health to old honest John Bull:” The verses were taken from a rare old volume entitled: The Norwich Minstrel, p. 30, (See Bibliog.):—

“HONEST JOHN BULL.”

“Here’s a health to ‘Old honest John Bull’;
When he’s gone we shan’t find such another;
With hearts and with glasses brim full,
We’ll drink to ‘Britannia, his mother’;
For she gave him a good education,
Bade him keep to his God and his King,
Be loyal and true to the nation,
And then to get merry and sing.

“For John is a good-natured fellow,
Industrious, honest and brave;
Not afraid of his betters when mellow,
For betters he knows he must have.
There must be fine lords and fine ladies,
There must be some little, some great;
Their wealth the support of our trade is,
Our trade the support of the State.

“Some were born for the court and the city,
And some for the village and cot;
For it would be a dolorous ditty,
If we were born ‘equal in lot’.
If our ships had no pilots to steer,
What would come of poor Jack on the shrouds?
Or our troops no commanders to fear,
They would soon be arm’d robbers in crowds.

“The plough and the loom would stand still,
If we were made gentlefolks all;
If clodhoppers—who then would fill
The parliament, pulpit or hall?
‘Rights of Man’ makes a very fine sound,
‘Equal riches’ a plausible tale;
Whose labourers would then till the ground?
All would drink, but who’d brew the ale?

“Half naked and starv’d, in the streets
We should wander about, sans culottes;
Would Liberty find us in meats,
Or Equality lengthen our coats?
That knaves are for levelling, don’t wonder,
We may easily guess at their views;
Pray, who’d gain the most by the plunder?
Why, they that have nothing to lose.

“Then away with this nonsense and stuff,
Full of treason, confusion and blood;
Every Briton has freedom enough
To be happy as long as he’s good.
To be rul’d by a glorious king,
To be govern’d by jury and laws;
Then let us be happy and sing,
‘This, this, is true Liberty’s cause’.”

Page 174. Haik, read Haïk: Armenian.—178. Conqueror of Tippoo Sahib: General Harris (1791).—181. March: The exact date was discovered by me in private letters in Norwich. See Life, i., p. 91. George left Norwich on the evening of 1st April, 1824, and consequently reached London early on the morning of 2nd April.—182. Lodging: No. 16 Millman Street, Bedford Row.—185. The publisher: Sir Richard Phillips.—185. Mr. so-and-so: Taylor of Norwich.—186. The Magazine: The Monthly Magazine; or, British Register.—187. The Oxford Review: The Universal Review; or, Chronicle of the Literature of all Nations. No. 1, March, 1824, to No. 6, January, 1825. See also pp. 190, 203 and ff.—191. Red Julius, called elsewhere by Borrow Iolo Goch: A Welsh bard of the fifteenth century.—193. Cæsar’s Castle: The Tower of London.—194 and 423. Blessed Mary Flanders: Defoe’s Moll Flanders, See Bibliog. at the end of Romany Rye.—197. Booksellers’ shop: The shop was a depository of the Religious Tract Society, the publishers of Legh Richmond’s Annals of the Poor, of which the first section was the Dairyman’s Daughter (pp. 101).—203. Newly married: Richard, Jr., m. Feb., 1823.—204. “Newgate Lives”: The true title was: Celebrated Trials, and Remarkable Cases of Criminal Jurisprudence, from the earliest records to the year 1825, Lond., 1825 (February), 6 vols. 8vo.—205. Translator of “Faustus”: Faust, a Drama by Goethe, and Schiller’s Song of the Bell; translated by Lord Francis Leveson Gower, Lond., J. Murray, 1823, 8vo; 2nd ed., enlarged, ibid., 1825, 2 vols. 8vo.—208. Translator of Quintilian: I doubt whether this was John Carey, LL.D. (1756-1826), who published an edition of Quintilian, 1822, but no translation. My information is positive that it was Wm. Gifford, translator of Juvenal, 1802, 3rd ed. 1817.—215. Oxford: This constant satirising of the great English university in connection with the publisher’s theory, doubtless grew out of a series of articles printed in the Magazine during the years ’23 and ’24, and which may be summarised by this notice in vol. lvi., p. 349: “In a few days will appear a series of Dialogues between an Oxford Tutor and a Disciple of the new Commonsense Philosophy; in which the mechanical principles of matter and motion will be accurately contrasted with the theories of occult powers which are at present cherished by the Universities and Royal Associations throughout Europe”.—220. Churchyard: St. Giles churchyard where Capt. Borrow was buried on the 4th of March previous.—220. A New Mayor: Inexact. Robert Hawkes was mayor of Norwich in 1822. Therefore he was now ex-mayor—220. Man with a Hump: Thomas Osborn Springfield, was not a watchmaker so far as is known in Norwich, but “carried on the wholesale silk business, having almost a monopoly of the market” (Bayne’s Norwich, p. 588).—221. Painter of the heroic: Benjamin Robert Haydon (1785-1846).—224. Norman Arch: The grand entrance and exit to the Norwich Cathedral, west side.—225. Snap: The Snap-Dragon of Norwich is the Tarasque of the south of France, and the Tarasca of Corpus day in Spain. It represents a Dragon or monster with hideous jaws, supported by men concealed, all but their legs, within its capacious belly, and carried about in civic processions prior to the year 1835; even now it is seen on Guy Fawkes’ day, the 5th of November.—Whiffler: An official character of the old Norwich Corporation, strangely uniformed and accoutred, who headed the annual procession on Guildhall day, flourishing a sword in a marvellous manner. All this was abolished on the passage of the Municipal Reform Act in 1835. As a consequence, says a contemporaneous writer, “the Aldermen left off wearing their scarlet gowns, Snap was laid up on a shelf in the ‘Sword Room’ in the Guildhall, and the Whifflers no longer danced at the head of the procession in their picturesque costume. It was a pretty sight, and their skill in flourishing their short swords was marvellous to behold.” See Romany Rye, pp. 349-50.—Billy Blind and Owlenglass (Till Eulenspiegel): See Bibliography.—228. Brandt and Struensee: For High-Treason in Denmark, 1772. See Celebrated Trials, iv., p. 465; and for Richard Patch (“yeoman Patch”), 1805, vol. v., p. 584.—229. Lord Byron: The remains of the poet lay in state from Friday 9th July, 1824, in Sir Edward Knatchbull’s house, Great George Street, to Monday the 12th when they were conveyed to Hucknall-Torkard in Nottinghamshire. On that day (12th July) Borrow witnessed the procession as described in the text.—233. Carolan’s Receipt: Torlough (i.e., Charles) O’Carolan, the celebrated Irish harper and bard, was born at Nobber, Co. Meath, in 1670, and died in 1738. See Alfred Webb’s Compendium of Irish Biography, Dublin, 1878, p. 372; J. C. Walker’s Irish Bards, 1786, App., pp. 86-87, and Dict. of Nat. Biog., xli., p. 343. The “Receipt” in Irish is in Walker, and at the end of Vallancey’s Irish Grammar, second ed., Dublin, 1781. [565] Here is the translation given in Walker:—

“When by sickness or sorrow assail’d,
To the mansion of Stafford I hie’d
His advice or his cordial ne’er fail’d
To relieve me—nor e’er was denied.

“At midnight our glasses went round,
In the morning a cup he would send;
By the force of his wit he has found
That my life did on drinking depend.

“With the spirit of Whiskey inspir’d,
By my Harp e’en the pow’r is confess’d;
’Tis then that my genius is fir’d,
’Tis then I sing sweetest and best.

“Ye friends and ye neighbours draw near,
Attend to the close of my song;
Remember, if life you hold dear,
That drinking your life will prolong.”

Curiously enough among the subscribers to the Romantic Ballads, Norwich, 1826, we find these names: (p. 185) “F. Arden, Esq., London, five copies,” “T. G. O’Donnahoo, Esq., London, five copies;” (p. 187) “Mr. J. Turner, London”.

Page 244. The Review: The Review actually ceased January, 1825, with its sixth number.—268. Laham: In Heb. bread is lèhem; but our author probably wrote it by sound. Z’hats is the acc. of hats, the Arm. for bread; for as Borrow’s source, old Villotte (1714), says: “Accusativus præfigit nominativo literam z”.—270 and 286. Mesroub, read Miesrob, who, about a.d. 450 introduced the Armenian alphabet. 271. Sea in Arm. is dzow. See Romany Rye, p. 356—281. Adelánte (Span.): Come in.—281. Bueno (Span.): Good. This sound of the word bueno, heard in 1825 from the Jew Manasseh, was brought to Borrow’s memory in 1836 when he met the Jew Abarbanel on the roads in Spain. See B. in S., p. 65, sm. ed.—282. Una vez, etc. (Span.): On one occasion when he was intoxicated.—282. Goyim (Heb.): Nations, Gentiles.—282. Lasan akhades, read Lâshôn haqqôdesh: Sacred language, i.e., Hebrew.—282. Janin: Wine in Heb. is yâyim (not yânin), but our author quoted correctly from the Dialoghi di Amore composti per Leone Medico, Vinegia, 1541, and the Span. ed. (which I use): Los Dialogos de Amor de mestre Leon Abarbanel medico y Filosofo excelente, Venetia, 1568, sm. 410 (Bodleian). The passage is: “And he (Noah), after the flood, was called Janus on account of his invention of wine, for Janin in Hebrew signifies wine, and he is represented with two faces turned in opposite directions, because he saw before the flood and after it”. [566] G. B. always writes Abarbenel for Abarbanel. His true name was Leo Abrabanel.—282. Janinoso (Judæo-Span.) meaning vinosus, intoxicated.—283. Epicouraiyim: Christians, as below, the “Epicureans,” for so the rabbis of the East call us in the West—properly, “unbelievers”. But Borrow’s form is not found in Buxtorf (1869)—read [unknown Hebrew text] Epikûrôsîn and (pop.) Epikûrîn.—285. Sephardim: Spanish and Portuguese Jews, as the Ashkenazim are the German Jews.—290 to 301. I am at . . .: Greenwich, Blackheath and Shooter’s Hill (301).—304. Colonel B. . . .: Col. Blood. See Celebrated Trials, vol. ii., pp. 248-354: “Thomas Blood, generally called Colonel Blood, who stole the crown from the Tower of London, 1671”.—317. Got fare to . . ., read Amesbury, Wilts.—323. City of the Spire: Salisbury.—325. From . . ., read Bristol.—330. Stranger: Could not be William Beckford (1759-1844) of Fonthill Park, three miles from Hinton, a dozen or fifteen miles from Salisbury. Besides the place was sold in 1822 and George Mortimer occupied it in 1825. Borrow had been walking five days in a N.W. direction from Salisbury, and all his narrative harmonises with the places and dates that bring him to Horncastle in August, 1825—362. Abedariums, read abecedariums.—363. Flaming Tinman: He is also called by Borrow, Blazing Tinman, Flying Tinker, Blazing Bosville or Boswell, and finally Anselo Herne, his true clan-name.—367. Ten years ago, i.e., thirteen, when he was at Tamworth in April or May, 1812.—377. The Romany chi, etc.: See p. 387 for the translation.—379. Answer to the gillie: The Rommany churl and the Rommany girl love thieving and spaeing and lying and everything but honesty and truth.—390. Peth yw, etc. (W.): What is that lying there on the ground? Yn wirionedd, in truth, surely.—390. Gwenwyn: Poison! Poison! the lad has been poisoned!—394. Hanged the mayor: The suppressed name of the Welshman and the whole account of the affair is given in Wild Wales, p. 7 (chapter iii).—404. Bardd Cwsg: The Sleeping Bard, by Ellis Wynn. See Bibliog.—421. Merddin Wyllt (Myrddin): i.e., Wild Merlin, called the Wizard.—423. Found written: See Moll Flanders by Defoe, p. 188, ed. 1722: “Oh! what a felicity is it to mankind,” said I, “that they cannot see into the hearts of one another!” I have carefully re-read the whole volume of Moll Flanders, and find no such passages as those referred to here, save the one above. Hence, we may justly infer that Borrow quoted the spirit, rather than the words, of his author. See Romany Rye, pp. 305-6.—431. Catraeth, read Cattraeth. The reference is to Aneurin’s book, the Gododin, or Battle of Cattraeth. See Bibliog.—432. Fish or flesh: See Borrow’s Targum, St. Petersb., 1835, p. 76, under the “History of Taliesin,” ending:—

“I saw the end with horror
Of Sodom and Gomorrah!
And with this very eye
Have seen the [Trinity];
I till the judgment day
Upon the earth shall stray:
None knows for certainty
Whether fish or flesh I be.”

The original Welsh of the “Hanes Taliesin” is in the Gorchestion Beirdd Cymru, 1773—Bibliog. at the end of Romany Rye.—432. Take this: This Bible, with Peter Williams’ name in it, was sold in London in 1886 out of Geo. Borrow’s collection.—443. Mumpers’ Dingle: Near Willenhall, Staffordshire. The place is properly Momber or Monmer Lane, and is now occupied by the “Monmer Lane Ironworks,” hence totally obliterated.—444. Volundr (Völundr): The Wayland Smith of Northern legends. See in the Bibliog. under “Wayland Smith,” and Mallet, p. 570.—456. Ingeborg: The lines are from the Romantic Ballads of 1826, p. 58, entitled the “Heroes of Dovrefeld. From the old Danish.”—456. “As I was jawing:” Text and translation of the whole eight lines are found on pp. 182-83 of the Lavo-Lil, 1874:—

As I to the town was going one day
My Roman lass I met by the way.

The MS. is somewhat different—“Rommany” instead of Roman, and the last line, “If you will share my lot with me”.—469. The man in black: This priest seems to have been a Fraser of Lovat. See Romany Rye, p. 25, and “Arbuthnot” in the Bibliog.—481. Armenian: It must be remembered that Borrow’s Armenian was limited to the Introduction, Grammar and Lat.-Arm. Dict. of the Jesuit Joseph Villotte, 1714, fol., which he picked up at Norwich in 1822-23 as he tells us on p. 175, and Romany Rye, p. 92. Hence all his examples are taken from that book—mi, one; yergou, two; yerek, three, and those in Romany Rye.—482. Buona sera (It.): Good evening.—482. Per far visita, etc.: To pay your lordship a call, that is my motive.—486. Che io non, etc., read ch’ in, etc.: That I do not believe at all.—488. Addio: Farewell.—497. Pulci: See the Bibliog. This version is rather free and local. Here is the original (canto xviii., f. 97, ed. 1546):—

Rispose allhor Margutte: “A dirtel tosto,
Io non credo piu al nero ch’ a l’azzurro,
Ma nel cappone, o lesso, o, vuogli, arrosto,
E credo alcuna volta anco nel burro,
Nella cervogia, e, quando io n’ho, nel mosto,
E molto pui nell’ aspro che il mangurro,
Ma sopra tutto nel buon vino ho fede,
E credo che sia salvo chi gli crede.”

503. O Cavaliere, etc.: Oh, Sir Walter, ye have wrought much in behalf of the Holy See!—504. Poveri frati: Poor friars!—508. One fellow I met: See the postillion’s story on pp. 536-48.—513. Master in Arm. is d’yèr; of a master, d’yearn; pl., d’yeark.—515. Koul Adonai, read Kôl A. The next quotation is from part of verse 4 of the xxixth Psalm, which he gives according to the prayer-book version.

printed by
hazell, watson and viney, ld.,
london and aylesbury

Footnotes to Lavengro:

[0a] We are all relations, all alike; all who are with us are ourselves.

[0b] Chal is simply the contraction of chavál, a form cognate with chavoró the diminutive of chavó, a lad. Chavál is still common in Spain, both among the Gypsies and the lower orders of Spaniards.—Ed.

[1a] MS., “On the fifth day of July, 1803, at East D---, a beautiful little town in the western division of Norfolk, I first saw the light”.

[1b] “In Cornwall are the best gentlemen.”—Corn. Prov.

[2a] MS., “after being insulted by him”.

[2b] So in MSS.; “manly,” an erratum.

[3] MS., “Orford”.

[13] Norwegian ells—about eight feet.

[23] MS., “in regimental slang”.

[34] MS., “Ambrose” throughout the book.

[81] MS., “like the philologist Scaliger, who, though acquainted with the exact value of every word in the Latin language, could see no beauty in the ‘Enchantments of Canidia,’ the masterpiece of the prince of Roman poets. What knew he,” etc.

[112] MS. note: “Written in 1843”.

[115] MS., “à Monsieur Peyrecourt” or “Pierrecourt”.

[126] MS., “Simpson”.

[137] Klopstock.

[158] MS., “John Thurtell”.

[185] MS., “Bartlett”.

[187] MS., “Saviour”.

[190] MS., “High Tory principles”.

[201] MS., “Arden” throughout.

[210] The MS. develops this paragraph as follows:—

So Francis Ardry called upon me, and right glad I was that he did so; and after we had sat conversing for some time, he said, “Did you ever see Kean?”

“No,” said I, “but I have heard both of him and of Belcher. I should like to see either, especially the latter. Where are they to be found?”

“I know nothing of the latter,” said Frank, “but if you wish to see Kean, you had better come with me where he will appear to-night after a long absence. The public are anxiously waiting for him, intending to pelt him off the stage.”

“And what has he done,” said I, “to be pelted off the stage?”

“What is very naughty,” said Frank; “breaking one of the commandments.”

“And did he break the commandment on the stage?”

“No,” said Frank, “I never heard that he broke it on the stage, except in the way of his profession.”

“Then, what have the public to do with the matter?”

“They think they have,” said Frank.

And then we went out together to see Shakespeare’s “Richard,” or rather we went to see the man who was to personate Shakespeare’s “Richard”—and so did thousands; we did not see him, however. There was a great tumult, I remember, in the theatre. The man who was to perform the part of Richard, and who it was said was the best hand for interpreting the character that had ever appeared on the stage, had a short time before been involved in a disgraceful affair, and this was to be his first appearance on the stage since the discovery. The consequence was that crowds flocked to the theatre with the firm intention of expressing their indignation. “We will pelt his eyes out,” said a man who sat beside me in the pit—for we sat in the pit—and who bore the breach of all the commandments in his face. The actor in question, however, who perhaps heard the threats which were vented against him, very prudently kept out of the way, and the manager coming forward informed the public that another would perform the part—whereupon there was a great uproar. “We have been imposed upon,” said the individual who sat beside me. “I came here for nothing else than to pelt that scoundrel off the stage.” The uproar, however, at length subsided, and the piece commenced. In a little time there was loud applause. The actor who had appeared in place of the other was performing. “What do you clap for?” said I to the individual by my side, who was clapping most of all. “What do I clap for?” said the man. “Why, to encourage Macready, to be sure. Don’t you see how divinely he acts? why, he beats Kean hollow. Besides that, he’s a moral man, and I like morality.” “Do you mean to say,” said I, “that he was never immoral?” “I neither know nor care,” said the man; “all I know is that he has never been found out. It will never do to encourage a public man who has been found out. No, no! the morality of the stage must be seen after.”

[212] MS. “Charlie” and “Charlie’s” throughout.

[222] The MS. adds: “‘It will, perhaps, be as well, first of all, to go to the exhibition of British art, which is at present open. I hear he has a picture there, which he has just finished. We will look at it, and from that you may form a tolerable estimate of his powers.’ Thereupon my brother led the way, and we presently found ourselves in the Gallery of British Art.”

[231] Arden throughout the MS.

[232] The text is: “Malheur, as the French say, that it is so choked”.

[235] “Bishop Sharpe,” a pugilist of that name and time.

[236] Three are after my death.

[249] MS. (apparently) “L---,” but see p. 276.

[250a] MS., “is quite as rational an amusement as politics”.

[250b] Le Noir in MS. A, and in Rom. Rye, app.

[251a] MS., “L---,” or “T.”

[251b] MS., “Canning”.

[350] MS., “The Times”.

[484] MS. “Lord A[berdeen]”.

[553] The one sole emendation consists in substituting the masc. cheval for the fem. jument, on p. 314. Le jument est beau was a solecism that could not longer be tolerated.

[555] Boxiana, ii., 497.

[565] Beginning—

Mas tinn no slán atharlaigheas féin,
Do ghluàis me trá, agus bfhéirde mé,
Air cuáirt an Seóin le sócal dfhághail,
“An Stafartach saímh, nach gnáth gan chéill.”

[566] “El qual (Noé) despues del diluuio, por su inuencion del uino, fue lhamado lano, porque Ianin en ebràico quiere dezir uino, y lo pintan con dos caras boltadas, porque tuuo uista antes del diluuio y despues” (Foja 71, verso).

FOOTNOTES to Romany Rye.

[0a] MS., “’49”.

[0b] MS., “execrated by every unmanly scoundrel, every sycophantic lacquey, and every political and religious renegade in Britain”.

[24] Cf. L’Inferno, xxvii., 25.

[42] The apothecary.

[46a] MS., see Life, i., 34, n.

[46b] Ibid.

[284] Tipperary.

[311a] MS., “Canning” (1827).

[311b] Viscount Goderich.

[311c] MS., “Canning” (1827).

[311d] MS., “Canning” (1827).

[312a] MS., “who eventually presented him with a bishopric, had espoused,” etc.

[312b] MS., “He is a small landed proprietor who eats,” etc.

[312c] MS., “the Despatch, of course”.

[312d] The Spanish Revolution of ’54–’56, made by O’Donnell.

[313] MS. (corrected):—

Un Erajái
Sinába chibando an sermón;
Y lle falta un balichó
Al chindomá de aquel gáo;
Y chanéla que los calés
Lo habían nicobáo;
Y penelá ’l erajái:
“Chaboró!
Guíllate á tu quer,
Y nicobéla la pirí
Que teréla ’l balichó,
Y chibéla andró
Una lima de tun chaborí,
Chaborí,
Una lima de tun chaborí.”

See also Lavo-Lil, p. 200.

[316a] Canto i, st. 53.

[316b] St. 57.

[318] An obscene oath.

[319] See Muses’ Library, pp. 86, 87. London, 1738. [Better, the original ed. (1547). See Notes.]

[320] Genteel with them seems to be synonymous with Gentile and Gentoo; if so, the manner in which it has been applied for ages ceases to surprise, for genteel is heathenish. Ideas of barbaric pearl and gold, glittering armour, plumes, tortures, blood-shedding, and lust, should always be connected with it. Wace, in his grand Norman poem, calls the Baron Genteel:—

“La furent li gentil Baron,” etc.

And he certainly could not have applied the word better than to the strong Norman thief, armed cap-a-pie without one particle of ruth or generosity; for a person to be a pink of gentility, that is heathenism, should have no such feelings; and, indeed, the admirers of gentility seldom or never associate any such feelings with it. It was from the Norman, the worst of all robbers and miscreants, who built strong castles, garrisoned them with devils, and tore out poor wretches’ eyes, as the Saxon Chronicle says, that the English got their detestable word genteel. What could ever have made the English such admirers of gentility, it would be difficult to say; for, during three hundred years, they suffered enough by it. Their genteel Norman landlords were their scourgers, their torturers, the plunderers of their homes, the dishonourers of their wives, and the deflowers of their daughters. Perhaps after all, fear is at the root of the English veneration for gentility.

[323] Gentle and gentlemanly may be derived from the same root as genteel; but nothing can be more distinct from the mere genteel, than the ideas which enlightened minds associate with these words. Gentle and gentlemanly mean something kind and genial; genteel, that which is glittering or gaudy. A person can be a gentleman in rags, but nobody can be genteel.

[342] The writer has been checked in print by the Scotch with being a Norfolk man. Surely, surely, these latter times have not been exactly the ones in which it was expedient for Scotchmen to check the children of any county in England with the place of their birth, more especially those who have had the honour of being born in Norfolk—times in which British fleets, commanded by Scotchmen, have returned laden with anything but laurels from foreign shores. It would have been well for Britain had she had the old Norfolk man to despatch to the Baltic or the black Sea, lately, instead of Scotch admirals.

[364] As the present work will come out in the midst of a vehement political contest, people may be led to suppose that the above was written expressly for the time. The writer therefore begs to state that it was written in the year 1854. He cannot help adding that he is neither Whig, Tory, nor Radical, and cares not a straw what party governs England, provided it is governed well. But he has no hopes of good government from the Whigs. It is true that amongst them there is one very great man, Lord Palmerston, who is indeed the sword and buckler, the chariots and the horses of the party; but it is impossible for his lordship to govern well with such colleagues as he has—colleagues which have been forced upon him by family influence, and who are continually pestering him into measures anything but conducive to the country’s honour and interest. If Palmerston would govern well, he must get rid of them; but from that step, with all his courage and all his greatness, he will shrink. Yet how proper and easy a step it would be! He could easily get better, but scarcely worse, associates. They appear to have one object in view and only one—jobbery. It was chiefly owing to a most flagitious piece of jobbery, which one of his lordship’s principal colleagues sanctioned and promoted, that his lordship experienced his late parliamentary disasters.

[369] A fact.

[372a] MS. “Aberdeen.”

[372b] MS. “Aberdeen.”

[383] Like Ingilis in Turkish, for English; Beritania (England) in Hawaiian, for Britannia.

[386a] Zincali, 1843, second ed., vol. ii., p. 146.*

[386b] “I think I’ll go there,” p. 301. “He is about to quit his native land on a grand philological expedition,” p. 303.

The Editor’s Postscript

Lavengro and The Romany Rye (properly Romanó Ráï) were terms applied to George Borrow in his youth by the Norfolk Gypsy, Ambrose Smith, better known in these volumes as Jasper Petulengro. The names signify respectively “Philologist” and “the Gypsy Gentleman.” The two works thus entitled constitute a more or less exact autobiography of the writer of them, from the date of his birth to the end of August, 1825. The author himself confesses in his Preface that “the time embraces nearly the first quarter of the present century.”

Lavengro was written at Oulton, in Suffolk, slowly and at intervals, between the years 1842 and 1851. The MSS. exist in three varieties: 1. The primitive draft of a portion, found scattered through sundry notebooks and on isolated scraps of paper, as described in the letter to Dawson Turner (Life, I, p. 394) 2. The definitive autograph text in one thick quarto volume. 3. The transcript for the printers, made by Mrs. Borrow, in one large folio volume, interlarded with the author’s additions and corrections.

The text of the present edition reproduces with fidelity the first issue of 1851. Occasionally a verbal alteration, introduced by the author himself into his second edition of 1872, has been adopted in this, whenever it seemed to improve the reading. In general, however, that reprint was in many respects a defective one. Not only words, but even whole sentences, which had escaped the printers, remained undetected by the editor, and, as a consequence, were lost to later impressions, based, as they all have been, on that issue. We should have preferred to alter, quietly and without remark, certain errors in the text, as we did in the documents published in the Life; but save in a single instance, we have left such inaccuracies intact, reserving all corrections for the place where we might be supposed to exercise a free hand.[217]

The insertion, with brackets of course, of the promised inedited episodes, caused in two cases some embarrassment. In removing them from the final form of his MS., Mr. Borrow closed up the gap with a few fitting lines which concealed the withdrawal. These words had to be suppressed on the restoration of the passages.

The insertions will be met with as follows:—

The Poet Parkinson, pp. 119–25.

The Wake of Freya, pp. 128–33.

Cromwell’s Statue and the Dairyman’s Daughter, pp. 196–98.

Portobello or the Irish Patriot, pp. 231–39.

Thomas d’Éterville, in the Notes, pp. 558–59.

Thus we have made a full statement as regards the text of the present reprint. Anyone who takes up this edition will discover no visible name, or preface, or introduction, save only those of George Borrow, from the title to the close. The book is, therefore, “all Borrow,” and we have sought to render the helping hand as inconspicuous as possible. Should, however, the prejudiced stumble at the Notes, we can say in the language of the fairy smith of Loughmore: is agad an t-leigheas, you have the remedy in your own power.

Speaking of the Notes, they have been drawn up on the unimpeachable testimony of contemporaneous record. Especially have we sought the works which Mr. Borrow was accustomed to read in his younger days, and at times with curious results. [...] What is not here explained can be easily looked up in our Life, Writings, and Correspondence of George Borrow, London, 1899, which of itself furnishes a sufficient and unalterable exhibition of the facts concerning the man and his work.

W. I. Knapp.

High St., Oxford,
November, 1899.

Endnotes

We are all relations, all alike; all who are with us are ourselves. ↩

Chal is simply the contraction of chavál, a form cognate with chavoró the diminutive of chavó, a lad. Chavál is still common in Spain, both among the Gypsies and the lower orders of Spaniards.

—Knapp

↩

East D⸺: East Dereham, a small town in Norfolk, 16 miles west of Norwich, and 102 northeast of London. Here Capt. Thomas Borrow, the father of George, was often stationed from 1792 to 1812.

—Knapp

↩

East Anglia: This Anglo-Saxon kingdom comprised the present counties of Norfolk, Suffolk and Cambridge.

—Knapp

↩

MS., “On the fifth day of July, 1803, at East D⸺, a beautiful little town in the western division of Norfolk, I first saw the light.”

—Knapp

↩

Tredinnock, read “Trethinnick;” Parish of St. Cleer, Cornwall.

—Knapp

↩

“In Cornwall are the best gentlemen.”

—Corn. Prov.

↩

MS., “after being insulted by him.”

—Knapp

↩

So in MSS.; “manly,” an erratum.

—Knapp

↩

Big Ben: Benjamin Brain or Bryan was born in 1753. Some of his most severe “battles” were fought between 1780 and 1790—one on the 30th of August in the latter year, with Hooper at Newbury, Berks. A few days after this exploit, he picked a quarrel with Sergeant Borrow of the Coldstream Guards, which resulted in the Hyde Park encounter. Some four months later, i.e., 17th January, 1791, the decisive fight for the championship came off between Brain and Johnson. It was an appalling spectacle, and struck dumb with horror, even in that day, the witnesses to the dreadful conflict. Big Ben was the victor, and remained champion of England from that date until his death three years (not “four months”) later—8th April, 1794. “Lavengro,” carried away by the enthusiasm of early reminiscence, allowed himself to declare that his father read the Bible to Brain in his latter moments. But in 1794 Thomas Borrow was busy recruiting soldiers in Norfolk, one hundred miles from the scene of the dying pugilist. However, the error was probably one of date merely, and during the year 1791 Thomas doubtless read the Bible to him in London, since we learn from Pierce Egan that “Ben derived great consolation from hearing the Bible read, and generally solicited those of his acquaintance who called upon him to read a chapter to him.”[409]

—Knapp

↩

Captain: The West Norfolk Militia was raised in 1759 by the third Earl of Orford.He died in December, 1791, when the regiment was reorganised (not “raised”) under the new Colonel, the Hon. Horatio Walpole, subsequently the sixth Earl of Orford. Thus in February, 1792, Thomas was transferred from the Guards to be Sergeant-major in the W.N.M., and stationed at East Dereham. He married the following year, became Quartermaster (with the rank of Ensign) in 1795, and Adjutant (Lieutenant) in February, 1798. This his final promotion doubtless gave him the honorary rank of Captain, since in the Monthly Army List for 1804 we read: “Adjutant, Thomas Borrow, Capt.” But a letter before me dated 18th April, 1799, from his Major, is officially addressed to him as “Lieut. Borrow, Adjutant,” etc., etc.

—Knapp

↩

MS., “Orford.”

—Knapp

↩

Petrement: Our author knew very well that his mother’s maiden name was Ann Perfrement, pronounced and written Parfrement at the present day by those of the family we have met. The correct spelling is found on the tombstone of her sister, Sarah, at Dereham (1817), and on that of her brother, Samuel, at Salthouse near Holt (1864).

—Knapp

↩

Castle of De Burgh: A fanciful Borrovian epithet applied to Norwich Castle. Nor did the exiles build the Church of St. Mary-the-Less, in Queen Street, Norwich; it was a distinct parish church long before Elizabeth’s reign, and in her time the parish was consolidated with the neighbouring one of St. George’s, Tombland, while the church became municipal property. But the French exiles of the Edict of 1685 did worship there, even as did the Dutch refugees from Alva’s persecution a century before (1565–70).

—Knapp

↩

Middle Age: Borrow’s father was thirty-four, and his mother twenty-one, at the date of their marriage. John was born seven years after the marriage, and George ten. The mother was, then, thirty-one at George’s birth.

—Knapp

↩

Bishop Hopkins: Sermons.

—Knapp

↩

Angola: More correctly “Angora.”

—Knapp

↩

Foreign grave: Lieut. John Thomas Borrow died at Guanajuato, Mexico, 22nd November, 1833.

—Knapp

↩

“Snorro” Sturleson: Poet and historian of Iceland (1178–1241). Harald (not “Harold”) III, called “Haardraade.” Battle of Stamford Bridge, 1066 AD, same year as Norman Conquest. See Mallet’s Northern Antiquities, pp. 168–71 and 194; Snorro’s Heimskringla, II, p. 164, and his Chronica, 1633, p. 381, for the quotation.

—Knapp

↩

Norwegian ells—about eight feet. ↩

Winchester: Rather “Winchelsea,” according to the Regimental Records.

—Knapp

↩

A gallant frigate: A reminiscence of Norman Cross gossip in 1810–11. “Ninety-eight French prisoners, the crew of a large French privateer of eighteen guns called the Contre-Amiral Magon, and commanded by the notorious Blackman, were captured 16th October, 1804, by Capt. Hancock of the Cruiser sloop, and brought into Yarmouth. They marched into Norwich, 26th November, and the next morning proceeded under guard on their way to Norman Cross barracks”—Norwich Papers, 1804.

—Knapp

↩

Lady Bountiful: Dame Eleanor Fenn (1743–1813).

—Knapp

↩

Bard: William Cowper (1731–1800).

—Knapp

↩

Some Saint: Withburga, daughter of Anna, king of the East Angles, was the “saint” and the “daughter” at the same time.

—Knapp

↩

Hunchbacked rhymer: Alexander Pope.

—Knapp

↩

Properties of God, read “attributes.”

—Knapp

↩

Rector: The Rev. F. J. H. Wollaston.

—Knapp

↩

Philoh: James Philo (1745–1829).

—Knapp

↩

Tolerism, read “toleration.”

—Knapp

↩

MS., “in regimental slang.”

—Knapp

↩

Mere: Whittlesea Mere, long since drained.

—Knapp

↩

Bengui: See the glossary for all Gypsy words.

—Editor

↩

MS., “Ambrose” throughout the book.[410]

—Knapp

↩

Three years: Included in the subsequent narrative, not excluded from it as his Norwich school days (1814–15, 1816–18) were. They extend from July, 1811, to April, 1813—from Norman Cross to Edinburgh. The chronology, according to the Regimental Records, was as follows: George was at East Dereham from 22nd July to 18th November, 1811, at J. S. Buck’s (“Dr. B.’s”) school; 30th November, 1811, to February, 1812, at Colchester; 28th February to 5th March, 1812, at Harwich; 15th to 19th March, at Leicester; 21st to 30th March, at Melton Mowbray; 2nd to 25th April, at Leicester again; 28th April to 3rd May, at Tamworth; 8th to 26th May, at Macclesfield; 28th May to 2nd August, at Stockport; 3rd to 23rd August, at Ashton; 24th August to 15th December, at Huddersfield; 16th December, 1812, to 19th March, 1813, at Sheffield; 20th and 21st March, 1813, at Leeds; 22nd March, at Wetherby; 23rd March, Boroughbridge; 24th March, Allerton; 25th March, Darlington; 26th March, Durham (Wild Wales, pp. 258–59); 27th and 28th March, Newcastle; 29th March, Morpeth; 30th March, Alnwick; 3rd and 4th April, at Berwick-upon-Tweed; 6th April, 1813, Edinburgh Castle.

—Knapp

↩

William Lilly: A Shorte Introdvction of Grammar, generally to be vsed in the Kynges Maiesties dominions, for the bryngynge up of all those that inteade to atteyne the knowlege of the Latine tongue (1549).

—Knapp

↩

Bank of a river: The Tweed. The scene here described occurred on a Sunday, 4th April, 1813, near Berwick, where they “arrived the preceding night”

—Knapp

↩

Elvir Hill: See Borrow’s Romantic Ballads, Norwich, 1826, pp. 111–14. This piece entitled “Elvir Hill,” one of the old Danish ballads of Vedel’s collection, 1591, represents the dangers attending a youth who “rested” his “head upon Elvir Hill’s side” where he was so charmed in his sleep by a brace of seductive fairies, that:

“If my good luck had not managed it so
That the cock crew out then in the distance,
I should have been murder’d by them on the Hill,
Without power to offer resistance.

“ ’Tis therefore I counsel each young Danish swain
Who may ride in the forest so dreary,
Ne’er to lay down upon lone Elvir Hill
Though he chance to be ever so weary.”

—Knapp

↩

Skaldaglam: The barditus of Tacitus, or the “din” made by the Norse “bards” (skalds) on shields and with shouts as they rushed into battle. It is not in Molbech, but Snorro frequently uses it in his Chronica, 1633.

—Knapp

↩

Kalevala: Title of the great Finnish epic, of which the hero is Woinomöinen.

—Knapp

↩

Polak: Polander or Pole.

—Knapp

↩

Magyar (pronounced “Mädjr”): Hungarian.

—Knapp

↩

Batuscha: An erratum of the author for his “Batuschca” (161)—better “Batyushca,” “father Tsar”—but generally applied by Borrow to his friend the Pope.

—Knapp

↩

Bui hin Digri: The Jomsburg Viking, 994 AD. See Borrow’s Romantic Ballads, p. 136, and Once a Week, IX, p. 686. The account is given in Snorro’s Chronica, 1633, p. 136 (see Snorre Sturlesøns Norake Kongers Chronica. Vdaat paa Danske / aff H. Peder Claussøn. Kiöbenhavn, 1633), but a more accessible version of it is found in Mallet’s Northern Antiquities (Bohn’s edition), pp. 144–45.

—Knapp

↩

Horunga Vog, read “Hjörúnga Vâgr” in Icelandic, or “Vaag” in Danish. In Romany Rye it is Englished as “Horinger Bay.”

—Knapp

↩

Hickathrift: A Norfolk worthy of the eleventh century, whose prodigious exploits with the axle of his cart as an offensive weapon, and the wheel as a shield, are handed down in the chap-books of the last three centuries.

—Knapp

↩

Elzigood: William E., of Heigham, Norwich, enlisted October, 1789, became Drum-major in the regiment, 22nd October, 1802; called facetiously or maliciously “Else-than-gude” [a few pages later].

—Knapp

↩

O’Hanlon: Redmond O’Hanlon (died 1681), a proprietor of Ulster, dispossessed under the Cromwellian settlement, and afterwards leader of a band of outlaws.

—Knapp

↩

See Life, Writings, and Correspondence of George Borrow, London, 1899, I, pp. 39–43.

—Knapp

↩

Disbanded: The W.N.M. regiment left Edinburgh in July, 1814, and was disembodied at Norwich, 19th July. It was again called out, 10th July, 1815, and sent to Ireland. John Borrow was appointed Ensign, 29th May, 1815, and Lieutenant, 13th December of the same year. The regiment sailed from Harwich (“port in Essex”) 31st August, reaching Cork harbour (“the cove”) about 9th September, 1815.

—Knapp

↩

Wight Wallace: The Life and Acts of Sir William Wallace, of Ellerslie. By Henry the Minstrel. (Published from a MS. of 1488 with Notes by Dr. Jamieson.) Edinburgh, 1820. This rhymed “Storybook of Wight Wallace” is in twelve parts or books.

—Knapp

↩

Shorsha: The Irish for “George,” properly written “Seors,” but the author usually wrote his Irish by sound.

—Knapp

↩

Saggart, read “sagart:” (Lat. sacerdos), a priest.

—Knapp

↩

Finn-ma-Coul: In Irish Fionn-mac-Cumhail, the father of Ossian.

—Knapp

↩

Brian Boroo: In Irish, Brian Boroimhe, a king of Ireland (926–1014).

—Knapp

↩

Saggarting: Studying with reference to the priesthood.

—Knapp

↩

Mavourneen: Properly “mo mhuirnin,” my darling.

—Knapp

↩

Hanam mon Dioul: Wrongly given for “M’anam o’n Diabhal” [God preserve] my soul from the devil! See Romany Rye, where it is quite correct—from sound.

—Knapp

↩

Christmas over: 1816. Regiment quartered at Templemore. John, now a lieutenant (not “ensign”), is sent with a detachment to Loughmore, three miles away. Sergeant Bagg, promoted to that rank, 10th July, 1815, accompanies him.

—Knapp

↩

Mountain: Called locally, “Devil’s Bit,” and not Devil’s Hill or Mountain, as in the text.

—Knapp

↩

Fine old language:

“A labhair Padric ’nninsè Fail na Riogh
’San faighe caomhsin Colum naomhtha ’n I.”

[which] “Patrick spoke in Innisfail to heathen chiefs of old,
And Columb, the mild prophet-saint, spoke in his island-hold.”

So Borrow gives the Irish and his version in Romantic Ballads, p. VIII. The Erse lines were taken from Lhuyd’s Archaeologia Britannica, Oxford, 1707.

—Knapp

↩

The Castle: Loughmore Castle.

—Knapp

↩

Figure of a man: Jerry Grant, the Irish outlaw. See the Newgate Calendars subsequent to 1840—Pelham. Griffith, etc.

—Knapp

↩

“Sas” and “Sassanach,” of course mean Englishman or English (Saxon).

—Knapp

↩

Clergyman of the parish: The Rev. Patrick Kennedy, vicar of Loughmore. His name is also on the list of subscribers to the Romantic Ballads, Norwich, 1826, as J. Kennedy, by mistake.

—Knapp

↩

Swanton Morley: A village near East Dereham.

—Knapp

↩

MS., “like the philologist Scaliger, who, though acquainted with the exact value of every word in the Latin language, could see no beauty in the ‘Enchantments of Canidia,’ the masterpiece of the prince of Roman poets. What knew he,” etc.

—Knapp

↩

Arrigod yuit (Irish), read “airgiod dhuit:” Have you any money?

—Knapp

↩

Tabhair chugam (pronounced “tower khoogam”): Give (it) to me.

—Knapp

↩

Is agam an’t leigeas (read “an t-leigheas”): I have the remedy.

—Knapp

↩

Another word: deaghbhlasda: See Romany Rye, p. 266, and Notes and Queries, 5th May, 1855, p. 339, article by George Métivier.

—Knapp

↩

Old city: Norwich. The regiment having returned to headquarters, 11th May, 1816, was mustered out 17th June. The author describes the city from the “ruined wall” of the old Priory on the hill to the east.

—Knapp

↩

The Norman Bridge: is Bishop’s Bridge.

—Knapp

↩

Sword of Cordova, in Guild Hall, is a mistake for the sword of the Spanish General Don Xavier Winthuysen.

—Knapp

↩

Vone banished priest: Rev. Thomas d’Éterville. The MS. gives the following inedited account of D’Éterville. I omit the oft-recurring expletive sacré (accursed):—

Myself. Were you not yourself forced to flee from your country?

D’Éterville. That’s very true. … I became one vagabond—nothing better, I assure you, my dear; had you seen me, you would have said so. I arrive at Douvres; no welcome. I walk to Canterbury and knock at the door of one auberge. The landlord opens. “What do you here?” he says; “who are you?” “Vone exiled priest,” I reply. “Get you gone, sirrah!” he says; “we have beggars enough of our own,” and he slams the door in my face. Ma foi, il faisoit bien, for my toe was sticking through my shoe.

Myself. But you are no longer a vagabond, and your toe does not stick through your shoe now.

D’Éterville. No, thank God, the times are changed. I walked and walked, till I came here, where I became one philologue and taught tongues—French and Italian. I found good friends here, those of my religion. “He very good man,” they say; “one banished priest; we must help him.” I am no longer a vagabond—ride a good horse when I go to visit pupils in the country—stop at auberge—landlord comes to the door: “What do you please to want, sir?” “Only to bait my horse, that is all.” Eh bien, landlord very polite; he not call me vagabond; I carry pistols in my pocket.

Myself. I know you do; I have often seen them. But why do you carry pistols?

D’Éterville. I ride along the road from the distant village. I have been to visit my pupil whom I instruct in philology. My pupil has paid me my bill, and I carry in my purse the fruits of my philology. I come to one dark spot. Suddenly my bridle is seized, and one tall robber stands at my horse’s head with a very clumsy club in his hand. “Stand, rascal,” says he; “your life or your purse!” “Very good, sir,” I respond; “there you have it.” So I put my hand, not into my pocket, but into my holster; I draw out, not my purse, but my weapon, and—bang! I shoot the English robber through the head.

Myself. It is a bad thing to shed blood; I should be loth to shoot a robber to save a purse.

D’Éterville. Que tu es bête! mon ami. Am I to be robbed of the fruits of my philology, made in foreign land, by one English robber? Shall I become once more one vagabond as of old? one exiled priest turned from people’s doors, my shoe broken, toe sticking through it, like that bad poet who put the Pope in hell? Bah, bah!

By degrees D’Éterville acquired a considerable fortune for one in his station. Some people go so far as to say that it was principally made by an extensive contraband trade in which he was engaged. Be this as it may, some twenty years from the time of which I am speaking, he departed this life, and shortly before his death his fellow-religionists, who knew him to be wealthy, persuaded him to make a will, by which he bequeathed all his property to certain popish establishments in England. In his last hours, however, he repented, destroyed his first will, and made another, in which he left all he had to certain of his relations in his native country;—“for,” said he, “they think me one fool, but I will show them that they are mistaken. I came to this land one banished priest, where I made one small fortune; and now I am dying, to whom should I leave the fruits of my philology but to my blood-relations? In God’s name, let me sign. Monsieur Boileau left the fruits of his verses to his niece; eh bien, I will bequeath the fruits of my philology to my niece and nephew. There, there! thanks be to God, it is done! They take me for a fool; I am no fool. Leave to the Pope the fruits of my philology! Bah, bah! I do no such thing. I do like Monsieur Boileau.”

—Knapp

↩

Earl’s Home: Earlham Hall, the residence of Joseph John Gurney (1788–1847), the Norwich banker and famous Quaker. The “tall figure” mentioned on the next page was Mr. Gurney, then twenty-eight years of age.

—Knapp

↩

Only read Greek: This is a mistake. Mr. Gurney was an early student of Italian. See Braithwaite’s Life, I.

—Knapp

↩

Zohar: Very correct. Braithwaite, I.

—Knapp

↩

Abarbenel, read Abarbanel or Abrabanel: A Spanish Jew driven from Spain in 1492.

—Knapp

↩

Castle Hill: Norwich.

—Knapp

↩

Fair of horses: Tombland Fair, held on Maundy Thursday every year.

—Knapp

↩

Heath: Mousehold Heath, near Norwich.

—Knapp

↩

Gemiti, sospiri ed alti guai, (compare Dante, Inferno, III, 8: “Quivi sospiri, pianti, e alti guai.”): Groans, sighs, and deep lamentations.

—Knapp

↩

MS. note: “Written in 1843.” ↩

Barddoniaeth Dafydd ab Gwilym. O grynhoad Owen Jones, a William Owen. [The Poetical Works of David ap Gwilym (son of William), edited by O. J. and W. O.] Llundain, 1789.

Translations into English Verse from the Poems of Davyth ap Gwilym, a Welsh Bard of the Fourteenth Century by Arthur J. Johnes. London, 1834.

—Knapp

↩

Cowydd: A species of Welsh poetry.

—Knapp

↩

Bwa Bach: The “little hunchback.”

—Knapp

↩

Narrow Court: Tuck’s Court, St. Giles, Norwich.

—Knapp

↩

Old master: William Simpson of the law firm of Simpson & Rackham, Norwich.

—Knapp

↩

Bon jour: read Bonjour … ! bien des chases de ma part à Monsieur Peyrecourt or Pierrecourt. “Expressions” in this sense (kind regards) is the Spanish expresiones, disguised as French.

—Knapp

↩

MS., “à Monsieur Peyrecourt” or “Pierrecourt.”

—Knapp

↩

Parkinson the poet: This character, who appears for the first time among the inedited episodes of Lavengro, was a real one, although his true name (Parkerson) is given somewhat veiled, as usual with Mr. Borrow. He seems to have been the poet-laureate of farmers, corn-merchants, drovers and publicans, selling his muse to the highest bidder, at first in printed sheets of eight pages, and subsequently gathered into pamphlets of thirty or more pages which he offered for one or two shillings each. They were printed by R. Walker, “near the Duke’s Palace, Norwich,” and sold by “Lane and Walker, St. Andrew’s.” They are without date, but cannot range far from 1818. Here are some specimens of his style: “The Norwich Corn Mart. By J. Parkerson, Junior.”

At one o’clock the busy scene begin,
Quick to the hall they all are posting in;
The cautious merchant takes his stand,
The farmer shows the produce of his land,

etc., for sixty-six lines. “On Mr. L … taking leave of his wife and children, who was sentenced to transportation for fourteen years” (!):—

Hannah, farewell, I’m bound to go,
To taste the bitter draught of woe,

134 lines. “A Description of the Pineapple at Trowse:”—

Both Beauty and Art have exerted their skill,
You will find on a spot near the brow of a hill;
The hill is near Norwich and call’d Bracondale,
I stepped into Vince’s myself to regale,

etc., four pages of that.

—Knapp

↩

Mr. C.: Thomas William Coke, Esq., of Holkham, Earl of Leicester in 1837, and died in 1842.

—Knapp

↩

MS., “Simpson.”

—Knapp

↩

Freya: The Venus of the North was the sister of Frey, according to Mallet (p. 94), and the original sources.

—Knapp

↩

The Wake of Freya: This incident must have occurred to Mrs. Borrow at her home, Dumpling Green, East Dereham, on a Friday night, 5th December, 1783, when she was twelve (not “ten”) years old. Her eldest sister, Elizabeth, would be in her seventeenth year. Friday was then, as now, market day at Dereham. The place was the Blyth farm about one and a half miles (not “three”) from “pretty D.” The superstition referred to in this episode is, or was, a very common one in Norfolk, and even other countries. See the Norfolk Chronicle for 14th May, 1791; Glyde’s Norfolk Garland, pp. 13–14, and George Borrow in the Quarterly Review for January, 1861, p. 62.

—Knapp

↩

To London: Crome (John’s teacher) died at Norwich, 22nd April, 1821; but John could not leave until after the Regimental Training, which closed that year on 26th June; hence his departure may be set down for the last of June, 1821.

—Knapp

↩

Rafael: Note inconsistent spelling with “Raphael” later in the book.

—Editor

↩

Corregio, read “Correggio.”

—Knapp

↩

Klopstock. ↩

Murray and Latroon, the Scotch outlaw and the “English Rogue.” English Rogue: Life of Meriton Latroon, a Witty Extravagant. Being a Compleat History of the Most Eminent Cheats of Both Sexes. London, 1665–80.

—Knapp

↩

Draoitheac, magic, read “draoidheachd”

—Knapp

↩

Muggletonians: Evidently a Borrovian slip here. See Notes and Queries for 3rd April, 1852, p. 320.

—Knapp

↩

Vedel: Anders Sörensen Vedel, first collector of the Kiaempeviser, or Heroic Ballads of the Danes, Copenhagen, 1591.

—Knapp

↩

Interview between William Taylor (21 King Street, Norwich) and George Borrow.

—Knapp

↩

Orm Ungarswayne: “Orm the youthful Swain,” Romantic Ballads, p. 86. But see the Danish ballad “Birting” in Borrow’s Targum, St. Petersburgh, 1835, pp. 59–61, commencing:—

“It was late at evening tide,
Sinks the daystar in the wave,
When alone Orm Ungarswayne
Rode to seek his father’s grave.”

—Knapp

↩

Swayne Vonved: See this piece in Romantic Ballads, pp. 61–81.

—Knapp

↩

Mousha, read “Muça,” in Arabic or “Moshé” in Hebrew; both represent our “Moses.” But the Jew’s name was Levi, according to the MS.

—Knapp

↩

The Fight: Between Painter and Oliver, near North Walsham, 17th July, 1820. This chapter XXIV relates the author’s call on Mr. Petre of Westwick House, which must have been after 20th May, when it was decided that the “battle” should take place within twenty miles of Norwich.

—Knapp

↩

Parr: There were two Parrs, one, Thomas, called “English” or “Old” Parr (1483–1635) who lived 152 years, and Samuel, called the “Greek” Parr (1747–1825,) who had been Head Master of the Norwich Grammar School from 1778 to 1785. This Dr. Samuel Parr was the one referred to by Mr. Petre.

—Knapp

↩

Whiter: Rev. Walter Whiter, author of the Commentary on Shakespeare, London 1794, and Etymologicum Magnum, Cambridge, 1800.

—Knapp

↩

Game Chicken: Henry Pierce, nicknamed Game Chicken, beat Gulley, 8th October, 1805 (Egan’s Boxiana, I, p. 145).

—Knapp

↩

Sporting Gentlemen: John Thurtell and Edward Painter (“Ned Flatnose”).

—Knapp

↩

Harmanbeck: Slang for “constable”—word taken from the English Rogue.

—Knapp

↩

MS., “John Thurtell.”

—Knapp

↩

Batuschca (read “Bátyooshca”)

—Knapp

↩

Priberjensky, read “Préobrazhenski:” Crack regiment of the Russian Imperial Guard, so called from the barracks situated near the Church of the Transfiguration (Préobrazhenïe).

—Knapp

↩

The Fight of 1820, chapter XXVI. We will here give a condensed portion of a chapter which we suppressed from the Life.

On the 20th of May, 1820, an eager crowd might have been seen pressing up to a card displayed in the Castle Tavern, Norwich. The card was signed “T. C.” and “T. Belcher;” but every one knew that the initials stood for the Champion of England, Thomas Cribb. The purport of the notice was that Edward Painter of Norwich was to fight Thomas Oliver of London for a purse of 100 guineas, on Monday, the 17th of July, in a field within twenty miles of the city.

A few days after this announcement, George Borrow was charged by his principals to convey a sum of money to a country gentleman by the name of John Berney Petre, Esq., J.P., residing at Westwick House, some thirteen and a half miles distant on the North Walsham road. The gentleman was just settling the transfer of his inheritance, his father having died eight months before. Borrow walked the entire distance, and while he tarried with the magistrate, the interview took place between him and Thurtell who desired to secure a field for the fight. Mr. Petre could not accommodate them, and they drove on to North Walsham. There they found the “pightle” which suited them in the vicinity of that town, on the road leading to Happisburgh (Hazebro).

Norwich began to fill on Saturday, the 15th of July, as the stagecoaches rolled in by the London (now Ipswich) and Newmarket roads. The Inn attached to the Bowling Green on Chapel-Field, then kept by the famous one-legged ex-coachman Dan Gurney, was the favourite resort of the “great men” of the day. Belcher, not old Belcher of 1791, but the “Teucer” Belcher, and Cribb, the champion of England, slept at the Castle Tavern, which like Janus had two faces—backed on the Meadows and fronted on White-Lion. The Norfolk in St. Giles and the Angel on the “Walk,” housed other varieties of the sporting world.

At an early hour on Monday, the 17th, the roads were alive with pedestrians, equestrians, Jews, Gentiles and Gypsies, in coaches, barouches and vehicles of every sort. From Norwich they streamed down Tombland into Magdalen street and road, out on the Coltishall highway, and thence—sixteen and one half miles in all—to North Walsham and the field. One ancient MacGowan (the Scotch for Petulengro) stood on Coltishall bridge and counted 2,050 carriages as they swept past. More than 25,000 men and thieves gathered in concentric circles about the stand.

I do not propose to attempt the description of this celebrated pugna or “battle with the fists.” Those who crave such diversions will find this one portrayed fittingly in the newspapers of the time. The closing passage of one of them has always seemed to me to be a masterpiece of grim brutality: “Oliver’s nob was exchequered, and he fell by heavy right-handed blows on his ears and temple. When on his second’s knee, his head dangled about like a poppy after a shower.”

A second fight, this time between Sampson, called the “Birmingham boy,” and Martin the “baker,” lost much of its interest by reason of the storm described in Lavengro. “During the contest,” says the Norfolk Chronicle, “a most tremendous black cloud informed the spectators that a rare sousing was in preparation for them.” And the Mercury states that “the heavy rain drenched the field, and most betook themselves to a retreat, but the rats were all drinkled.” Thus the “cloud” was no fiction, by which the Gypsy foretold the dreadful fate awaiting John Thurtell before Hertford gaol, 9th January, 1824. Ned Painter never fought again. He was landlord of the White Hart Inn from 1823 to 1835. The present proprietor still shows his portrait there, with the above fact duly inscribed on the back of the frame.

—Knapp

↩

Public: The Castle Tavern, Holborn, kept by Tom Belcher—the “Daffy Club.”

—Knapp

↩

“Here’s a health to old honest John Bull:” The verses were taken from a rare old volume entitled: The Norwich Minstrel, p. 30:—

Honest John Bull

Here’s a health to ‘Old honest John Bull’;
When he’s gone we shan’t find such another;
With hearts and with glasses brim full,
We’ll drink to ‘Britannia, his mother’;
For she gave him a good education,
Bade him keep to his God and his King,
Be loyal and true to the nation,
And then to get merry and sing.

For John is a good-natured fellow,
Industrious, honest and brave;
Not afraid of his betters when mellow,
For betters he knows he must have.
There must be fine lords and fine ladies,
There must be some little, some great;
Their wealth the support of our trade is,
Our trade the support of the State.

Some were born for the court and the city,
And some for the village and cot;
For it would be a dolorous ditty,
If we were born ‘equal in lot.’
If our ships had no pilots to steer,
What would come of poor Jack on the shrouds?
Or our troops no commanders to fear,
They would soon be arm’d robbers in crowds.

The plough and the loom would stand still,
If we were made gentlefolks all;
If clodhoppers—who then would fill
The parliament, pulpit or hall?
‘Rights of Man’ makes a very fine sound,
‘Equal riches’ a plausible tale;
Whose labourers would then till the ground?
All would drink, but who’d brew the ale?

Half naked and starv’d, in the streets
We should wander about, sans culottes;
Would Liberty find us in meats,
Or Equality lengthen our coats?
That knaves are for levelling, don’t wonder,
We may easily guess at their views;
Pray, who’d gain the most by the plunder?
Why, they that have nothing to lose.

Then away with this nonsense and stuff,
Full of treason, confusion and blood;
Every Briton has freedom enough
To be happy as long as he’s good.
To be rul’d by a glorious king,
To be govern’d by jury and laws;
Then let us be happy and sing,
‘This, this, is true Liberty’s cause.’

—Knapp

↩

Haik, read “Haïk:” Armenian.

—Knapp

↩

Conqueror of Tippoo Sahib: General Harris (1791).

—Knapp

↩

March: The exact date was discovered by me in private letters in Norwich. See Life, I, p. 91. George left Norwich on the evening of 1st April, 1824, and consequently reached London early on the morning of 2nd April.

—Knapp

↩

Lodging: No. 16 Millman Street, Bedford Row.

—Knapp

↩

The publisher: Sir Richard Phillips.

—Knapp

↩

Mr. so-and-so: Taylor of Norwich.

—Knapp

↩

MS., “Bartlett.”

—Knapp

↩

The Magazine: The Monthly Magazine; or, British Register.

—Knapp

↩

MS., “Saviour.”

—Knapp

↩

MS., “High Tory principles.”

—Knapp

↩

The Oxford Review: The Universal Review; or, Chronicle of the Literature of All Nations. No. 1, March, 1824, to No. 6, January, 1825.

—Knapp

↩

Red Julius, called elsewhere by Borrow Iolo Goch: A Welsh bard of the fifteenth century.

—Knapp

↩

Caesar’s Castle: The Tower of London.

—Knapp

↩

Blessed Mary Flanders: Defoe’s “Moll Flanders:” The Fortunes and Misfortunes of the Famous Moll Flanders, etc., Who Was Born in Newgate, and during a Life of continu’d Variety for Threescore Years, besides her Childhood, Was Twelve Year a W⸺, five Times a Wife ⸻, Twelve Year a Thief, Eight Year a Transported Felon in Virginia, at Last Grew Rich, liv’d Honest, and Died a Penitent. Written from her Own Memorandums. London, 1721.

—Knapp

↩

Booksellers’ shop: The shop was a depository of the Religious Tract Society, the publishers of Legh Richmond’s Annals of the Poor, of which the first section was the Dairyman’s Daughter.

—Knapp

↩

MS., “Arden” throughout.

—Knapp

↩

Newly married: Richard, Jr., married Feb., 1823.

—Knapp

↩

“Newgate Lives:” The true title was: Celebrated Trials, and Remarkable Cases of Criminal Jurisprudence, from the Earliest Records to the Year 1825, London, 1825 (February).

—Knapp

↩

Translator of “Faustus:” Faust, a Drama by Goethe, and Schiller’s Song of the Bell; translated by Lord Francis Leveson Gower, London, J. Murray, 1823

—Knapp

↩

Translator of Quintilian: I doubt whether this was John Carey, LL.D. (1756–1826), who published an edition of Quintilian, 1822, but no translation. My information is positive that it was Wm. Gifford, translator of Juvenal, 1802, 3rd ed. 1817.

—Knapp

↩

The MS. develops this paragraph as follows:—

So Francis Ardry called upon me, and right glad I was that he did so; and after we had sat conversing for some time, he said, “Did you ever see Kean?”

“No,” said I, “but I have heard both of him and of Belcher. I should like to see either, especially the latter. Where are they to be found?”

“I know nothing of the latter,” said Frank, “but if you wish to see Kean, you had better come with me where he will appear tonight after a long absence. The public are anxiously waiting for him, intending to pelt him off the stage.”

“And what has he done,” said I, “to be pelted off the stage?”

“What is very naughty,” said Frank; “breaking one of the commandments.”

“And did he break the commandment on the stage?”

“No,” said Frank, “I never heard that he broke it on the stage, except in the way of his profession.”

“Then, what have the public to do with the matter?”

“They think they have,” said Frank.

And then we went out together to see Shakespeare’s Richard, or rather we went to see the man who was to personate Shakespeare’s Richard—and so did thousands; we did not see him, however. There was a great tumult, I remember, in the theatre. The man who was to perform the part of Richard, and who it was said was the best hand for interpreting the character that had ever appeared on the stage, had a short time before been involved in a disgraceful affair, and this was to be his first appearance on the stage since the discovery. The consequence was that crowds flocked to the theatre with the firm intention of expressing their indignation. “We will pelt his eyes out,” said a man who sat beside me in the pit—for we sat in the pit—and who bore the breach of all the commandments in his face. The actor in question, however, who perhaps heard the threats which were vented against him, very prudently kept out of the way, and the manager coming forward informed the public that another would perform the part—whereupon there was a great uproar. “We have been imposed upon,” said the individual who sat beside me. “I came here for nothing else than to pelt that scoundrel off the stage.” The uproar, however, at length subsided, and the piece commenced. In a little time there was loud applause. The actor who had appeared in place of the other was performing. “What do you clap for?” said I to the individual by my side, who was clapping most of all. “What do I clap for?” said the man. “Why, to encourage Macready, to be sure. Don’t you see how divinely he acts? why, he beats Kean hollow. Besides that, he’s a moral man, and I like morality.” “Do you mean to say,” said I, “that he was never immoral?” “I neither know nor care,” said the man; “all I know is that he has never been found out. It will never do to encourage a public man who has been found out. No, no! the morality of the stage must be seen after.”

—Knapp

↩

MS. “Charlie” and “Charlie’s” throughout.

—Knapp

↩

Oxford: This constant satirising of the great English university in connection with the publisher’s theory, doubtless grew out of a series of articles printed in the Magazine during the years ’23 and ’24, and which may be summarised by this notice in volume LVI, p. 349: “In a few days will appear a series of Dialogues between an Oxford Tutor and a Disciple of the new Commonsense Philosophy; in which the mechanical principles of matter and motion will be accurately contrasted with the theories of occult powers which are at present cherished by the Universities and Royal Associations throughout Europe.”

—Knapp

↩

Churchyard: St. Giles churchyard where Capt. Borrow was buried on the 4th of March previous.

—Knapp

↩

A New Mayor: Inexact. Robert Hawkes was mayor of Norwich in 1822. Therefore he was now ex-mayor.

—Knapp

↩

Man with a Hump: Thomas Osborn Springfield, was not a watchmaker so far as is known in Norwich, but “carried on the wholesale silk business, having almost a monopoly of the market” (Bayne’s Norwich, p. 588).

—Knapp

↩

Painter of the heroic: Benjamin Robert Haydon (1785–1846).

—Knapp

↩

The MS. adds: “ ‘It will, perhaps, be as well, first of all, to go to the exhibition of British art, which is at present open. I hear he has a picture there, which he has just finished. We will look at it, and from that you may form a tolerable estimate of his powers.’ Thereupon my brother led the way, and we presently found ourselves in the Gallery of British Art.”

—Knapp

↩

Norman Arch: The grand entrance and exit to the Norwich Cathedral, west side.

—Knapp

↩

Snap: The Snapdragon of Norwich is the Tarasque of the south of France, and the Tarasca of Corpus day in Spain. It represents a Dragon or monster with hideous jaws, supported by men concealed, all but their legs, within its capacious belly, and carried about in civic processions prior to the year 1835; even now it is seen on Guy Fawkes’ day, the 5th of November.

—Knapp

↩

Whiffler: An official character of the old Norwich Corporation, strangely uniformed and accoutred, who headed the annual procession on Guildhall day, flourishing a sword in a marvellous manner. All this was abolished on the passage of the Municipal Reform Act in 1835. As a consequence, says a contemporaneous writer, “the Aldermen left off wearing their scarlet gowns, Snap was laid up on a shelf in the ‘Sword Room’ in the Guildhall, and the Whifflers no longer danced at the head of the procession in their picturesque costume. It was a pretty sight, and their skill in flourishing their short swords was marvellous to behold.”

—Knapp

↩

Billy Blind and Owlenglass: Till Eulenspiegel: The German Rogue; or, the Life and Merry Adventures, Cheats, Stratagems, and Contrivances of Tiel Eulespiegle. Made English from the High-Dutch. London, 1720.

—Knapp

↩

Brandt and Struensee: For High-Treason in Denmark, 1772. See Celebrated Trials, IV, p. 465; and for Richard Patch (“yeoman Patch”), 1805, volume V, p. 584.

—Knapp

↩

Lord Byron: The remains of the poet lay in state from Friday 9th July, 1824, in Sir Edward Knatchbull’s house, Great George Street, to Monday the 12th when they were conveyed to Hucknall-Torkard in Nottinghamshire. On that day (12th July) Borrow witnessed the procession as described in the text.

—Knapp

↩

“Arden” throughout the MS.

—Knapp

↩

The text is: “Malheur, as the French say, that it is so choked.”

—Knapp

↩

Carolan’s Receipt: Torlough (i.e., Charles) O’Carolan, the celebrated Irish harper and bard, was born at Nobber, Co. Meath, in 1670, and died in 1738. See Alfred Webb’s Compendium of Irish Biography, Dublin, 1878, p. 372; J. C. Walker’s Irish Bards, 1786, App., pp. 86–87, and Dictionary of National Biography, XLI, p. 343. The “Receipt” in Irish is in Walker, and at the end of Vallancey’s Irish Grammar, second ed., Dublin, 1781.[411] Here is the translation given in Walker:—

“When by sickness or sorrow assail’d,
To the mansion of Stafford I hie’d
His advice or his cordial ne’er fail’d
To relieve me—nor e’er was denied.

“At midnight our glasses went round,
In the morning a cup he would send;
By the force of his wit he has found
That my life did on drinking depend.

“With the spirit of Whiskey inspir’d,
By my Harp e’en the pow’r is confess’d;
’Tis then that my genius is fir’d,
’Tis then I sing sweetest and best.

“Ye friends and ye neighbours draw near,
Attend to the close of my song;
Remember, if life you hold dear,
That drinking your life will prolong.”

Curiously enough among the subscribers to the Romantic Ballads, Norwich, 1826, we find these names: (p. 185) “F. Arden, Esq., London, five copies,” “T. G. O’Donnahoo, Esq., London, five copies;” (p. 187) “Mr. J. Turner, London.”

—Knapp

↩

“Bishop Sharpe,” a pugilist of that name and time.

—Knapp

↩

“Three are after my death.”

—Knapp

↩

The Review: The Review actually ceased January, 1825, with its sixth number.

—Knapp

↩

MS. (apparently) “L⸺,” but [later, T⸺].

—Knapp

↩

MS., “is quite as rational an amusement as politics.”

—Knapp

↩

“Le Noir” in MS. A, and in Romany Rye, appendix.

—Knapp

↩

MS., “L⸺,” or “T.”

—Knapp

↩

MS., “Canning.”

—Knapp

↩

MS., “L⸺,” or “T⸺.”

—Knapp

↩

Laham: In Hebrew bread is lèhem; but our author probably wrote it by sound. Z’hats is the accusative of hats, the Armenian for bread; for as Borrow’s source, old Villotte (1714), says: “Accusativus praefigit nominativo literam z.”

—Knapp

↩

Mesroub, read “Miesrob,” who, about 450 AD introduced the Armenian alphabet.

—Knapp

↩

Sea in Armenian is dzow.

—Knapp

↩

Adelánte (Spanish): Come in.

—Knapp

↩

Bueno (Spanish): Good. This sound of the word bueno, heard in 1825 from the Jew Manasseh, was brought to Borrow’s memory in 1836 when he met the Jew Abarbanel on the roads in Spain.

—Knapp

↩

Una vez, etc. (Spanish): On one occasion when he was intoxicated.

—Knapp

↩

Goyim (Hebrew): Nations, Gentiles.

—Knapp

↩

Lasan akhades, read “Lâshôn haqqôdesh:” Sacred language, i.e., Hebrew.

—Knapp

↩

Janin: Wine in Hebrew is “yâyim” (not “yânin”), but our author quoted correctly from the Dialoghi di Amore composti per Leone Medico, Vinegia, 1541, and the Spanish edition (which I use): Los Dialogos de Amor de mestre Leon Abarbanel medico y Filosofo excelente, Venetia, 1568. The passage is: “And he (Noah), after the flood, was called Janus on account of his invention of wine, for Janin in Hebrew signifies wine, and he is represented with two faces turned in opposite directions, because he saw before the flood and after it.”[412] George Borrow always writes Abarbenel for Abarbanel. His true name was Leo Abrabanel.

—Knapp

↩

Janinoso (Judaeo-Spanish) meaning vinosus, intoxicated.

—Knapp

↩

Epicouraiyim: Christians, as below, the “Epicureans,” for so the rabbis of the East call us in the West—properly, “unbelievers.” But Borrow’s form is not found in Buxtorf (1869)—read [unknown Hebrew text] Epikûrôsîn and (pop.) Epikûrîn.

—Knapp

↩

Sephardim: Spanish and Portuguese Jews, as the Ashkenazim are the German Jews.

—Knapp

↩

I am at ⸻: Greenwich, Blackheath and Shooter’s Hill.

—Knapp

↩

Colonel B. … : Colonel Blood. See Celebrated Trials, volume II, pp. 248–354: “Thomas Blood, generally called Colonel Blood, who stole the crown from the Tower of London, 1671.”

—Knapp

↩

Got fare to ⸻, read Amesbury, Wiltshire.

—Knapp

↩

City of the Spire: Salisbury.

—Knapp

↩

From ⸻, read Bristol.

—Knapp

↩

Stranger: Could not be William Beckford (1759–1844) of Fonthill Park, three miles from Hinton, a dozen or fifteen miles from Salisbury. Besides the place was sold in 1822 and George Mortimer occupied it in 1825. Borrow had been walking five days in a N.W. direction from Salisbury, and all his narrative harmonises with the places and dates that bring him to Horncastle in August, 1825.

—Knapp

↩

MS., “The Times.”

—Knapp

↩

Abedariums, read “abecedariums.”

—Knapp

↩

Flaming Tinman: He is also called by Borrow, Blazing Tinman, Flying Tinker, Blazing Bosville or Boswell, and finally Anselo Herne, his true clan-name.

—Knapp

↩

Ten years ago, i.e., thirteen, when he was at Tamworth in April or May, 1812.

—Knapp

↩

The Romany chi, etc. [the translation appears later in the book]:

The Rommany churl
And the Rommany girl,
Tomorrow shall hie
To poison the sty,
And bewitch on the mead
The farmer’s steed.

—Knapp

↩

Answer to the gillie: The Rommany churl and the Rommany girl love thieving and spaeing and lying and everything but honesty and truth.

—Knapp

↩

Peth yw, etc. (Welsh): What is that lying there on the ground? Yn wirionedd, in truth, surely.

—Knapp

↩

Gwenwyn: Poison! Poison! the lad has been poisoned!

—Knapp

↩

Hanged the mayor: The suppressed name of the Welshman and the whole account of the affair is given in Wild Wales, p. 7 (chapter III).

—Knapp

↩

Bardd Cwsg: The Sleeping Bard, by Ellis Wynn: The Sleeping Bard; or Visions of the World, Death, and Hell. By Elis Wyn. Translated from the Cambrian British by George Borrow. London, 1860.

—Knapp

↩

Merddin Wyllt (“Myrddin”): i.e., Wild Merlin, called the Wizard.

—Knapp

↩

Found written: See Moll Flanders by Defoe, p. 188, ed. 1722: “Oh! what a felicity is it to mankind,” said I, “that they cannot see into the hearts of one another!” I have carefully reread the whole volume of Moll Flanders, and find no such passages as those referred to here, save the one above. Hence, we may justly infer that Borrow quoted the spirit, rather than the words, of his author.

—Knapp

↩

Catraeth, read “Cattraeth.” The reference is to Aneurin’s book, the Y Gododin. A poem on the Battle of Cattraeth, by Aneurin, a Welsh Bard of the Sixth Century. With an English translation by J. Williams ab Ithel. Llandovery, 1852.

—Knapp

↩

Fish or flesh: See Borrow’s Targum, St. Petersburg, 1835, p. 76, under the “History of Taliesin,” ending:—

“I saw the end with horror
Of Sodom and Gomorrah!
And with this very eye
Have seen the [Trinity];
I till the judgment day
Upon the earth shall stray:
None knows for certainty
Whether fish or flesh I be.”

The original Welsh of the “Hanes Taliesin” is in the Gorchestion Beirdd Cymru, 1773.

—Knapp

↩

Take this: This Bible, with Peter Williams’ name in it, was sold in London in 1886 out of George Borrow’s collection.

—Knapp

↩

Mumpers’ Dingle: Near Willenhall, Staffordshire. The place is properly Momber or Monmer Lane, and is now occupied by the “Monmer Lane Ironworks,” hence totally obliterated.

—Knapp

↩

Volundr (Völundr): The Wayland Smith of Northern legends. Wayland Smith.—A Dissertation on a Tradition of the Middle Ages. From the French of G. B. Depping and Francisque Michel. London, 1847.

—Knapp

↩

Ingeborg: The lines are from the Romantic Ballads of 1826, p. 58, entitled the “Heroes of Dovrefeld. From the old Danish.”

—Knapp

↩

“As I was jawing:” Text and translation of the whole eight lines are found on pp. 182–83 of the Lavo-Lil, 1874:—

As I to the town was going one day
My Roman lass I met by the way.

The MS. is somewhat different—“Rommany” instead of “Roman,” and the last line, “If you will share my lot with me.”

—Knapp

↩

The man in black: This priest seems to have been a Fraser of Lovat. See The Life, Adventures, and many and great Vicissitudes of Fortune of Simon, Lord Lovat, the Head of the Family of Frasers. From his birth at Beaufort, near Inverness, in the Highlands of Scotland, in 1668, to the time of his being taken by Capt. Millar, after three days search, in a hollow tree, on the coasts of Knoidart and Arisaig. By the Rev. Archibald Arbuthnot, London, 1746.

—Knapp

↩

Armenian: It must be remembered that Borrow’s Armenian was limited to the Introduction, Grammar and Latin-Armenian Dictionary of the Jesuit Joseph Villotte, 1714, which he picked up at Norwich in 1822–23. Hence all his examples are taken from that book—mi, one; yergou, two; yerek, three, and those in Romany Rye.

—Knapp

↩

Buona sera (Italian): Good evening.

—Knapp

↩

Per far visita, etc.: To pay your lordship a call, that is my motive.

—Knapp

↩

MS. “Lord A[berdeen].”

—Knapp

↩

Che io non, etc., read ch’ in, etc.: That I do not believe at all.

—Knapp

↩

Addio: Farewell.

—Knapp

↩

Pulci: See Morgante Maggiore di Luigi Pulci Firentino, etc. Venetia, 1546. This version is rather free and local. Here is the original (canto XVIII, f. 97, ed. 1546):—

Rispose allhor Margutte: “A dirtel tosto,
Io non credo piu al nero ch’ a l’azzurro,
Ma nel cappone, o lesso, o, vuogli, arrosto,
E credo alcuna volta anco nel burro,
Nella cervogia, e, quando io n’ho, nel mosto,
E molto pui nell’ aspro che il mangurro,
Ma sopra tutto nel buon vino ho fede,
E credo che sia salvo chi gli crede.”

—Knapp

↩

O Cavaliere, etc.: Oh, Sir Walter, ye have wrought much in behalf of the Holy See!

—Knapp

↩

Poveri frati: Poor friars!

—Knapp

↩

One fellow I met: See the postillion’s story [later].

—Knapp

↩

Master in Armenian is d’yèr; of a master, d’yearn; plural, d’yeark.

—Knapp

↩

Koul Adonai, read “Kôl Adonai.” The next quotation is from part of verse 4 of the XXIX Psalm, which he gives according to the prayerbook version.

—Knapp

↩

The one sole emendation consists in substituting the masculine cheval for the feminine jument, [in chapter XVIII]. Le jument est beau was a solecism that could not longer be tolerated.

—Knapp

↩

MS., “ ’49.”

—Knapp

↩

MS., “execrated by every unmanly scoundrel, every sycophantic lackey, and every political and religious renegade in Britain.”

—Knapp

↩

The man in black: This priest seems to have been a Fraser of Lovat. See The Life, Adventures, and many and great Vicissitudes of Fortune of Simon, Lord Lovat, the Head of the Family of Frasers. From his birth at Beaufort, near Inverness, in the Highlands of Scotland, in 1668, to the time of his being taken by Capt. Millar, after three days search, in a hollow tree, on the coasts of Knoidart and Arisaig. By the Rev. Archibald Arbuthnot, London, 1746.

—Knapp

↩

Barbarini, read “Barberini:” Urban VIII, Pope 1623–44.

—Knapp

↩

Nipotismo di Roma: Il Nipotismo di Roma: or, the History of the Popes Nephews. From the time of Sixtus IV anno 1471, to the death of the late Pope, Alexander VII anno 1667. In Two Parts. By Gregorio Leti. Written originally in Italian, and Englished by W. A., Fellow of the Royal Society. London, 1673.

This was the edition used by Mr. Borrow, and purchased by me.

—Knapp

↩

Ganganelli: Clement XIV, Pope, 1769–74.

—Knapp

↩

Mezzofanti: So here and elsewhere in Romany Rye; Mezzofante in Lavengro—Cardinal Giuseppe, 1774–1849, the celebrated linguist.

—Knapp

↩

Leon the Isaurian: Reigned at Constantinople from 717–741.

—Knapp

↩

Ignacio: Spanish form of Ignatius.

—Knapp

↩

Omani batsikhom: Manchu Tartar form of prayer given elsewhere by Borrow as Oum-ma-ni-bat-mi-houm. See Life, I, p. 176.

—Knapp

↩

Bellissima Biondina (Italian): Fairest of blondes.

—Knapp

↩

Sono un Prete, etc. (Italian): I am a Roman Catholic Priest.

—Knapp

↩

Zamarra (Spanish): A sheepskin jacket with the wool outside.

—Knapp

↩

Scotch blood: He was, then, a Fraser of Lovat, of whom Simon Lord F. was a supporter of the last Pretender, Charles Edward Stuart, 1746.

—Knapp

↩

Puta (Spanish): The most offensive word for harlot.

—Knapp

↩

Alcoran des Cordeliers, i.e., “the Franciscans’ Coran:” A blasphemous work written in 1399 in Latin by Bartolommeo Albizzi (Albitius); first published in printed form at Milan in 1510, then by Luther in 1542 with his peculiar comments, and finally in French at Geneva, 1556.

—Knapp

↩

Bible: The price of the old apple-woman’s Bible was, it will be remembered, one half-crown (Lavengro).

—Knapp

↩

Alexander VI.: Pope 1492–1503. He was a Spaniard of Valencia, and his family name was Rodrigo Borja, in Italian, Borgia.

—Knapp

↩

L’opere sue, etc.: His deeds were not those of lions, but of foxes—a slight alteration of Dante’s “L’opere mie,” etc. See L’inferno, XXVII, stanza 25.

—Knapp

↩

Oimè (Italian): Alas!

—Knapp

↩

To ⸻, read “Rome.”

—Knapp

↩

There is at ⸻, read “Rome.”

—Knapp

↩

Yes, per Dio (Italian): By Heaven!

—Knapp

↩

Parsons and Garnet: Two English Jesuits—Robert Parsons (1547–1610), superior to the Catholic Missions in England, and Henry Garnet (1555–1606), hanged because he refused to reveal the secrets of the confessional in connection with the Gunpowder Plot.

—Knapp

↩

No hay remedio (Spanish): There is no help for it.

—Knapp

↩

Inserted it: In volume IV, p. 330.

—Knapp

↩

Calañés: A Spanish hat worn by the lower classes, having the rim turned up against the crown.

—Knapp

↩

There’s a chovahanee, etc.: The full ditty runs thus in one of Borrow’s MSS.:—

The Petulengres

“There’s a chovahanee and a chovahanó,
The nav se lendè Petulengro;
Sore the chavès ’dré their ten
Are chories and labbenies—tatchipen,”

which reading corrects that of the text.

—Knapp

↩

Flaming Bosville: Anselo Herne. He is also called by Borrow, Flaming Tinman, Blazing Tinman, Flying Tinker, Blazing Bosville or Boswell.

—Knapp

↩

Gentleman Cooper and White-headed Bob: i.e., George Cooper and Ned Baldwin, who fought on the 5th of July, 1825, according to Pearce Egan’s Boxiana, V, pp. 61 and 80. Observe that the date harmonises perfectly with the chronology of the expedition.

—Knapp

↩

Brynhilda the Valkyrie, or Amazon, was the wife of Gunnar and friend of Sigurd. Sigurd, called Fafnisbane or the Slayer of Fafnir, was a heroic character frequently mentioned in the Edda, the Wilkina Saga, Snorro’s Heimskringla, and Saxo-Grammaticus. In the Wilkina he is Sigurdr Sveinn, in the old Danish Heroic Ballads (Kiaempeviser) he is Sigurd Snaresvend (Borrow’s “Snareswayne”), and Siegfrid in the Lay of the Nibelungs. Sivard or Sivord is a German variety of the same name.

—Knapp

↩

Feasting: This rustic banquet was offered to Sylvester and Ursula who were married that day, although our “rye” was not aware of the fact till later.

—Knapp

↩

Piramus: In MS. also “Priamus.”

—Knapp

↩

Gipsy song: The song was built up by our author from a very slender prose draft, which I find in its earliest form given thus:—

“1. Drabbing the Baulo

“We jaws to the drab-engro and lels dui or trin hors-worth of drab, and when we wels to the sweti we pens we can have a drab at a baulo. Then we kairs it opré, and jaws to a farm-ker to mang a bit of habben, and then we pens: ‘Chuva lis acai and dov-odoy baulo will lel it, and tomorrow sorlu we’ll wel apopli and mang it.’ And so we kairs, and on the sorlu when we’ve got it, we toves it well; we kins levinor at the kitchema, and have a kosko habben. The boshom-engro plays (kils), and the tawni juva gils, a kosko puro Rommany guillie.”

Then follows the gillie nearly as in the text.

“2. Drabbing the Baulo

“To mande shoon ye Rommany Chals
Who besh in the pus about the yag
I’ll pen how we drab the baulo.

“We jaws to the drab-engro ker
Trin hors-worth there of drab we lels
And when to the swety back we wels
We pens we’ll drab the baulo.

“And then we kairs the drab opré,
And then we jaws to the farming ker
To mang a beti habben,
A beti poggado habben.

“A rinkeno baulo there we dick,
And then we pens in Rommany jib:
‘Chiv lis odoy oprey the chick,
The baulo he will lel lis,
The baulo he will lel lis.

“ ‘Apopli on the sorlo we
Will wel and mang him mullo,
Will wel and mang his truppo.’

“And so we kairs, and so we kairs,
We mang him on the sorlo,
And rig to the tan the baulo.

“And then we toves his wendror well
Till sore the wendror iuziou sie,
Till kekkeno drab’s adrey lis,
Till drab there’s kek adrey lis.

“And then his truppo well we hatch,
Kin levinor at the kitchema,
And have a kosko habben,
A kosko Rommano habben.

“The boshom-engro kils, he kils,
The tawni juva gils, she gils,
A puro Rommany gillie,
Now shoon the Rommany gillie.”

3. The third and last MS. is complete, but varies considerably from the printed text. “Romany” is written with two m’s, as in Lavengro throughout; in the fourth verse it reads: “In Rommany chib: chiv lis odoy opré the chik;” fourth line omits “and;” in the fifth and sixth verses it gives “sorlo” properly, instead of “saulo;” in seventh verse it reads “his wendror,” and in the last, “boshom-engro” and “tawni.”

From all these variants it results that MS. No. 3 furnishes a better reading than the printed text.

—Knapp

↩

The apothecary. ↩

Ursula’s Song: By the aid of the Gypsy list [the Glossary] at the end of this volume, the translation can be easily made out by the curious reader.

—Knapp

↩

MS., see Life, I, 34, n.

—Knapp

↩

Sanpriel: Corrupt form of “Sanspareil,” unrivalled.

—Knapp

↩

Synfye: Slavonic form of “Cynthia”—th in Russian is pronounced ph or f; Thomas, Fómas.

—Knapp

↩

Life, I, 34, n.

—Knapp

↩

Life of Charles: Add “XII”

—Knapp

↩

The church: Mentioned as three miles from the dingle, has not yet been discovered.

—Knapp

↩

The Edda: Early Icelandic literary monuments, consisting of the Elder or Poetic Edda collected by Saemund, and the later or Prose Edda collected by Snorro Sturleson. See Mallet’s Northern Antiquities, Bohn’s Edition.

—Knapp

↩

Sagas: Early historical tales handed down by oral tradition.

—Knapp

↩

Anselo Herne: His clan-name.

—Knapp

↩

Pulci: Luigi Pulci (1432–87). See Morgante Maggiore di Luigi Pulci Firentino, etc. Venetia, 1546.

—Knapp

↩

Ingravidata (Italian): With child.

—Knapp

↩

E nacquene, etc.: “And of her a son was born, says story, who subsequently gave great victory to Charlemagne.”

—Knapp

↩

Fortiguerra: Niccolò Fortiguerra (1674–1735). He did not live to print his voluminous poem entitled Ricciardetto, having died in 1735, just “ninety years” from the date 1825, as our text declares.

—Knapp

↩

Slammocks, etc.: Norwich worthies, I suppose; at least I do not find them in the Boxiana at my command.

—Knapp

↩

The Armenian in this chapter I find correct. “Hramahyel” should have been given hramaïyel, “hntal,” etc., khntal (χντάλ), and “madagh,” madag.

See The Latin-Armenian Dictionary, with a Grammar Prefixed. By Jacobus Villotte, from which Borrow drew the Haïkian words and forms displayed in Lavengro and Romany Rye.

—Knapp

↩

Hard-mouthed jade: This favourite expression of Mr. Borrow’s proceeds, I opine, from his readings in the quaint eighteenth century literature with which his library abounded. In Defoe’s Moll Flanders, p. 301, edition of 1722, we read: “The witnesses were the two wenches, a couple of hard mouth’d jades indeed.” And on p. 323: “A hard mouth’d man.”

—Knapp

↩

The “daffodil” poet: William Wordsworth (1770–1850).

—Knapp

↩

Carlo Borromeo: The Cardinal saint, born 1538, died 1584.

—Knapp

↩

Bricconi abbasso (It.): “Down with the rogues!”

—Knapp

↩

Friar Bacon: The celebrated scientist Roger Bacon (1214–94) was fated, like Virgil, to be popularly metamorphosed into a magician and conjuror. Hence the “Friar Bacon” series of chap-books, extending (so far as we know them) from the sixteenth century to the present. I will give the passage referred to by Mr. Borrow, so that it may be seen that the myth had no reference to the railway. No. 3 in The History of Frier Bacon. London, 1683, leaf 8:—

“Chapter V: How Miles watched the Brazen-head, and in the end went away from his master.

“Fryer Bacon, having performed many wonderful things by his curious Art, was now sifting out how he might wall England with brass; wherefore he and Fryer Bungy, when they had raised the devil, bound him to a tree, for to make him tell them how it might be performed. He told them that they should make a Brazen-head, which (if they could watch it till it spoke) would tell them how it might be done. The head was made, and they watched till they could watch no longer. At last Fryer Bungey persuaded Fryer Bacon to let his man Miles watch while they slept; to which the Fryer agreed. Then Miles was called, who undertook to awake them when the Head would speak. So to sleep they went, and Miles expected some great speech to come from the Head. At last the Head cryed, ‘Time Is’; at which Miles fell into a great laughter, and made his scoffs and jears thereat. Then it said, ‘Time Was’; but yet he would not awake his master, counting them but silly and frivolous words. Lastly, the Head said, ‘Time Is Past’; at which words down it fell, and in falling made such a noise that it awakened the two Fryers, and had almost affrighted poor Miles out of his senses,” etc.

—Knapp

↩

L⸺, read Liverpool.

—Knapp

↩

C⸺, read Chester.

—Knapp

↩

Brooke of Borneo: Sir James Brooke, Rajah of Sarawak (1803–68), George Borrow’s schoolmate at Norwich in 1816–18.

—Knapp

↩

“Vails:” He means, of course, “vale.”

—Knapp

↩

Romanvile: London. See The English Rogue, the Life of Meriton Latroon, a Witty Extravagant. Being a Compleat History of the Most Eminent Cheats of Both Sexes. London, 1665–80.

—Knapp

↩

The chi she is kaulo (read “kauley”), etc.: “The lass she is black, she sleeps upon her back.”

—Knapp

↩

Sivord: Or Sivard, the same as Sigurd, called the Snaresvend (“Snareswayne” on the next page). See Romantic Ballads, 1826, pp. 83 and 90. For the reason of Borrow’s changing the Danish svend into “swayne,” see Life, II, p. 269.

—Knapp

↩

The horse Grayman: i.e., the “Skimming gray” of p. 96, Romantic Ballads

—Knapp

↩

The Maugrabin sorcerer: The “African Magician” in Lane’s translation. There is in this passage of The Romany Rye evidently a confusion of two of the tales in the Arabian Nights—those of Aladdin and Sindbad, fifth voyage.

—Knapp

↩

Isten (pronounced “ishten”): Hungarian for God.

—Knapp

↩

Magyar (pronounced “mädjr”): A Hungarian.

—Knapp

↩

L’Eau de la Reine d’Hongrie, read “de Hongrie,” h being aspirate in this word.

—Knapp

↩

Tékéli (1658–1705).

—Knapp

↩

Pigault Lebrun (Charles), 1753–1835; Les Barons de Felsheim, Paris, 1822.

—Knapp

↩

Ersebet, read “Erszebet,” Elisabeth.

—Knapp

↩

Florentius of Buda: Flourished 1790–1805. See Magyar Ország Poigári Históriá-járá való Lexicon. Nagy-Varad (Gross-Wardein), by Budai Ferencz, 1804–5.

—Knapp

↩

Álmus, or Álmos (“älmosh”), died 889. The Hungarian scholar Vámbéri, has exploded the “dream” (or rather “sleep”) theory heretofore entertained with regard to the origin of the name Almos; he says it is an epithet, meaning the Great, the Sublime, the Noble, the Glorious (Ursprung, pp. 62, 156).

—Knapp

↩

Dunau, read “Donau,” German for Danube.

—Knapp

↩

Király and Ház: The former comes from the Serbian Králj (lj like Spanish ll or Portugese lh), which the Hungarian lengthened into kir-ály, not finding it convenient to pronounce kr.[413] As for haz, from haus (Austrian popular pronunciation hôs), we are told by Vámbéri that the ancient form was not ház, but hos (Ursprung, p. 556).

—Knapp

↩

Janos (pronounced “Yánosh”): John.

—Knapp

↩

Szava (Hungarian): The Save.

—Knapp

↩

Laszlo: Ladislaus.

—Knapp

↩

Cilejia: The Roman Claudia Celleia, now Cilly, in Carinthia.

—Knapp

↩

Matyas: In English “Matthias.”

—Knapp

↩

Huz, read “husz” (Hungarian): Twenty. Vámbéri questions this etymology of “hussar” (p. 283), but unsatisfactorily, we think.

—Knapp

↩

Ulazslo: Wladislaus.

—Knapp

↩

Tché Drak: The Romanian cé dracŭ, but pronounced as in the text, and equivalent to the exclamation que diable!

—Knapp

↩

Mohacs Veszedelem, read “Mohacsi Veszedelem:” The Disaster of Mohács, the title of a poem by Baron Liszti.

—Knapp

↩

Lajos (“laï-osh”), Louis or Lewis.

—Knapp

↩

Bátory: A mere epithet, the “valiant.”

—Knapp

↩

Mufti: The ulémas or Doctors of the (Mahomedan) law.

—Knapp

↩

Coloscvar, read “Koloszvár,” in German, “Klausenburg.”

—Knapp

↩

Budáï Ferencz: Flourished 1790–1805. See Magyar Ország Poigári Históriá-járá való Lexicon. Nagy-Varad (Gross-Wardein), by Budai Ferencz, 1804–5.

—Knapp

↩

Rysckie Tsar, read “Russki Tsar:” The Russian Emperor.

—Knapp

↩

Plescova, now Pskov.

—Knapp

↩

Iván Basilowitz, read “Vasiliévitch,” known as Iván the Terrible.

—Knapp

↩

Izbushka (Russian): Hut.

—Knapp

↩

Tyzza, read “Tisza:” The river Theiss.

—Knapp

↩

Kopacs Teto, read “Kopász Tetö.”

—Knapp

↩

Kassau, read “Kaschau.”

—Knapp

↩

Eljen edes, etc. (pronounced “elyen edesh tsigáñ oor, elyen gool eraï”): “Long live the sweet Gypsy gentleman, long live the gudlo Rye.”

—Knapp

↩

Roth-Welsch: The German for Thieves’ Slang.

—Knapp

↩

Tzernebock, read “Tchernobog” (g like German ch): Black god, evil principle.

—Knapp

↩

Bielebock, read “Bielbog:” White god, the good principle.

—Knapp

↩

Saxo-Gramaticus, read “Grammaticus.”

—Knapp

↩

Fekete (Hungarian): Black.

—Knapp

↩

Erik Bloodaxe (Danish Blodöxe): King of Norway [c. 947–948].

—Knapp

↩

Regner Lodbrok: “Regnar” in Icelandic; Borrow gives the Danish term of this king’s name. See his famous “Death Song” in Mallet, Northern Antiquities; or, an Historical Account of the Manners, Customs, Religion and Laws, Language and Literature of the Ancient Scandinavians. London: Bonn, 1859, pp. 383–85.

—Knapp

↩

Halgerdr, read “Halgerda,” Mallet, Northern Antiquities; or, an Historical Account of the Manners, Customs, Religion and Laws, Language and Literature of the Ancient Scandinavians. London: Bonn, 1859, pp. 340–41.

—Knapp

↩

Biorn, read “Björn” and Ivarr, “Ivar.”

—Knapp

↩

Verdammt (German): Confounded.

—Knapp

↩

“Wife selling:” A very common practice among a certain class, it seems, in England; and, as this will hardly be credited in America, I will append some extracts from the newspapers. The Norfolk Chronicle of 5th May, 1894, says:

“The belief formerly prevailed, especially among the rural population, that a man had a perfectly legal right to sell his wife to another, provided he observed two indispensable formalities. One was that he placed a halter about her neck, and the other that he led her into the market and publicly transferred her to the purchaser. Numerous instances of these strange transactions have been recorded. Our columns, on the 9th of February, 1805, contained an account of the sale of a wife at Norwich. A Kentish tailor, the affections and person of whose amiable spouse had been jockeyed away by a neighbouring horsedealer, caparisoned her neck with a halter and surrendered all right and title to his virtuous rib, in consideration of the sum of £5. On the 2nd of May, 1823, a similar sale was effected in this city. A man named Stebbings disposed of his wile to a person named Turner for the sum of £6 10s. The latter paid £4 on account, took the woman home, and brutally turned his lawful wife out of doors.”

The London Daily Mail of 1st March, 1899, prints the following:—

“Very few people are aware that wives are literally sold today in England. A very common error of the vulgar is that a man by selling his wife releases himself from the marriage contract as surely as if he were legally divorced. In March, 1796, The Times announced the sale of a wife at Sheffield for sixpence. A short time afterwards the same journal calmly stated that the price of wives has risen in Smithfield Market from half a guinea to three guineas and a half! In 1803 a man led his wife, by a halter round her neck, into the cattle market at Sheffield, and sold her for a guinea, the purchaser leading away the woman to his home. In 1820 a man named Brouchet hired a cattle-pen in the Canterbury market, placed his wife in it, and ultimately sold her for 5s. Then wives began to increase in value, for soon afterwards one was sold for £15. This was followed by a ‘slump.’ In 1855 a man led his wife with a halter round her waist into Derby marketplace and offered her for sale, but all be could get for her was eighteen pence and a quart of ale. In 1873 a husband left his home and creditors in Belper for the liberty of America. The week after his flight all his goods were put up for auction to satisfy his debts. His wife claimed part of the money, and this being refused she insisted on being offered for sale as part of her husband’s assets. There was no sale, however, for ‘Lot 29.’ In even more recent days wife sales were common, and are even being effected in this present year of grace. In 1882 John Wilson, a collier of Alfreton, Derbyshire, sold his wife in a public-house for fourpence. Sheffield knife-grinders have long been noted for their transactions in the wife trade. Within quite recent times many a Sheffield wife has been sold by her husband for a gallon of beer, which has been drunk on the spot. Sometimes these sales assume a more formal aspect. In 1887, in the Sheffield County Court, a man admitted that he had bought another man’s wife for 5s. Most of these discreditable ‘deals’ escape notice, but a case has come to light where a man agreed to sell his wife to a collier, and the trio, with the woman’s father and mother and two family friends, assembled to arrange terms. Thirty shillings was the price finally agreed on. Four years ago, at Leeds, a man charged with bigamy pleaded that, as he had sold his wife for 3s. 6d. to another man, he could marry again legally! Eighteen months’ imprisonment was what he got, and more than deserved. A police court case in 1896 at Doncaster revealed the fact that John Tart sold his wife to Enoch Childs, on the understanding that the latter reared the vendor’s four children. In a Durham court in 1894 it transpired that a man named Shaw sold his daughter, a girl of sixteen, to a collier called Cudman, for 1s. Many a wife is at present sold in the East End of London, as well as in Yorkshire, for a quart of beer or an ounce of thick twist. It is the poor man’s method of divorce, and such is popular ignorance that there are scores of people who imagine that selling a wife is as legal a separation as a decree nisi pronounced by a bewigged and berobed judge.”

—Knapp

↩

Herodotus: The story is found in Thalia III, 84–88 (pp. 208–9 of Cary’s English translation). The groom’s name was “Oebares.”

—Knapp

↩

Deaghblasda, read “deaghbhlasda” (Irish): Sweet-tasted, dainty. This is the soothing word hinted at, but not given, in Lavengro [end of Chapter XIII].

—Knapp

↩

At H⸺, read “Hertford,” where John Thurtell was hanged, 9th January, 1824.

—Knapp

↩

Ned Flatnose: Edward Painter of Norwich.

—Knapp

↩

Spring: His true name was Thomas Winter. He died 20th August, 1851.

—Knapp

↩

⸻ Fair, read “Greenwich Fair,” on Easter Monday. See Dickens’ Sketches.

—Knapp

↩

Oilien (and later, “Oilein”) nan Naomha, read “Oilean na Naomhtha” (Irish): Island of the Saints (Patrick and Columba).

—Knapp

↩

Finn-ma-Coul: The tale of Finn was first learned by Borrow in January, 1854, from his Irish guide Cronan, while travelling in Cornwall (Life, II, p. 86, and note). This fact shows that Murtagh and his tale are introduced here to exhibit the author’s discovery of the identity between the Finn of Ireland and the Eddaic tradition of Sigurd Fafnisbane (p. 281). For Sigurd in the Wilkina Saga is suckled by a hind (p. 120) and fostered by Mymmer Smed or Mimer the Smith (p. 121) whom he eventually slays (p. 124). In the Eddaic Lay of the serpent-killer we read: “Sigurd took the heart of Fafnir and broiled it on a spit. And when he judged that it was done, he touched it with his finger to ascertain if that were really the case. Having burned his finger in the act, he put it to his mouth, and no sooner had the heart’s blood of Fafnir come in contact with Sigurd’s tongue than he understood the speech of birds,” etc. Here we have the two sides verified, the Irish by Cronan, and the Scandian by the Edda. But Brooke’s Reliques, a favourite work of Borrow’s in his Norwich days, and which he cites in 1832 (Life, I, p. 146), give us certain other fragments of these Finnic fables, whereby we can trace the sources of the text before us. For example, after Jack Dale had stripped Murtagh of all his money he is observed to be sitting “in deep despondency, holding his thumb to his mouth” (p. 278). And a little farther on (p. 282) a verse is cited from “Conan the Bald.” Now all this is found in Miss Brooke, that is, the names and the ideas—Conan the Bald (p. 106), Lochlin (p. 46), and Darmod Odeen (minus Taffy) and the verse with this note (p. 109):—“This strange passage is explained by some lines in the Poem of Dubmac-Dighruibh, where Finn is reproached with deriving all his courage from chewing his thumb for prophetic information.”

—Knapp

↩

Dungarvon times of old: See Life, I, p. 46, and II, pp. 16–17. Cradock’s letter was dated, 18th August, 1849, and Mr. B.’s answer (I, p. 146) a little after.

—Knapp

↩

Siol Loughlin, read “Lochlin” (Irish): Literally “the seed of Norway,” i.e., the Danish or Norwegian race. Miss Brooke very properly says (p. 46): “Lochlin is the Gaelic (and Irish) name for Scandinavia in general;” but Borrow limits it to Denmark—the Danish race. And a little below, “the Loughlin songs” are his Danish Ballads which he published the following year.

—Knapp

↩

Religious house: The story of Murtagh at the Irish College in Rome, and his subsequent wanderings in the South of France and in Spain, mask, as we have said elsewhere, the peregrinations of George Borrow in 1826–27.

—Knapp

↩

Tipperary. ↩

M’anam on Dioul: [God preserve] my soul from the devil!

—Knapp

↩

Raparees: Irish marauders, [in the time of] James II. See Life, I, p. 146, and Brooke’s Reliques, p. 205. The latter says that the word is from the Irish Réubóir Ri, plunderer, robber, freebooter of the king, from reubaim, I tear.

—Knapp

↩

Chiviter Vik: Cività Vecchia, the modern seaport of Rome, fifty miles distant.

—Knapp

↩

Army of the Faith: Spanish frontier corps of observation under Gen. Don Vicente Quesada, 1823–24.

—Knapp

↩

Prince Hilt: The Duke d’Angoulême, nephew of Louis XVIII, and son of the Count d’Artois (afterwards Charles X). D’Angoulême invaded Spain in 1823 with 100,000 Frenchmen, to restore Ferdinand VII to his absolute throne, against the Liberals of 1820–23.

—Knapp

↩

To ⸻, read Rome.

—Knapp

↩

Educated at ⸻, read Rome

—Knapp

↩

Direction of the east, read “south.” He could only have gone south from Horncastle to reach Boston (the “large town on the arm of the sea”) that day. The next he came to Spalding, some fifteen miles farther, where he met the recruiting serjeant, thence on to Norwich by Lynn Regis.

We must not forget that before Lavengro was begun, and fifteen years prior to the publication of The Romany Rye, that is, 26th December, 1842, Mr. Petulengro remarked to George Borrow at Oulton: “I suppose you have not forgot how, fifteen [seventeen] years ago, when you made horseshoes in the dingle by the side of the great north road, I lent you fifty guineas to purchase the wonderful trotting cob of the innkeeper with the green Newmarket coat, which three days after you sold for two hundred.”[414] Now, this is a very remarkable statement, and, taken in connection with the fact that so little is said about Horncastle in the book, it seems to me we are justified in proclaiming that Borrow was never in Horncastle at all. The interview with the Magyar and the syllabus of Hungarian history are clearly drawn from his experiences in Hungary and Transylvania in the year 1844, and hence are an anachronism here. It is a pity that the author did not adhere to the chronological facts of his life so strictly in The Romany Rye as he did in Lavengro. Truth and literature would have gained by it. And then that valedictory pledge,[415] confirmed in the appendix, drawing a veil over the period of his travails, if not his travels, was an error of judgment which, in an autobiography will, we fear, not easily be condoned.

—Knapp

↩

Age of nineteen, read “twenty;” he was twenty-one less four months at his father’s death.

—Knapp

↩

Children of Roma: Borrovian for Gypsies.

—Knapp

↩

Balm in Mary Flanders: Defoe’s Moll Flanders.

—Knapp

↩

MS., “Canning” (1827).[416]

—Knapp

↩

Viscount Goderich.

—Knapp

↩

MS., “Canning” (1827).

—Knapp

↩

MS., “Canning” (1827).

—Knapp

↩

MS., “who eventually presented him with a bishopric, had espoused,”

—Knapp

etc. ↩

MS., “He is a small landed proprietor who eats,” etc.

—Knapp

↩

Vaya! qué demonio es este! (Spanish): Bless me! what demon have we here!

—Knapp

↩

MS., “the Despatch, of course.”

—Knapp

↩

The Spanish Revolution of ’54–’56, made by O’Donnell. ↩

MS. (corrected):—

Un Erajái
Sinába chibando an sermón;
Y lle falta un balichó
Al chindomá de aquel gáo;
Y chanéla que los calés
Lo habían nicobáo;
Y penelá ’l erajái:
“Chaboró!
Guíllate á tu quer,
Y nicobéla la pirí
Que teréla ’l balichó,
Y chibéla andró
Una lima de tun chaborí,
Chaborí,
Una lima de tun chaborí.”

See also Lavo-Lil, p. 200.

—Knapp

↩

Sessions of Hariri: Arabic tales in prose interlarded with verse.

—Knapp

↩

The two languages: Chinese and Manchu.

—Knapp

↩

Canto I, stanza 53.[417]

—Knapp

↩

Stanza 57.[418]

—Knapp

↩

An obscene oath.[419] ↩

Oberon: A poem by Wieland (1733–1813).

—Knapp

↩

The father of Anglo-Germanism: Taylor of Norwich.

—Knapp

↩

Andrew Borde: The Fyrst Boke of the Introduction of Knowledge. “The which doth teache a man to speake parte of all maner of Languages, and to knowe the vsage and fashion of al maner of coũtreys. And for to knowe the most parte of all maner of Coynes of money, ye which is curraunt in euery region. Made by Andrew Borde, of Phisicke Doctor. Dedicated to the right Honorable and gracios lady Mary doughter of our souerayne lord Kyng Henry the eyght.”

The text of the Bodleian copy (1547?) runs as follows—(A 3 verso):—

“I am an Englysh man, and naked I stand here,
Musyng in my mynd what rayment I shall were;
For now I wyll were thys, and now I wyl were that,
Now I wvl were I cannot tel what.
All new fashyons be plesaunt to me,
I wyll haue them, whether I thryue or thee;
Now I am a frysker, all men doth on me looke,
What should I do but set cocke on the hoope;
What do I care yf all the worlde me fayle,
I wyl get a garment shal reche to my tayle;
Than I am a minion, for I were the new gyse;
The yere after this I trust to be wyse,
Not only in wering my gorgious aray,
For I wyl go to learnyng a hoole somers day;
I wyll learne Latyne, Hebrew, Grecke and Frenche,
And I wyl learne Douche sittyng on my benche;
I do feare no man, all men fearyth me,
I ouercome my aduersaries by land and by see;
I had no peere yf to my selfe I were trew,
Because I am not so diuers times I do rew;
Yet I lake nothing, I haue all thyng at wyll
If were wyse and wold holde my selfe styll,
And medel wyth no matters not to me partayning;
But I haue suche matters rolling in my pate,
That I wyl speake and do I cannot tell what.” etc.

—Knapp

↩

See Muses’ Library, pp. 86, 87. London, 1738. [Better, the original ed. (1547).

—Knapp

] ↩

Genteel with them seems to be synonymous with Gentile and Gentoo; if so, the manner in which it has been applied for ages ceases to surprise, for genteel is heathenish. Ideas of barbaric pearl and gold, glittering armour, plumes, tortures, blood-shedding, and lust, should always be connected with it. Wace, in his grand Norman poem, calls the Baron Genteel:—

“La furent li gentil Baron,” etc.

And he certainly could not have applied the word better than to the strong Norman thief, armed cap-a-pie without one particle of ruth or generosity; for a person to be a pink of gentility, that is heathenism, should have no such feelings; and, indeed, the admirers of gentility seldom or never associate any such feelings with it. It was from the Norman, the worst of all robbers and miscreants, who built strong castles, garrisoned them with devils, and tore out poor wretches’ eyes, as the Saxon Chronicle says, that the English got their detestable word genteel. What could ever have made the English such admirers of gentility, it would be difficult to say; for, during three hundred years, they suffered enough by it. Their genteel Norman landlords were their scourgers, their torturers, the plunderers of their homes, the dishonourers of their wives, and the deflowerers of their daughters. Perhaps after all, fear is at the root of the English veneration for gentility. ↩

Mr. Flamson: Samuel Morton Peto, M.P., later Sir Morton Peto of Somerleyton Hall, some five miles inland from Lowestoft. See Life, II, p. 52.

—Knapp

↩

Gentle and gentlemanly may be derived from the same root as genteel; but nothing can be more distinct from the mere genteel, than the ideas which enlightened minds associate with these words. Gentle and gentlemanly mean something kind and genial; genteel, that which is glittering or gaudy. A person can be a gentleman in rags, but nobody can be genteel. ↩

Orcadian poet: “Ragnvald, Earl of the Orkney Islands, passed for a very able poet; he boasts himself, in a song of his which is still extant, that he knew how to compose verses on all subjects,” Mallet, [Northern Antiquities] p. 235. The original Runic of the lines translated by Borrow is found in Olaus Wormius. Transliterated into Latin letters they read thus:—

Tafl em eg or at efta
Idrottir kan eg niu
Tum eg tradla Runur
Tid er mer bog og smider
Skrid kann eg a gidum
Skot eg og re so nyter
Hvor tweggia kan ek hyggiu
Harpslatt og bragdattu.

—Knapp

↩

Lieut. P⸺, read “Perry.” The item was taken from a newspaper (which, I know not) published in September, 1854. Mr. Borrow read it at Llangollen in Wales. I loaned the clipping and it was not returned.

—Knapp

↩

Balaklava: The usual etymon of this famous name is the Italian Bella chiave, beautiful key.

—Knapp

↩

Companion of Bligh: This was Thomas Hayward.

—Knapp

↩

Once: See Bligh’s Narrative (A Narrative of the Mutiny on board His Majesty’s Ship Bounty; and the subsequent voyage of part of the crew, in the ship’s boat, from Tofoa, one of the Friendly Islands, to Timor, a Dutch settlement in the East Indies. Written by Lieutenant William Bligh. London, 1790.), p. 55.—336.

—Knapp

↩

“Malditas sean tus tripas,” etc.: This Borrovian Spanish must be rendered truthfully or not at all. The squeamish may excuse the borracha: “D⸺ your g⸺s; we had enough of the stink of your g⸺s the day you ran away from the battle of the Boyne.”

—Knapp

↩

Coronach (Gaelic), read “Corránach:” The funeral wail, a dirge; in Irish, coránach.

—Knapp

↩

The writer has been checked in print by the Scotch with being a Norfolk man. Surely, surely, these latter times have not been exactly the ones in which it was expedient for Scotchmen to check the children of any county in England with the place of their birth, more especially those who have had the honour of being born in Norfolk—times in which British fleets, commanded by Scotchmen, have returned laden with anything but laurels from foreign shores. It would have been well for Britain had she had the old Norfolk man to despatch to the Baltic or the Black Sea, lately, instead of Scotch admirals. ↩

Abencerages, read “Abencerrages:” Arabic ibn-serradj; son of the saddle.

—Knapp

↩

Whiffler: An official character of the old Norwich Corporation, strangely uniformed and accoutred, who headed the annual procession on Guildhall day, flourishing a sword in a marvellous manner. All this was abolished on the passage of the Municipal Reform Act in 1835. As a consequence, says a contemporaneous writer, “the Aldermen left off wearing their scarlet gowns, Snap was laid up on a shelf in the ‘Sword Room’ in the Guildhall, and the Whifflers no longer danced at the head of the procession in their picturesque costume. It was a pretty sight, and their skill in flourishing their short swords was marvellous to behold.”

—Knapp

↩

Francis Spira: Francesco Spiera, a lawyer of Cittadella (Venice), accepted the doctrines of the Reformation in 1548. Terrified by the menaces of the Church of Rome and the prospective ruin of his family, he went to Venice and solemnly abjured the Evangelical faith in the hands of the Legate, Giovan della Casa (see Dict. de Bayle) who required him to return home and repeat his abjuration before his fellow-townsmen and the local authorities. Having performed this act, he fell into the horrid state of remorse depicted in the Protestant accounts of the time. The report was first brought to Geneva by Pietro Paolo Vergerio, ex-bishop of Pola, who visited Spiera in his last moments at Padua, whence he himself bent his way to the Valtelina, as a fugitive from the Roman Church.

—Knapp

↩

Duncan Campbell: History of the Life and Adventures of Mr. Duncan Campbell, a gentleman who, though deaf and dumb, writes down any strangers’ name at first sight, with their future contingencies of fortune; now living in Exeter Court, over against the Savoy in the Strand. By Daniel Defoe.

—Knapp

↩

Falconer, The Voyages, dangerous Adventures and imminent escapes of Captain Richard Falconer … intermix’d with the Voyages … of T. Randal. London, 1720.

—Knapp

↩

John Randall: Here is a confusion of John Rolfe and John Randolph of Roanoke (1773–1833). Pocahontas, daughter of the Indian Chief Powhatan, saved the life of Captain John Smith in Virginia and married John Rolfe in 1614. John Randolph of Roanoke claimed to be descended from Pocahontas, but Rolfe is evidently the one referred to in the text.

See The Indian Princess; or, the Story of Pocahontas. By Edward Eggleston and Lillie Eggleston Seelye. London (1880?).

—Knapp

↩

Iriarte (1750–96): Spanish poet and writer of fables. See Coleccion de Obras en Verso y Prosa de D. Tomas de Yriarte. Madrid, 1787.

—Knapp

↩

Autobiographical character of Lavengro denied: but see Life, II, pp. 3–27 and 211.

—Knapp

↩

Ginnúngagap: The “yawning abyss” of Northern Mythology. See Mallet, Northern Antiquities p. 402.

—Knapp

↩

Horinger Bay: Hjörúnga Vâgr in Icelandic, or Vaag in Danish.

—Knapp

↩

Harum-beck, read “harmanbeck,” as in Lavengro.

—Knapp

↩

Holkham Estate: The seat of the Cokes of Norfolk and the Earl of Leicester. See White’s Norfolk.

—Knapp

↩

He said in ’32: See Life, I, p. 143.

—Knapp

↩

Son of Norfolk clergyman: Nelson (nom de noms!).

—Knapp

↩

As the present work will come out in the midst of a vehement political contest, people may be led to suppose that the above was written expressly for the time. The writer therefore begs to state that it was written in the year 1854. He cannot help adding that he is neither Whig, Tory, nor Radical, and cares not a straw what party governs England, provided it is governed well. But he has no hopes of good government from the Whigs. It is true that amongst them there is one very great man, Lord Palmerston, who is indeed the sword and buckler, the chariots and the horses of the party; but it is impossible for his lordship to govern well with such colleagues as he has—colleagues which have been forced upon him by family influence, and who are continually pestering him into measures anything but conducive to the country’s honour and interest. If Palmerston would govern well, he must get rid of them; but from that step, with all his courage and all his greatness, he will shrink. Yet how proper and easy a step it would be! He could easily get better, but scarcely worse, associates. They appear to have one object in view and only one—jobbery. It was chiefly owing to a most flagitious piece of jobbery, which one of his lordship’s principal colleagues sanctioned and promoted, that his lordship experienced his late parliamentary disasters. ↩

Thistlewood and Ings: See article in Celebrated Lives and Trials, volume VI, p. 339.

—Knapp

↩

The old Radical: John Bowring in 1821.

—Knapp

↩

Volume of translations: See Specimen of the Russian Poets: With Preliminary Remarks and Biographical Notices. By John Bowring, F.L.S. London: Whittaker, 1821.

—Knapp

↩

Red Rhys: Rhys Goch of Snowdon. See Wild Wales, p. 150, and Neu Flodau Godidowgrwydd Awen. O gasgliad Rhys Jones, o’r Tyddyn Mawr. [Beauties of the Bards of Wales; or, Flowers of Welsh Poetry. Collected by Rhys Jones of Great Farms] Amwythig (Shrewsbury), 1773.

—Knapp

↩

A fact. ↩

The Doctor of Medicine: Dr. Lewis Evans. See Life, I, p. 74.

—Knapp

↩

S⸺, read “Southey.”

—Knapp

↩

Literary project (1829–30): See Life, I, p. 129.

—Knapp

↩

Astolfo: His journey to the moon mentioned in Pulci, ed. 1546, Canto XXI, f. cxx b:

“Malagigi tagliava le parole,
Astolfo sopra ’l suo caval rimonta;
Cavalcano à la luna tanto e al sole
Che capitorno al castel di Creonta.”

—Knapp

↩

MS. “Aberdeen.”

—Knapp

↩

MS. “Aberdeen.”

—Knapp

↩

In ⸻, read “China.”

—Knapp

↩

To ⸻, read “China.”

—Knapp

↩

Copy of a work: Borrow’s edition of the Manchu New Testament, St. Petersburg, 1835. All the dashes mean Canton or China.

—Knapp

↩

Serendib: (Ceylon) put for China.

—Knapp

↩

Boxiana—Fights for the Championship, and Celebrated Prize Battles, from the Days of Figg and Broughton to the Present Time. London, 1855, II, 497.

—Knapp

↩

The change from Ambrose to Jasper was made in pencil in Mrs. Borrow’s transcript at the last moment in 1849, before handing it to the printers.

—Knapp

↩

Beginning—

Mas tinn no slán atharlaigheas féin,
Do ghluàis me trá, agus bfhéirde mé,
Air cuáirt an Seóin le sócal dfhághail,
“An Stafartach saímh, nach gnáth gan chéill.”

—Knapp

↩

“El qual (Noé) despues del diluuio, por su inuencion del uino, fue lhamado lano, porque Ianin en ebràico quiere dezir uino, y lo pintan con dos caras boltadas, porque tuuo uista antes del diluuio y despues” (Foja 71, verso).

—Knapp

↩

Like Ingilis in Turkish, for English; Beritania (England) in Hawaiian, for Britannia.

—Knapp

↩

Zincali, 1843, second ed., volume II, p. 146.

—Knapp

↩

“I think I’ll go there,” p. 301. “He is about to quit his native land on a grand philological expedition,” p. 303.

—Knapp

↩

Canning: Premier from 24th April to his death, 8th August, 1827; succeeded by Viscount Goderich from September, 1827, to 25th January, 1828.—312.

—Knapp

↩

Luigi Pulci: Io vo’ tagliar, etc.: I’ll sever the hands of them all and bring them to those holy monks.

—Knapp

↩

Tu sarai or perfetto, etc.: Now thou wilt be as true a friend to Christ as aforetime thou wert his foe (Morgante Maggiore di Luigi Pulci Firentino, etc. Venetia, 1546, canto I, stanzas 53 and 57).

—Knapp

↩

Carajo: An oath fit neither to be written nor pronounced, but common to the lower classes of Spaniards, or to ambitious foreign Hispanophiles who cannot know its meaning. See Oudin’s Tesoro, Paris, 1607.

—Knapp

↩

Glossary

A

Abdalrahman

(Ab-dal-rahˈman), founder of the independent Ommiad (Saracenic) power in Spain, conquered at Tours by Charles Martel.

LIST OF GYPSY WORDS IN LAVENGRO

Adrey, in.

Ambról, pear.

Andé, in, into.

André, in, within.

Angár, charcoal, coals.

Apopli, again.

Aukko, here is.

Ava, yes.

Ávali, yes.

Avella, comes, is coming.

Baró, large, big.

Bawlor, swine.

Bebee (aunt), grandmother.

Bengui, devil.

Bitchadey, pl. sent.

Bitchadey pawdel (p. 300), an error for bitchadó pawdel, sing.

Boró, great.

Borodromengro, highwayman.

Boro foros, London.

Cafi, horse-shoe nail.

Cana, when.

Caulor, shillings.

Chabé, pl. of

Chabó, child, lad, Gypsy.

Chachipen, truth.

Chal, lad, Gypsy.

Chal Devlehi, go with God, farewell.

Chavó, i.q. chabó.

Chi, girl, lass, Gypsy.

Chinomescro, chisel.

Chipes, pl. tongues.

Chive, to throw; pass (bad money).

Chivios, he or it is cast.

Chong, hill.

Chong gav, Norwich.

Churi, knife.

Coor, to strike, hammer.

Cooromengro, boxer.

Covantza, anvil.

Dearginni (Hung. G.), it thunders.

Dinelo, a fool, silly.

Divvus, day.

Dloovu, money (for lovo).

Dook, to bewitch, to spirit away.

Dook, spirit, soul, divining spirit, demon, ghost.

Dosta, enough.

Dovey odoi, that there, up yonder.

Drab, herb, poison.

Drab, to poison.

Drom, road, way.

Drow (often pl.), drugs; poison.

Dui, two.

Dukkerin (the in is Eng. “ing”), any one’s fortune, or fortunes, fate, fortune-telling.

Dukkerindook, the fortune-telling or divining spirit or demon.

Dukkeripen, fortune-telling.

Duvel, God.

Duvelskoe, divine.

Engro (mere ending), Borrovian for “master,” “fellow,” “chap”.

Foros, city, town.

Gav, village, town.

Gillie, song, ditty.

Gorgio, non-gypsy, stranger, somebody, police. G. avella, some one is coming. G. shunella, some one is listening. G.’s welling, the police are about.

Gorgious, adj. formed from gorgio.

Grandbabee, see bebee.

Grondinni (Roumanian G.), it hails.

Gry, horse, pony.

Harkomescro, tinker.

Hinjiri, executioner.

Hir mi Devlis, by my G—.

Hokkeripen, falsehood.

Jaw, to go. Jaw-ing, going.

Jib, tongue, language.

Juggal, dog.

Juwa, woman.

Kauley, f. of

Kaulo, black, dark.

Kaulomescro, blacksmith.

Kaured, stole.

Kekaubi, kettle.

Ker, house.

Kosko, good.

Kral or Krallis, king.

Lachipen, honesty.

Lavengro, “word-master,” “philologist”.

Leste, him.

Lil, book.

Loovu, coin, money.

Lundra, London.

Luripen, theft, robbery.

Mailla, donkey.

Manricli, cake.

Manro, bread.

Manus, man.

Marel (read merel), dies.

Men, we.

Mensar (read mensa), with us.

Miro, my.

Morro, bread.

Muchtar, tool-box.

Nashkado, lost, hanged.

Nashky, gallows.

O, the.

Odoi, there; dovey o., yonder.

Pa, over, for.

Pal, brother, friend, mate.

Palor, brothers.

Parraco, I thank.

Pawdel, on the other side, across; bitchadey p., transported.

Pen, to say, to tell; penning, telling.

Peshota, pl. bellows.

Petul, horse-shoe.

Petulengro, smith.

Pindro, hoof, foot.

Pios, health (in toasting).

Plaistra, pincers.

Plastramengro, runner, detective.

Poknees, magistrate.

Prala (voc.). brother.

Pudamengro, blower, bellows.

Puró, old, ancient.

Puv, earth, ground.

Ran, stick, cane.

Rati, blood, stock.

Rikkení, f. of

Rikkenó, pretty, fine.

Rin, file.

Rom, husband; Gypsy.

Roman, Borrovian for Gypsy.

Romaneskoenæs, in Gypsy fashion.

Romanly (Bor.), in Gypsy, G.-like.

Romanó, Gypsy.

Rome and dree (Rom andré?) Gypsy at heart.

Romí, wife.

Rommanis, in Gypsy.

Rommany, Gypsy.

Rommany Chal, Eng. Gypsy.

Rommany Chi, f. Eng. Gypsy-girl.

Rovel, weeps.

Rye, gentleman; farming r., farmer.

Sap, snake.

Sapengro, snake-catcher.

Sastra, iron.

Sastramescro, worker in iron, smith.

Scoppelo, ninny.

Sherengro, head man.

Shoon, to hear, to listen.

Shukaro, hammer.

Shunella, is listening.

Si, is, are.

Sore, all (who).

Ta, and.

Tacho rommanis, faithful wife.

Tan, tent.

Tasaulor (ta-sorlo), to-morrow.

Tatchipen, truth.

Tawno Chickno, “Shorty”.

Tu, thy.

Tute, thee.

Vagescoe chipes, tongues of fire.

Villaminni (Hung. G.), it lightens.

Wafodo, bad, false.

Welling (corruption of avella), coming. G.’s welling, “the hawks are abroad”.

Wesh, forest.

Yag, fire.

Yeck, one.

Zigañ (Slavic), Gypsy.

Zingaro (Italian), Gypsy.

COMPLETE LIST OF ENG. GYPSY WORDS SCATTERED THROUGH LAVENGRO AND ROMANY RYE.

Common European G. forms are in parenthesis.

Abri (avrí), out, forth.

Adré / Adrey } (andré), in, into.

Ambról, a pear.

Andé, in, into.

Angár, charcoal, coal.

Apopli, again, once more.

Ankko (aveká), here is.

Ava / Ávali } yes.

Avella (3rd sing. of aváva), he comes; gorgio a., some one is coming. [Avava, avesa, avela.]

Ballúva (baló), pork.

Baló, hog.

Baró, f. barí, pl. baré, big, great.

Bátu, father.

Baulo, see baló.

Bawlor (pl. of baló), swine.

Bebee (bibí), aunt; (in G. B. grandmother, with and without grand).

Beng, toad; dragon, devil.

Bengui (Sp. G. bengue), i.q. beng.

Besh (beshava), to sit.

Beti, a little, a bit of.

Bitchadey (bichavdé; pl. of bichavdó), sent. With pawdel, transported.

Bokht (bakht), fate, luck, fortune.

Boró, see baró.

Borodromengro, highwayman.

Boshom (bashava, I sing or play), violin, fiddle.

Boshomengro, fiddler.

Bovaló (barvaló), rich.

Bute (but), much. B. dosta, a good many, plenty of.

Cafi (καρφἱ), horse-shoe nail.

Caloró, f, a Spanish Gypsy. Dim. of caló; see kaló.

Cambrí (kamní), with child.

Camomescro (fr. kamama, I love), a Lovell (Gypsy tribe-name).

Cana (kánna), when.

Caulor (collor, L.L.), pl. shillings.

Chabé, pl. of Chabó.

Chabó (tchavó), child, lad; Gypsy.

Chachipen (tchatchipé), truth.

Chal (chabál or chavál, still existant in Spain), lad; Gypsy. Romany ch., Gypsy; R. chi, Gypsy (lass).

Chal (for jal, from java). Ch. Devléhi (ja Devlésa), go with God, farewell.

Chavó, i.q. chabó.

Chi (tchái), girl, lass, child; Gypsy.

Chibándo (Sp. G., see chive), tossing; preaching (a sermon).

Chick (tchik), dirt, mud.

Chie, i.q. chi.

Chiknó (tiknó), a youth. Tawno Ch., “Shorty”.

Chinomescro (from tchinava, I cut), chisel, parer.

Chipe (tchip), tongue.

Chive (tchivava), to throw; to pass (false coin).

Chívios, is cast (he).

Chong (tumba), hill. Ch. gav, Norwich, town of the Castle hill.

Choomer (tchumi), a kiss.

Chore (tchorava), to steal.

Chories, thieves.

Chovahanee (tchovekhaní), a witch.

Chovahanó (tchovekhanó), a wizard.

Churi (tchorí), knife.

Coin (kon), who?

Coko (káko), uncle.

Colikó (kalikó, Sp. G. calicaste, on the morrow), on the morrow, in the morning (B.’s “early” is a mistake).

Coor (curava, I strike), to strike, to hammer.

Cooromengro, boxer.

Covántza, anvil.

Covar (ková), a thing.

Cral / Crállis } (krális), king

Cukkerin (merely alliterative with dukkerin).

Curomengro, boxer.

Czigány (Hung.), Gypsy—(tsigáñ).

Dearginni (Hung., dörŏg, thunder; dörgeni, to th.), it thunders.

Dick (dikava), to see.

Dinelo (deniló or diniló), a fool.

Divvus (divés), day.

Dloovu (error for lovó).

Dook (Slavic), spirit, soul, divining spirit, demon, ghost. Russ. dux.

Dook, to spirit away, to bewitch.

Dosta, enough.

Dove odoy (fr. odová), that there; up yonder.

Drab, herb, drug; poison, see drow.

Drab, to poison.

Drabengro, seller of medicines, apothecary. D. ker, apothecary’s shop.

Drom (δρόμος), road, way.

Drow, i.q. drab; often pl. drugs; poison.

Dúi, two.

Duk (B.’s dook).

Dukker (fr. duk, spirit or demon, and ker, to make, to evoke), to tell any one’s fortune, to tell fortunes.

Dukkerin (the in is Eng. ing), any one’s fortune or fortunes, fate; fortune-telling. “To pen” a dukkerin is incorrect.

Dukkerin dook, the fortune-telling or divining spirit.

Dukkeripen, fortune-telling.

Dumo (dumó), the back.

Duvel (devél), God.

Duvelskoe (devlesko), divine.

Dye (daï), mother.

Engro (a mere adj. ending, er, ing), Borrovian for “master,” “fellow,” “chap”.

Erajái (rashaï), priest, in Sp. Gyp.

Eray, see rye.

Farm-engro, farmer.

Fino, Eng. fine.

Fóros (φόρος = ἀγορά), city, town.

Gav, village, town.

Gil, to sing.

Gillie (ghili), song, ditty.

Gitáno, a (Sp.) Gypsy.

Gorgikie, f. of.

Gorgiko, f, non-gypsy.

Gorgio (gadjó), non-gypsy, stranger, somebody, policeman.

Gorgious, adj. formed from gorgio.

Grandbebee, grandmother. See bebee.

Grasní, mare; jade.

Grondinni (fr. Roumanian), it hails.

Gry (graï), horse. Pellengo g., stallion.

Gudló, í, sweet; g. pesham, honeycomb.

Gul eray (Hung. G.?), sweet gentleman.

Habben (khabé, fr. khavava, I eat), food, victuals; feast.

Harkomescro (arkíchi, tin), tinker.

Hatch, to cook (evidently fr. pekava, rather than atchava).

Hinjirí (f. of hinjiró, fr. djandjir, a chain), executioner.

Hir mi devlis (or diblis), by G—.

Hokkawar (khokhavava), to lie, to cheat.

Hokkeripen, falsehood, deception.

Hors-worth, pennyworth. (Hors, fr. grosch?)

Iuziou (shuzó), clean.

Jaw (java), to go. See chal.

Jawing, going.

Jib (chib) tongue, language.

Juggal (jukél), dog.

Juva / Juwa } (young) woman.

Kair, see ker.

Kairdó, see Kerdó.

Kaló, f. kalí, pl. kalé, black, dark.

Kauley, f. of kaulo.

Kaulo, see kaló.

Kaulomescro, blacksmith.

Ke, to.

Kek, none.

Kekaubi / Kekkauvi } (kakkávi), kettle.

Kekauviskoe saster, kettle iron or hook.

Kekkaubi, see kekaubi.

Kekkenó, no, not one.

Ker, house.

Ker (kerava), to make, to do.

Kerdó, made (he).

Kil (kelava), to play.

Kin (kinava), to buy.

Kistur (klisava), to ride.

Kitchema, tavern, ale-house.

Kosko, i, good.

Kral / Krallis } king, see cral.

Lachipen, goodness.

Laki / Lakie } (lake), her, to her.

Lavengro, “word-master,” “philologist”.

Lel (lava, lesa, lela), to take; to buy.

Len, i.q. lende.

Lende, their, to them.

Leste, him.

Levinor (levina), ale.

Lil, paper, book.

Lirí, law.

Lis, it.

Lolló (loló), red.

Loovu, see

Lovó, coin; pl. lové, money.

Lubbeny (lubní), harlot.

Lundra, London.

Luripen, theft, robbery.

Mailla, donkey.

Man, me.

Mande, to me.

Mang (mangava), to beg.

Manriclí (manrikló), cake.

Manró, bread.

Manus (manush), man.

Marél (error for merel): merava, meresa, merela—he dies.

Mek (mukava), to leave, to let; mek lis, drop it.

Men, we.

Mensar (mensa), with us.

Mer (merava), to die.

Mi (me), I.

Miduveleskoe lil, divine or godly book.

Miró, f, my, mine.

Miry (mirí), my.

Morro, bread.

Muchtar (muktar), box, tool-box.

Mullo (muló), dead.

Nashkadó, í (nashavdó), lost, ruined; hanged (G. B.).

Nashky, gallows (G. B.).

Nav, name.

O, the.

Odoi / Odoy } there, here.

Opré, on, upon, up.

Pa, over, for.

Pal (pral), brother; friend, mate.

Palor (pralá), brothers.

Parraco (L.L. paracrow; Zinc. parauco), I thank.

Patteran (patrín), leaf of a tree, Gypsy trail.

Pawdel (perdál), on the other side, across.

Pellengo (pelengro, fr. pelé, testicles), with gry, a stallion.

Pen (penava), to say, to tell.

Peshotá, pl. of peshót (pishót), bellows.

Petúl (pétalo), horse-shoe.

Petulengro, head of the clan “Smith”.

Pindró (pinró), foot, hoof.

Pios (fr. piava, I drink), health, in toasting.

Piramus, MS. Priamus.

Plaistra (klashta), pincers, tongs.

Plastramengro, runner, detective.

Poggadó, í (panghiardó), broken.

Poknees (paknís, a man of trust), magistrate.

Prala, voc. of pal or pral, brother.

Pré (opré), on, upon.

Pudamengro (fr. purdava or pudava, I blow), bellows.

Puró, f. purí, pl. puré, old, ancient.

Pus, straw.

Puv (or phuv) earth, ground.

Ran, stick, rod, cane.

Ráni, lady, wife.

Rarde (ratt), night.

Rat, rate and rati, blood, race.

Rawnie, see ráni.

Rig (?) to carry.

Rikkeno, see rinkenó.

Rin, a file.

Rinkenó, í, pretty, fine.

Rom, husband; Gypsy.

Roman, Borrovian tor Gypsy.

Romaneskoenaes, in Gypsy fashion.

Romanies, Gypsies.

Romanly, in Gypsy, Gypsy-like.

Romanó, í, Gypsy.

Romany (Anglicised form of Romanó, í), Gypsy.

Romany Chal, Gypsy.

Romany Chi, Gypsy (girl).

Romany Rye, Gypsy gentleman.

Rome and dree (Rom andré? Gypsy at heart).

Romí, wife.

Rommanis, in Gypsy, also wife (G. B.).

Rommany, i.q. Romany.

Rovél (3rd sing. of rovava), he weeps.

Rup, silver.

Rye (ráï), gentleman.

Sanpriel, Sanspareil.

Sap, snake.

Sapengro, snake-catcher.

Sar shan, how art thou?

Sas, it was, were it.

Saster / Sastra } iron.

Sastramescro, worker in iron, smith.

Saulo (MS. sorlo), morning; early (?)

Savó, what kind of a man? who?

Scoppelo, ninny.

Se (isi), is, are.

Shan (isán), thou art.

Sherengro (fr. sheró, the head), head man, chief.

Shom (isóm), I am.

Shoon (shunava), to hear, to listen.

Shukaro (tchokanó), hammer.

Shunella (shunéla, 3rd sing. of shunava), is listening.

Si (isí), is, are; si men, are we; si mensar (mensa), is or are with us.

Sinaba (Sp. G.), was.

Sore (saré), pl. all, all who.

Sos, who.

Sos (isás), was.

Sove (sovava), to sleep.

Swety (pl. of Russ. sviet), people, folks.

Synfye, Cinthia (Slav. th is pron. ph).

Ta, and.

Tachó, í, true.

Tan, place, tent.

Tasaulor (read ta-sorlo), to-morrow.

Tatchenó, í, modest, chaste.

Tatchipen, truth.

Tawnie, f. of

Tawnó, í. (tarnó), little, short.

Tove (tovava), to wash.

Trin, three.

Truppo (trupo), body.

Tu, thou.

Tute (tut), thee, to thy.

Vagescoe, adj. of yag.

Vassavie, f. of.

Vassavó, í, vile.

Villaminni (Hung. villám), it lightens.

Wafodo, i, bad, raise.

Wel (corrupted from avella), to come, to go.

Welling, coming.

Wendror (connected with andró, within?), the insides.

Wesh (vesh), forest.

Wust, to throw (better the first MS. form, chiv).

Yag, fire.

Ye, the.

Yeck (yek), one.

Yov (ov), be.

Zigeuner (Ger.), Gypsy.

Zingaro (It.), Gypsy.